<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>tartley.com</title><link>https://tartley.com/</link><description>Creating a website devoted to oneself has been described as the greatest act of hubris. Welcome aboard!</description><atom:link href="https://www.tartley.com/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2022 &lt;a href="mailto:tartley @ the domain tartley dot com"&gt;Jonathan Hartley&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Sat, 09 Jul 2022 17:42:07 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>US Civics for Naturalization Quiz</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/basic-us-civics/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;I had to learn 100 questions and answers for my US Naturalization civics
quiz this week, and my default way of learning something is to organize the information
into an essay. Not the best work I've ever done, but it got me through the test, so
good enough:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;History&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The region now occupied by the US was originally settled by Native Americans,
probably travelling from the Far East, around 15,000 years ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Modern Native tribes include Apache, Arawak, Blackfeet, Cherokee, Cheyenne,
Chippewa, Choctaw, Creek, Crow, Hopi, Huron, Inuit, Iroquois, Lakota, Mohegan,
Navajo, Oneida, Pueblo, Seminole, Shawnee, Sioux, and Teton.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;European colonists came to America to escape persecution, in pursuit of religious
and political freedom, and economic opportunity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Atlantic slave trade took Africans to the American colonies as slaves. This
practice was widespread by the time of the American Revolution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The colonists decided to fight for freedom from British rule because:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They didn't want to pay high taxes to the British government without representation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They did not like the British army being quartered in their houses.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They wanted self-government.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By the time of the declaration of independence, there were thirteen colonies that
became the initial thirteen United States:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Connecticut&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Delaware&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Georgia&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Maryland&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Massachusetts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;New Hampshire&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;New Jersey&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;New York&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;North Carolina&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pennsylvania&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rhode Island&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;South Carolina&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Virginia&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These States fought the American Revolutionary War against Great Britain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 1803 (27 years after the declaration of independence), the United States
bought the Louisiana territory from France.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Founding&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Declaration of Independence&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;Declaration of Independence&lt;/em&gt; declared the United States to be independent
of, and free from, the rule of Great Britain. It was written by Thomas
Jefferson, and adopted on July 4th, 1776.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It notes the right of all men to enjoy life, liberty and the pursuit of
happiness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The American Constitution&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The supreme law of the land is the &lt;em&gt;constitution&lt;/em&gt;. It sets up and defines the
government, and also enumerates the basic rights of American citizens and
residents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The idea of self-government is represented in the constitution's first three
words: "&lt;em&gt;We the people...&lt;/em&gt;".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The constitution was written at the &lt;em&gt;constitutional convention&lt;/em&gt; of 1787, by
the &lt;em&gt;Founding Fathers&lt;/em&gt;. Its passage was supported by the Federalist Papers,
written by James Madison, Alexander Hamilton, and John Jay, under the pseudonym
"&lt;em&gt;Publius&lt;/em&gt;", after &lt;em&gt;Publius Valerius Poplicola&lt;/em&gt;, a Roman aristocrat who led the
overthrow of the monarchy to found the Roman Republic in 509 BC.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Benjamin Franklin is known as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Oldest member of the constitutional convention,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The first Postmaster General of the United States,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Writer of "Poor Richard's Almanac",&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Starter of the first free libraries,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A US diplomat.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;George Washington is known as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The first President&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The "Father of our Country"&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The original text of the constitution has since been modified by twenty-seven
&lt;em&gt;amendments&lt;/em&gt;, each of which is numbered, and takes the form of an addition to
the existing text.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Rights and Responsibilities&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first ten amendments are known as &lt;em&gt;"the Bill of Rights"&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first amendment prohibits the government from infringing on the right of
residents in the US to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Establish or practice any religion, or no religion at all.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Free speech.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Freedom of the press.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Peaceably assemble.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Petition the government for a redress of grievances.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The final four items above are together known as "freedom of expression".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition, the constitution establishes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The right to bear arms.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;US citizens are granted additional rights that do not apply to all residents,
including:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Running for federal office&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Voting in federal elections&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And US citizens are additionally assigned responsibilities:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jury service&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Voting in federal elections&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Voting in federal elections is thus established as both a right and a
responsibility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The pledge of allegiance declares loyalty to the US flag and the United States.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ways for citizens to participate in their democracy include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Voting&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Join a political party&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Help with a political campaign&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Join a civic or community group&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Give opinions to elected officials, such as calling Senators or Representatives.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Publicly support or oppose an issue or policy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Run for office&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Write to a newspaper&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When becoming a naturalized US citizen, the oath of allegiance declares one will:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Give up loyalty to other countries&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Be loyal to the United States&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Obey the laws of the United States&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Defend the constitution and laws of the United States&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Serve in the US military (if the law demands it)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Serve civil projects for the nation (if the law demands it)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All men resident in the USA must register for &lt;em&gt;selective service&lt;/em&gt; (a list from which
draftees are chosen should the need arise) between the ages of 18 and 26.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last day to submit federal income tax forms is April 15th.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Voting rights&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The enfranchisement and disenfranchisement of different groups has been a
moral and political issue throughout United States history.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The original constitution did not explicitly specify who was able to vote,
and states demonstrated considerable diversity in whom they did or did not grant
suffrage. In particular, most states only granted the vote to white, male,
property owners - about 6% of the population.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the 1820s, attitudes and state laws shifted, to allow all white males to
vote in most states, although some laws removing the poor's right to vote
continued until the 20th century, and practices that disproportionately
affect the poor's ability to vote continue today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several constitutional amendments successively modified who can vote,
notably:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The 15th Amendment of 1870, in the wake of the Civil War and Emancipation
  Proclamation, prevented the denial of voting rights based on a person's race.
  This was effectively interpreted to mean that men of any race could vote.
  However, states continued to prevent the majority of African Americans in the
  United States from voting, via Jim Crow laws, poll taxes, literacy tests,
  grandfather clauses and the like. Only later in the 20th century were these
  laws ruled unconstitutional.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The 19th Amendment of 1920 allowed women to vote. However, in practice, women
  — who were rarely in control of independent sources of income —
  were usually still prevented from voting by the same discriminatory practices
  that prevented voting by poor or non-white men.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The 24th amendment of 1964 prohibited using a poll tax to control who could
  vote in federal elections.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The 26th amendment of 1971 lowered the voting age from 21 to 18. This was
  passed in response to Vietnam War protest, which noted that if draftees were
  considered old enough to be sent to fight, they should also be old enough to
  vote.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following section was not part of the USCIS civics test. But I'm including it
because it's clear that although the Declaration asserted "all men are created
equal", subsequent laws and behavior has severely curtailed that assertion when it
comes to issues such as being allowed to vote. So, who currently is, and is
not, allowed to vote? Sometimes the best way to understand something is to
trace its contours, by enumerating the exceptions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those who are currently legally denied the right to vote, for reasons that I
personally find arguably understandable, are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Those aged under 18.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Those deemed mentally "incapacitated" or "incompetent" by a conservatorship
  process.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Illegal or undocumented immigrants (16 million people).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following people are also legally denied the vote, for reasons that I personally
find controversial or outright wrong:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;US Citizens and nationals who reside in the United States territories that are
  not States, such as Puerto Rico.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Washington DC residents (718,000 people) have had the right to vote in
  presidential elections since 1961, but no congressional elections have been
  held there since 1801.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Non-citizen residents of the United States such as myself (13 million
  people). This includes legal aliens in good standing, such as foreign
  spouses, asylum claimants and refugees, who might reside within the US,
  paying taxes, for years or decades. Contrast this with the United Kingdom,
  for example, where people in the similar category "with leave to remain" &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt;
  able to vote.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The homeless (580,000 people) are often excluded from voting by residency
  requirements, or by the inability to register without a mailing address or proof
  of identity.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Current prisoners, in almost all states (5.5 million people). Some states
  impose a lifelong denial of voting rights to anyone with a previous felony
  record, which affects another 5.9 million people.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;US Citizens who have never established residence in the United States may be
  denied the vote by various states.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The above categories represent 28.8 million people, around 11 percent of
the adult population, who currently have no legal right to vote for US government
positions due to reasons I personally find controversial or wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Civil Rights&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Susan B Anthony was a prominent activist for womens rights and civil rights.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Martin Luther King Jr. fought for civil rights, to try and provide equality for
Americans of all races.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Wars&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The United States has waged many wars, including:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;18th Century Wars&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;American Revolutionary War to free America from British rule.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cherokee-American wars&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Northwest Indian War&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Quasi-War (a naval war, allied with Britain, against France &amp;amp; Guadeloupe)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;19th Century Wars&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;56 official wars, mostly resulting in the genocide or internment of various
indigenous Native American nations. Sometimes the United States was allied with
or fighting against Great Britain, and sometimes on the soil of other foes such
as the Ottoman Empire and Morocco, China, Mexico, Spanish Florida, the
Philippines, Cuba, Puerto Rico, or Guam. Notable among these wars were:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The War of 1812 against Great Britain&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Mexican-American war, in the disputed former Mexican territories of
  Texas, New Mexico, California and regions of Mexico.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The American Civil War.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Spanish-American war.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;The Civil War&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The American Civil War of 1861 to 1865 was fought between the United States and
the Confederacy of Southern States, over the issues of whether slavery was to
remain legal in the Southern States, upon which many southern white livelihoods
and businesses depended. This is sometimes framed as an academic disagreement about
"States Rights" to self-government, but I personally find it hard to interpret
that as anything other than a disingenuous fig leaf.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abraham Lincoln lead the Northern states to victory in the Civil War, and is praised
for saving or preserving the Union. He presided over the Emancipation
Proclamation which ostensibly freed the slaves, although many still suffer from
ongoing repercussions and outright racism even up to the present day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;20th Century Wars&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;31 official wars, some against outstanding Native American nations, others in
diverse locations such as Cuba, Nicaragua, Haiti, Dominican Republic, Russia,
Mongolia, Korea, Vietnam, Laos, Lebanon, Cambodia, Grenada, Libya, Iran &amp;amp;
Persian Gulf, Panama, Iraq, Kuwait, Saudi Arabia, Israel, Somalia, Bosnia,
Herzegovina, Croatia, Haiti, and Serbia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Notable amongst these were:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;World War I, during which the president was Woodrow Wilson.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;World War II, against Germany, Japan and Italy, during which the president
  was Franklin D. Roosevelt. Eisenhower was a general in this war, and
  subsequently went on to become President.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Korean War&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Vietnam War&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Persian Gulf War&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the Cold war, the main concern of the United States was communism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;21st Century Wars&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;11 thus far, including Afghanistan, Libya, Somalia, Syria and Iraq.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Government&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The constitution grants the federal government power to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Print money.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Declare war.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Raise an army.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make treaties.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The states are granted power to provide:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Protection in the form of police.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fire departments.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Schooling and education.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Driver's licenses.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Zoning and land use.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The government defined by the constitution is divided into three branches:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The executive branch is formed by the President and their administration.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The legislative branch is formed by Congress.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The judicial branch is formed by the courts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The separation of powers between these three branches forms a system of checks
and balances that prevents any one part of government from becoming too
powerful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The Executive&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The President leads the executive branch. They sign bills into law, and have
veto power over new laws. They are the Commander in Chief of the military.
Presidents are elected for four year terms, in a vote that takes place in
November.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The President appoints a Cabinet of advisors. If the President cannot serve,
succession falls to the Vice President, and then to the Speaker of the House.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other cabinet-level positions include Attorney General, and Secretaries of
Agriculture, Commerce, Defence, Education, Energy, Health and Human Services,
Homeland Security, Housing and Urban Development, the Interior, Labor,
State, Transportation, the Treasury, and Veterans Affairs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The President is currently Joseph Robinette Biden Jr (Democratic).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Vice President is currently Kamala Harris (Democratic).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Speaker of the House is currently Nancy Pelosi (Democratic).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The Legislature&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Congress makes federal laws.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It comprises two parts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Senate.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The House of Representatives.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;The Senate&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Senate comprises two senators from each state, yielding 100 total senators.
Each senator represents the entirety of their state. Senators are elected
for six year terms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;The House of Representatives&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each state is divided into a number of &lt;em&gt;congressional districts&lt;/em&gt;, the number
of which depends on the population of the state. Each district sends a single
representative to the House, whose job is to represent the people of their
specific district. Currently, this yields a total of 435 representatives.
Representatives are elected for two year terms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The Judicial branch&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The courts review and explain laws, resolves disputes, and decides whether
laws contravene the constitution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The "rule of law" states that every individual, no matter how highly-placed,
must obey the law, as must the government itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The highest court in the land is the Supreme Court, which comprises nine
justices, lead by Chief Justice John Glover Roberts Jr.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;States, Territories, and Geography&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The United States of America contains 335 million people, of whom around 261
million are adults. The regions of the country comprise:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;50 States (the 48 &lt;em&gt;contiguous&lt;/em&gt; States, plus Hawaii and Alaska)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Washington DC, the capital city and federal district (690,000 people).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Plus other territories:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;American Samoa (43,000 people).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Guam (169,000 people).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Northern Mariana Islands (56,000 people).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Puerto Rico (3,286,000 people).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;United States Virgin Islands (87,000 people).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For comparison, the least populated state, Wyoming, contains 581,000 people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Pacific Ocean is on the West Coast of the United States, while the Atlantic
ocean is on the East Coast.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The two longest rivers within the United States are the Missouri and the Mississippi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Statue of Liberty is on Liberty Island, in New York Harbour, on the Hudson River
near the south end of Manhattan in New York City.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;States that border Canada are: Maine, New Hampshire, Vermont, New York, Pennsylvania,
Ohio, Michigan, Minnesota, North Dakota, Montana, Idaho, Washington, and Alaska.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;States that border Mexico are: California, Arizona, New Mexico, and Texas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The flag has 50 stars to represent the 50 states, and 13 stripes to represent the
initial 13 colonies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The national anthem is &lt;em&gt;The Star-Spangled Banner&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Independence Day is celebrated every July 4th. Other national holidays are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;New Year's Day&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Martin Luther King Jr. Day&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Presidents' Day&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Memorial Day&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Independence Day&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Labor Day&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Columbus Day&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Veterans Day&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Thanksgiving&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Christmas&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;My State, Minnesota&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The capital of Minnesota is St Paul.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The current Governor of Minnesota is Tim Waltz.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The current senators for Minnesota are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Amy Klobuchar (Democratic)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tina Smith (Democratic)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The current representative for my district, the first congressional district of
Minnesota, is Jim Hagadorn (Republican).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Miscellanea&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The economic system of the United States is a capitalist, free market economy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The two major political parties in the US are the Democratic and Republican
parties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On 11th September 2001, terrorists attacked the United States by crashing
commercial passenger airliners into the Pentagon in Virginia near Washington
DC, and the twin towers of the World Trade Center, destroying them and killing
almost 3,000 people.&lt;/p&gt;</description><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/basic-us-civics/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 08 Jul 2022 16:19:32 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Journey</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/journey/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2022/journey-screenshot.webp"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Released on PlayStation 3 by thatgamecompany in 2012. Played on Windows 10 in
2022.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The slow-paced opening scenes, alternately trudging up and then surfing down
sunbaked desert dunes, failed to sustain Zander's interest, so I ended up
playing through its short runtime by myself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In some ways it's an indictment of videogame culture that ten years later it
still feels so fresh and radical to pair players up with another internet
rando, while giving them no means to communicate or interact other than helping
each other out, either leading by example, or exchanging wordless shouts. It
seems like a pretty limited repertoire at first. I'm half tempted to just wander
off ahead, alone, into the endless desert.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, you realize that standing close enough together recharges each other's
magical flying scarves. Suddenly, it's enough. You cling to each other for dear
life through the howling storms, double back to rescue each other from prowling
beasts, and then fly exuberantly above the sunlit clouds, forever curving back
to seek each other's life-giving sustenance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don't know who the two internet randos were, with whom I shared the first and
second halves of my journey. But in those minutes together, we lived a
lifetime's worth.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>completed</category><category>media</category><category>videogame</category><category>windows</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/journey/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 09 May 2022 11:22:20 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Expanse</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/the-expanse/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="The Expanse screencap" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2022/the-expanse-screencap.webp"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(This post rescues content from
&lt;a href="https://www.facebook.com/mfoord/posts/10158389841835880?comment_id=10158390351245880I"&gt;a Facebook comment&lt;/a&gt; I got carried away with recently.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's so much to write about the Expanse. It's such a relief to find a
science fiction show with an ambitiously futuristic setting depicted in a way
that doesn't make scientifically literate people cringe and shout at the
television.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, it shines at taking the time for quiet moments of character work, from
Miller's lonely, poignant realization in s01 that he wasn't the talented
office maverick, just incompetent and unreliable, right up to the quiet,
unseen payoff of Naomi's years-long efforts to save her son from his father's
influence, in the final seconds of s06.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On many axes, it's the best SF on television, which is saying something, as
there are so many competitors. Science fiction output is following some sort
of Moore's law of endless expansion, in response to society's need for
mythic stories of relevance to modern life, itself a symptom of the meaning
crisis of modern society. But this is a mixed blessing, because the resulting
shows &amp;amp; movies are often drawn to using the superficial trappings of science
fiction, spaceships and lasers (pew pew!), while failing to fulfil the deeper
psychological needs of mythical or symbolic significance that brought about
their creation. The Expanse is perhaps the prime example of this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.tartley.com/posts/the-expanse/damiengwalter.com"&gt;My fantastic SF podcast guy&lt;/a&gt; defines SF as the arena in
which we forge new myths of psychological meaning for modern life, which are
sorely needed as traditional myths dwindle in relevance, as they are
predominantly based on nature and superstition. Movements such as spiritual
atheism are a reflection that even the least spiritual amongst us recognize
that something is missing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I do concede that defining SF in this way is a bit of a cheat. It's somewhat
aggrandizing, claiming any great mythic work as actually being part of the
SF genre, an no doubt is a somewhat defensive reaction to mainstream
dismissal of science fiction as puerile. But it does provide a marvellous
framework for discussion, and adopting this definition makes several
previously puzzling things fall into place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It settles the revealing, never-ending debates over which works are, and
are not, science fiction. Somewhat tellingly, to me, such debates are
irreconcilable precisely because of the misnomer "science fiction", which was
never really about the science to begin with, as this style of fiction has
existed long before science was the focus. It only gravitated towards using
science as it became apparent that is now where society's power and
transformation springs from - our incarnation of gods and magic - and the name
"science fiction" was then applied post-facto, missing the underlying fact
that this is just mythic fiction with some modern attributes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This definition perfectly explains things like how the first half of the movie
"Sunshine" could be such astonishing science-fiction, while the second half
- set aboard the exact same spaceship - is just a mediocre slasher flick.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So. SF is the arena within which we construct new mythic narratives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By this I mean that great science fiction tends to create a story that
resonates because it leans on powerful mythic tropes - symbolic
representations of psychological significance, character arcs mirroring
Jungian archetypes, thematic elements that are told allegorically, suggesting
things to the reader/watcher on a level that can be more powerful than merely
stating them directly to the conscious mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this way, all-time-great examples such as &lt;em&gt;2001: A Space Odyssey&lt;/em&gt; (the
title being conscious of this mythic entanglement) leans heavily into themes
such as humanity watched over by an ancient, mysterious, godlike alien
influence which has literally created humanity in its present form, and
observes as we now reach a second inflection point, materializing not
just a tale of personal transcendence (although it is certainly that), but one
of species-wide sublimation - suggesting that it is time for us all to reach
spiritual adulthood, to graduate to whatever comes next, to meet and be
transformed by the wise and powerful force that has shepherded humanity
through our previous prehistorical transitions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I could go on with similar examples, but will just briefly mention the original
Matrix movie, which is a story which resonates because it is absolutely soaked
in allegory of both religious transcendence and Jungian archetypes - which are
so on-the-nose that it cannot possibly be accidental, a fact acknowledged
directly by the creators in the sequels, when they depict the Architect,
ultimate villain encountered at the narrative peak of the story, as a prim,
middle aged, white bearded gentleman, wearing an Edwardian suit. He speaks in a
precise, almost Germanic manner. This is, unmistakably, Sigmund Freud. Why is
Freud the villain of the Matrix? Because Freud was a contemporaneous antagonist
to Jung, resisting Jung's ideas of self actualization through reconciliation of
the archetypes, just as the Architect resists Neo's progression along that same
path.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It may be my own lack of imagination, but compared to examples like this, the
Expanse starts to look a bit thin. I don't see any symbolism or allegory.
There is some good character work but no actual arcs of transcendence. Through
the unfortunate realities of converting books to screen, large chunks of what
could have been the most meaningful story were simply abandoned and will
apparently never be finished on the screen. In their stead, what would have
been mythic elements become a series of "McGuffin of the week", as we never
circle back to resolve why the protomolecule was created, why it was sent to
our ancient solar system, why it turns people into nuclear-powered zombies,
and what force destroyed the protomolecule creators, and why? And that's just
series one's unresolved elements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, lacking that, what the Expanse has to offer is its superlative
world-building and sane, believable depictions of a gritty interplanetary
future. Which is no small feat - arguably nobody else has done it better. But,
for me, it isn't enough. Maybe that's just because I'm a godless heathen who
looks to get my spiritual fix through TV shows about spaceships. Or maybe it's
because science fiction is where we show ourselves what we're capable of, what
to aim for, and I believe we can aim higher than just exciting technological
dystopias.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>fiction</category><category>media</category><category>science-fiction</category><category>tv</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/the-expanse/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 08 Apr 2022 19:42:40 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Contact</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/contact/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Contact cover" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2022/contact-cover.webp"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Carl Sagan, 1985.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I put this into my library queue as it's highly regarded in some parts, and I'd
never read it. But at about chapter 2, I started to realize that I actually
have read it, maybe thirty years ago. Not only that, but I'm pretty sure I
actually have a copy somewhere on the shelves here at home. I'm going senile.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oh well, at least it's the sort of senile that gives me quick, pleasant things
to read.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also this month: &lt;em&gt;The Long Way to a Small, Angry Planet&lt;/em&gt; by Becky Chambers.
Once again, I wanted to like this so much. I started reading it twice, spaced
about 18 months apart. But each time, I just couldn't get into it, and
abandoned it about 1/3 in. It is indubitably me, not you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: left"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>fiction</category><category>media</category><category>novel</category><category>science-fiction</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/contact/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 20 Mar 2022 04:01:53 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Witch's Heart</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/the-witches-heart/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="The Witch's Heart cover" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2022/the-witchs-heart-cover.webp"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Genevieve Gornichec, 2021.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Old Norse mythology only briefly mentions the witch
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Angrbo%C3%B0a"&gt;Angrboða&lt;/a&gt;,
as the mother of three "monsters", fathered by the trickster god, Loki. This
book explores her life, explicitly acknowledging her erasure as a woman, and
resolves it, providing her a powerful story, in which she survives men, gods,
and all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another fantastic Suze recommendation. Loved it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also this month: &lt;em&gt;The Emperess of Salt and Fortune&lt;/em&gt; by Nghi Vo. I wanted to
like this sooo much, and can see so many things about that are wonderful, but
for some reason I just couldn't get in the mood. The problem is indubitably me,
not you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: left"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>fantasy</category><category>fiction</category><category>media</category><category>mythology</category><category>novel</category><category>science-fiction</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/the-witches-heart/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 20 Mar 2022 03:43:53 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Circe</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/circe/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Circe cover" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2022/circe-cover.webp"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Madeline Miller, 2018.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recommended by The Suze, after reading it for one of her book clubs,
and I absolutely loved it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tells the life story of the mythical Circe of the ancient Greek pantheon.
Daughter of Helios, mightiest of the Titans, Circe is driven from her family by
their capricious cruelty. She puts her meagre supernatural talents to work in
service of witchcraft, amongst mortals. Along the way she meets many well-known
mythological characters, such as Odysseus, and the Cretean Minotaur.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was the writing style that captivated me. A timeless, elegant style uses
powerful turns of phrase to spin a tale of drama and high passions, soaked
in the psychological resonances so typical of Greek mythology.
This style, along with the setting, reminded me powerfully of another favourite
couple of novels of recent years, Mary Renault's absolutely fabulous &lt;em&gt;The King
Must Die&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;The Bull From the Sea&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Circe is my favorite book of the year so far, beating out even the marvellous
&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.tartley.com/posts/klara-and-the-sun"&gt;Klara and the Sun&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: left"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>fantasy</category><category>fiction</category><category>media</category><category>mythology</category><category>novel</category><category>science-fiction</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/circe/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 20 Mar 2022 03:14:53 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Project Hail Mary</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/project-hail-mary/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Project Hail Mary cover" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2022/project-hail-mary-cover.webp"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lot of people really like this, but it really isn't for me. The plot
is an eerie recreation of the author's previous (and superior) big hit,
&lt;em&gt;The Martian&lt;/em&gt;, in which an astronaut finds themselves unexpectedly alone on an
ambitious space mission, and has to science the shit out of things (by which we
mean deploy some high-school science trivia, along with a penchant for very
ordinary mental arithmetic) to save the day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A badly written, distractingly unconvincing, and ultimately deeply annoying
collision between hard science fiction and hand-wavy nonsense, with no literate
themes, no higher meanings, no lurking Jungian archetypes - no mythology to it
at all. Just a succession of edge-of-the-seat will-he-or-won't-he survive tense
moments... Then: Yay, it worked, he did it! But &lt;em&gt;in space!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not even worth engaging the subjectivity-proof rating system for this one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rating: 2/10. I did finish it, but I wish I hadn't.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: both"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>fiction</category><category>media</category><category>novel</category><category>science-fiction</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/project-hail-mary/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 14 Feb 2022 02:07:47 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Electric State</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/the-electric-state/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: right"&gt;
&lt;img alt="The Electric State cover" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2022/the-electric-state-cover.webp"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Simon Stålenhag (2017)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I listen to
&lt;a href="https://damiengwalter.com/podcast/"&gt;a really fantastic science fiction podcast&lt;/a&gt;
by Damien Walter, which is fascinatingly cerebral. Damien selected Stålenhag's
work for his recent round-up of
&lt;a href="https://damiengwalter.com/2021/12/03/the-21-most-significant-science-fiction-storytellers-of-the-21st-century-so-far/"&gt;the 21 most significant science fiction storytellers of the 21st century (so
far)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the same artist whose work inspired 2020's
&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt8741290/"&gt;Tales from the Loop&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;,
and Damien's selection spurred me to engage more fully than just browse around
Stålenhag's images all over the web.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wasn't disappointed. The word count is low enough to be considered a short,
but the main event is the accompanying illustrations, which are downright
startling in their contrasts of the mundane and the fantastic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Charting the journey of a runaway teenager and her small yellow robot, through
a ruined near-future American landscape, littered with the debris of a high
tech consumerist society addicted to an all-encompassing virtual-reality
system. As they approach the edge of the continent, the world outside the car
window unravels at an ever faster pace, as if somewhere beyond the horizon, the
hollow core of civilization has finally caved in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: both"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>comic</category><category>fiction</category><category>media</category><category>science-fiction</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/the-electric-state/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 14 Feb 2022 01:32:45 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Works of Larry Niven</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/the-works-of-larry-niven/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2022/niven/view-from-the-surface-of-a-ringworld.webp"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few days ago I mistakenly
&lt;a href="https://www.tartley.com/posts/termination-shock"&gt;named Neal Stephenson as the author I'd read more of&lt;/a&gt;
than any other. But I was forgetting about being young and inhaling books.
On reflection, that title must surely belong to Larry Niven. As a teenager I
read every last thing he did - or at least everything I could find in my
hometown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At one point my Mom picked up &lt;em&gt;World Out of Time&lt;/em&gt;, to see what craziness her
son was always buried in, and she concluded over the dinner table that I was
reading it for the sex scenes she'd found. I presumably objected inarticulately
that I was so little interested in Larry Niven's brief nerdy depictions of
space sex that I'd barely even noticed they were there, but I have the
impression she wasn't convinced. But it &lt;em&gt;really was&lt;/em&gt; was his brand of hard
science fiction that I was there for (I protest too much!) - revolving around
ideas rather than character arcs, and the ruthless application of consistent
world-views.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In inventing the Ringworld, Niven was inspired by Dyson spheres,
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Star_Maker"&gt;first described by Olaf Stapledon&lt;/a&gt;,
and &lt;a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20140109033551/http://meaningoflife.tv/transcript.php?speaker=dyson"&gt;popularized by Freeman Dyson&lt;/a&gt;.
A full, solid Dyson sphere was, in some regards, inefficient. Dyson postulated
miraculous gravity generators to make the inner surface of the sphere
habitable. But this can be achieved much more feasibly by simply spinning the
structure. However, all the matter inside the sphere, including any atmosphere,
then pools at the equator. Niven observed that the superfluous surface of the
sphere, away from the equator, can then be removed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This vastly reduces the material needed to construct the megastructure.
Given miraculous elemental transmutation, one could easily gather enough
matter by recycling all the planets in a solar system as building material,
even with a 1,000km "wall" along each edge to keep the fringes of the
atmosphere in. Although this yields a much smaller habitable interior surface
area than a full sphere, it's still something like a million times larger than
planet Earth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The aliens themselves weren't quite like any I've read before or since. The
creepy sessile but sentient Grogs. The mysterious Outsiders, information
brokers who are able to answer any question humanity has - if only we could
afford the prices. The warlike, carnivorous Kzinti (picture a species of
vicious feline Chewbaccas - surely the inspiration for Wing Commander's
Kilrathi) forever attacking humanity before they were quite ready. You can't
help but almost feel sorry for them. By the times of Ringworld, representatives
such as Speaker to Animals (named for his shameful profession, interfacing with
humans) are sufficiently adapted to working alongside humans to become
formidable allies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps Niven's greatest alien race was The Pierson's Puppeteers - like an
ostrich with two necks, each topped with a single eye and dexterous mouth,
while the brain resides safely in the body (pictured below, on the cover for
Neutron star). The body plan makes so much sense in action. Mobile eyes mean
they routinely view objects from both sides simultaneously, perfect for
close-up detailed work, using the hand-like mouths. Or, spread the necks wide
for amazing stereoscopic vision when distance estimation matters. And that
gestural laugh - eyes turned inward to briefly gaze into one another, observing
the self, no mirror required.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The psychology is also exquisite. Herbivores and herd-beasts, the Puppeteers
are inveterate cowards. No human has ever met a sane one - only their more
unstable individuals would venture out alone to run the risks of space travel
and meeting alien species. However, they are very intelligent, more so than
humans, and industrious, and manipulative. It becomes clear over the course of
the books that Puppeteers have selectively bred the Kzinti into constructive
docility by engineering the many human-kzin wars, and their plans for everyone
else are scarcely less devious.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, my personal favorite was always the Pak. As alien as could be, and yet
they are us. On humanity's original homeworld, long before introduction to
planet Earth, a symbiotic plant grows which young humans find uninteresting,
but in middle-age they develop a compulsion to binge on it. It activates genes
that provoke startling physiological and psychological changes, transforming
the human from a &lt;em&gt;breeder&lt;/em&gt;, into a &lt;em&gt;protector&lt;/em&gt; - stronger, and with large
joints for better leverage, with a tough wrinkled armour-like skin, much
smarter, with a second heart, and ruthlessly dedicated to just one goal -
protecting their own offspring. It is protectors who, it turns out many novels
later, originally built the Ringworld. The absence of the transforming plant,
which won't grow on Earth, means we grow without its benefits, leaving us with
inadequate hearts, joints that fail with age, and an old-aged descent into
feeble bodies and minds. Then, as the story begins, the first known
interstellar spaceship shows up at Earth, piloted by one protector, come to
rescue the failed colony, with a hold full of strange plant roots...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wonders like these, from the novels and short stories set in his Known Space
universe kept me up at night, and shaped the way I thought. Although Niven's
writing had some mildly conservative tendencies, especially when under the
influence of his militaristic writing partner Jerry Pournelle, it is also
permeated with the necessity of a very liberal philosophy of non-judgemental
tolerance of other lifestyles, both alien and human, a philosophy made explicit
in one of &lt;em&gt;Niven's Laws&lt;/em&gt;: "The only universal message in science fiction: There
exist minds that think as well as you do, but differently."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's clear I wasn't the only one spellbound. Niven's ideas have been
influential throughout science fiction culture. Bank's Culture's Orbitals and
the understandably much rarer full Rings are clear descendants, as is the
eponymous megastructure/superweapon of the juggernaut &lt;em&gt;Halo&lt;/em&gt; franchise, and
countless other imitators. Niven's meticulous hard-SF approach to fantasy in
&lt;em&gt;The Magic Goes Away&lt;/em&gt;, and in particular his concept of the conservation of
&lt;em&gt;mana&lt;/em&gt;, was an influence on &lt;em&gt;Magic: The Gathering&lt;/em&gt;, as acknowledged in the card
Nevinyrral's Disk (Niven's name backwards), which uses magic to simultaneously
accelerate it's own spin, and to hold itself together, thus rapidly using up
all the mana in an area, rendering further magic unusable. Movies such as
Wall-E throw in sly nods - the Axiom is labelled in a passing graphic as using
a "General Dynamics Type Three Hull", which is a similar size and shape to
Niven's "General Products Number Three Hull".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For years I remember toting Niven's various doorstop 500 page novels to one
place or another, such as being forbidden from carrying one into the Houses of
Parliament viewing gallery. All the better that they usually had these crazy
great '70s covers, mostly by artist
&lt;a href="http://www.peterandrewjones.net/iacg.htm"&gt;Peter Andrew Jones&lt;/a&gt;,
from whom you can buy prints of some of them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Collecting these today by Google image search, I see today that these funky
covers are relatively rare - the vast majority of Niven's sales were of
editions with far less interesting and less skillfully put together covers. So
I think it's appropriate to collect and celebrate them here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;span style="padding: 0.3em"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2022/niven/mote-in-gods-eye.webp"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style="padding: 0.3em"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2022/niven/footfall.webp"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style="padding: 0.3em"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2022/niven/oath-of-fealty.webp"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style="padding: 0.3em"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2022/niven/dream-park.webp"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style="padding: 0.3em"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2022/niven/patchwork-girl.webp"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style="padding: 0.3em"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2022/niven/convergent-series.webp"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style="padding: 0.3em"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2022/niven/magic-goes-away.webp"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style="padding: 0.3em"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2022/niven/lucifers-hammer.webp"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style="padding: 0.3em"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2022/niven/world-out-of-time.webp"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style="padding: 0.3em"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2022/niven/tales-of-known-space.webp"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style="padding: 0.3em"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2022/niven/hole-in-space.webp"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style="padding: 0.3em"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2022/niven/flight-of-the-horse.webp"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style="padding: 0.3em"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2022/niven/protector.webp"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style="padding: 0.3em"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2022/niven/inconstant-moon.webp"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style="padding: 0.3em"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2022/niven/ringworld.webp"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style="padding: 0.3em"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2022/niven/ringworld-engineers.webp"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style="padding: 0.3em"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2022/niven/long-arm-of-gil-hamilton.webp"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style="padding: 0.3em"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2022/niven/a-gift-from-earth.webp"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style="padding: 0.3em"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2022/niven/neutron-star.webp"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style="padding: 0.3em"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2022/niven/world-of-ptavvs.webp"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: both"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've not even read half of what Niven wrote. By the '90s the crazy covers had
been replaced by more conservative designs, and at the same time I drifted away
to other things. At the time it felt more like Niven was drifting away from me,
evolving in style over the years, losing something hard-to-characterize that
I'd enjoyed, maybe just the rawness of his earlier works. Maybe his style was
diluted through him writing so many books as partnerships, or, as I
increasingly assumed, in an advisory role, lending his name to the cover for
younger, less well-known authors, who did most of the work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking back on it, with 30-or-so year's hindsight, there are also
components of Niven's writing that are lacking, and I was slowly growing out of
it. Hard SF often celebrates the elevation of ideas over characters, and while
there is a value to that, particularly for those readers who are the most
vulnerable to the sensation of wonder, it also needlessly shuns other aspects,
like the emotional impact of character-driven drama or individual psychological
epiphany. A more skilled writer, I now think, would have a broader range of
tools to imbue the story with more emotional resonance and meaning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, while the affair lasted, it was fabulous. Goodreads page counts
indicates it was eleven thousand pages, beating my Neal Stephenson consumption
by a clear thousand pages. Combining that with a very conservative estimate of
the number of times I re-read each one, nearly twenty five thousand pages. What
can I say, I was a teenager, with seemingly endless oceans of time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following are just his books that I've read. He has many others, especially
many that are more recent than these.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Title&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align="right"&gt;Pages&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align="right"&gt;Times&lt;br&gt;read&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align="right"&gt;Effective&lt;br&gt;pages&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/100379.Rainbow_Mars"&gt;Rainbow Mars&lt;/a&gt; (1999)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;477&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;477&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/64750.Destiny_s_Road"&gt;Destiny's Road&lt;/a&gt; (1997)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;448&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;448&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/64467.The_Ringworld_Throne"&gt;The Ringworld Throne&lt;/a&gt; (1996)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;368&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;368&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/69448.Beowulf_s_Children"&gt;Beowulf's Children&lt;/a&gt; (1995)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;512&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;1,024&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/40932142-flatlander"&gt;Flatlander&lt;/a&gt; (1995)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;369&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;369&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/100347.Crashlander"&gt;Crashlander&lt;/a&gt; (1994)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;281&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;281&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/218453.The_Gripping_Hand"&gt;The Gripping Hand&lt;/a&gt; (1993)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;413&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;826&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/218470.The_Barsoom_Project"&gt;The Barsoom Project&lt;/a&gt; (1989)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;352&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;352&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/899392.The_Legacy_of_Heorot"&gt;The Legacy of Heorot&lt;/a&gt; (1987)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;383&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;766&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/100351.The_Smoke_Ring"&gt;The Smoke Ring&lt;/a&gt; (1987)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;323&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;646&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/116356.Footfall"&gt;Footfall&lt;/a&gt; (1985)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;524&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;1,572&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/939740.The_Integral_Trees"&gt;The Integral Trees&lt;/a&gt; (1983)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;272&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;544&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/583441.Oath_of_Fealty"&gt;Oath of Fealty&lt;/a&gt; (1981)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;324&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;648&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/357922.Dream_Park"&gt;Dream Park&lt;/a&gt; (1981)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;448&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;1,344&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/1124048.The_Patchwork_Girl"&gt;The Patchwork Girl&lt;/a&gt; (1980)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;205&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;410&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/61181.The_Ringworld_Engineers"&gt;The Ringworld Engineers&lt;/a&gt; (1979)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;307&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;614&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/1124090.Convergent_Series"&gt;Convergent Series&lt;/a&gt; (1979)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;227&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;454&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/1002736.The_Magic_Goes_Away"&gt;The Magic Goes Away&lt;/a&gt; (1978)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;212&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;1,060&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/218467.Lucifer_s_Hammer"&gt;Lucifer's Hammer&lt;/a&gt; (1977)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;629&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;1,258&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/64725.A_World_Out_of_Time"&gt;A World Out of Time&lt;/a&gt; (1976)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;246&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;738&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/100359.Tales_of_Known_Space"&gt;Tales of Known Space&lt;/a&gt; (1975)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;240&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;1,200&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/100365.The_Mote_in_God_s_Eye"&gt;The Mote in God's Eye&lt;/a&gt; (1974)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;596&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;1,788&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/218473.A_Hole_in_Space"&gt;A Hole in Space&lt;/a&gt; (1974)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;196&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;392&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/378683.The_Flight_of_the_Horse"&gt;The Flight of the Horse&lt;/a&gt; (1973)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;212&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;1,060&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/100344.Protector"&gt;Protector&lt;/a&gt; (1973)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;218&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;872&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/1255867.Inconstant_Moon"&gt;Inconstant Moon&lt;/a&gt; (1971)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;200&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;800&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/61179.Ringworld"&gt;Ringworld&lt;/a&gt; (1970)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;228&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;456&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/100363.N_Space"&gt;N-Space&lt;/a&gt; (1969)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;693&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;693&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/116355.The_Long_Arm_of_Gil_Hamilton"&gt;The Long Arm of Gil Hamilton&lt;/a&gt; (1969)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;182&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;364&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/218479.All_the_Myriad_Ways"&gt;All the Myriad Ways&lt;/a&gt; (1968)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;181&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;362&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/218461.A_Gift_from_Earth"&gt;A Gift from Earth&lt;/a&gt; (1968)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;256&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;768&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/100366.Neutron_Star"&gt;Neutron Star&lt;/a&gt; (1966)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;285&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;1,140&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/218463.The_World_of_Ptavvs"&gt;The World of Ptavvs&lt;/a&gt; (1966)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;188&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;752&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;totals&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;10,995&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;24,842&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(&lt;a href="https://www.facebook.com/groups/324897304599197/permalink/1329010600854524"&gt;Discussion&lt;/a&gt;
on Damien Walter's &lt;em&gt;Science Fiction&lt;/em&gt; Facebook group)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: both"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>fiction</category><category>media</category><category>niven</category><category>novel</category><category>science-fiction</category><category>short</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/the-works-of-larry-niven/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 14 Jan 2022 23:37:37 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Termination Shock</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/termination-shock/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Termination Shock cover" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2022/termination-shock-cover.webp"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Neal Stephenson, 2021&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's another 720-page doorstop from the much-beloved author (which is actually
slightly slimmer than his average book, which would be 770 pages). It was
enjoyable, but not life changing. Not as compelling as some of his previous.
Reads a lot like a narrative wrapped around the author's own personal
justifications for pro-active geo-engineering projects. Which, I have to admit,
I was pretty horrified by the idea when I first heard about it - meddling
further with a critical and horrifically complex dynamic system that we don't
undertand, and all that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The story presents the the scenario of countering the temperature rise caused
by CO2 in the atmosphere by releasing high altitude sulphur dioxide, to reflect
sunlight back into space. This mitigates many of the most prominent effects of
climate change, such as high-temperatures, storms, forest fires, and sea-level
rises.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It further presents the idea that it's relatively easy and cheap to do, and
some nation or part thereof that cares the most - e.g. The Netherlands, or
Venice, amongst others, will either take a crack at it, or else will cease to
exist. So we might as well get used to the idea and be prepared for what,
geopolitically, happens after that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don't know if it's simply the story making me increasingly familiar with the
idea, or whether the depiction of the mechanism genuinely quells some of my
worries, in that it seems easy to start at a small scale, monitor the results,
scale up as required, and the fail-safe is that the sulphur should quickly fall
out of the air, allegedly harmlessly, if we realize this was a bad idea. I've
at least tempered my initial harshly negative viewpoint somewhat. So, mission
accomplished, I guess?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've probably read more text by Stephenson than any other writer. Hmmm. By
Goodreads page counts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Title&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align="right"&gt;Pages&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align="right"&gt;Times&lt;br&gt;read&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align="right"&gt;Effective&lt;br&gt;pages&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/825.Zodiac"&gt;Zodiac&lt;/a&gt; (1988)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;308&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;308&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/40651883-snow-crash"&gt;Snow Crash&lt;/a&gt; (1992)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;559&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;1,118&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/828.Interface"&gt;Interface&lt;/a&gt; (1994)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;640&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;640&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/827.The_Diamond_Age"&gt;The Diamond Age&lt;/a&gt; (1995)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;499&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;1,497&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/824.The_Cobweb"&gt;The Cobweb&lt;/a&gt; (1996)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;448&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;448&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/40383049-in-the-beginning-was-the-command-line"&gt;In the Beginning... Was the Command Line&lt;/a&gt; (1999)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;160&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;320&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/816.Cryptonomicon"&gt;Cryptonomicon&lt;/a&gt; (1999)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;1,152&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;3,456&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/823.Quicksilver"&gt;Quicksilver&lt;/a&gt; (2003)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;927&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;927&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/822.The_Confusion"&gt;The Confusion&lt;/a&gt; (2004)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;815&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;815&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/116257.The_System_of_the_World"&gt;The System of the World&lt;/a&gt; (2004)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;908&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;908&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/2845024-anathem"&gt;Anathem&lt;/a&gt; (2008)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;937&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;1,874&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/10552338-reamde"&gt;Reamde&lt;/a&gt; (2011)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;1,044&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;1,044&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/22816087-seveneves"&gt;Seveneves&lt;/a&gt; (2015)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;880&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;880&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/57094295-termination-shock"&gt;Termination Shock&lt;/a&gt; (2021)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;720&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;720&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;totals&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;9,997&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;14,955&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ten thousand pages, all from one author, or fifteen thousand if you include
re-reads. Not bad! The number of re-reads is a reasonable proxy for the impact
each book had on me at the time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But on reflection, &lt;a href="https://www.tartley.com/posts/the-works-of-larry-niven"&gt;there is another contender&lt;/a&gt;...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: left"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>environment</category><category>fiction</category><category>media</category><category>novel</category><category>science-fiction</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/termination-shock/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 14 Jan 2022 15:20:55 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>