<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>tartley.com</title><link>https://tartley.com/</link><description>Creating a website devoted to oneself has been described as the greatest act of hubris. Welcome aboard!</description><atom:link href="https://www.tartley.com/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2022 &lt;a href="mailto:tartley @ the domain tartley dot com"&gt;Jonathan Hartley&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 06 Jan 2022 18:14:07 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>The Incal</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/the-incal/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="The Incal page" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2022/the-incal-frame.webp"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: left"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;written by Alejandro Jodorowsky, art by Jean Giraud (aka Mœbius), 1980-88&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I grabbed this in the English translation from the original French, having been
intrigued by the &lt;em&gt;Pocket Essential Alan Moore&lt;/em&gt;'s description of it as a
contender for "the best comic in the medium's history".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This creative pairing also worked together on the unproduced 1970s movie of
Dune, the one that was to have featured Salvador Dali, and presumably would
have been pretty trippy - I mean, &lt;em&gt;even more&lt;/em&gt; trippy than the David Lynch
one turned out to be. Mœbius has had a long and glorious career, knighted
for his art in his native France, and he worked on other genre movies such as
Alien, Tron, The Fifth Element, and The Abyss.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Echoes of all of these are visible in The Incal, throughout which the artwork
is consistently stunning. With hindsight, it looks like the leading edge of
waves that subsequently shifted the whole industry, from the expansive decayed
futurescapes of Akira and Blade Runner, to the flamboyant visuals of the Star
Wars prequels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The writing really swings for the fences, a sprawling tale of a reluctant
hero's journey, taking in societal commentary, intergalactic travel, spiritual
transformation, iconic representations of good and evil, and a deep thread of
mysticism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For me, it does have a very evident "foreign" feeling - small social nuances
with which I'm unfamiliar. Equally clearly, this is part of its exotic charm.
And while the story touches on, perhaps even consists of, deep themes, it
perhaps doesn't explore them very articulately.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In lesser hands, it might have been undisciplined. But, come rain or shine, the
artwork is endlessly enthralling, including touches such as the protagonist,
John DiFool, starting out distinctly ugly, but being rendered more handsomely
on the rare occasions he manages to get in touch with his more noble aspects.
Jodorowsky manages to keep it all together, bringing it around to a splendidly
satisfying theatrical close. &lt;em&gt;Bravo!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: left"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>comic</category><category>fiction</category><category>media</category><category>science-fiction</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/the-incal/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 05 Jan 2022 19:56:03 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Klara and the Sun</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/klara-and-the-sun/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Klara and the Sun cover" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2022/klara-and-the-sun-cover.webp"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Kazuo Ishiguro, 2021&lt;/em&gt; &lt;img alt="spoilers" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/spoilers.svg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was just wonderful to read.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The near-future scenario is revealed in a compellingly minimal way, teased
in minor details. Eventually we piece together an epidemic of children without
siblings, born into a competitive, authoritarian society. Higher-rank parents
are able to purchase artificial friends, to help with the rigors of
socialization. Klara, a newly activated artificial friend, demonstrates a lack
of experience in dealing with human situations, but her efforts are
unstinting, to understand what is going on within the family to whom she is
sold, and do her best for them. Her earnest naivety as a narrator only
serves to magnify the emotional impacts of the story, as her keen but
inexperienced observation conveys everything we need to know about the
dysfunctions of her tragic new family. She describes
herself as feeling emotions, so the story is partly a discussion of what it
means to be concious, to feel, as the humans around her are forced by
circumstance into desperate schemes that expose the self-protective
aspects of their love.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For all that, though, I'm not sure what to take away from it. Clearly the
author is very skilled. It seems likely that metaphors are at work here. But,
lunk that I am, I'm unable to discern what they are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm fairly sure that the "boxes" Klara sometimes relates her perceptions being
divided into are just stylish flair - a reference to the ways in which her
brain works differently from ours, calving off processing into separate
processors, or some-such, which comes to the fore when she is under stress,
or deciphering complex emotions. I don't &lt;em&gt;think&lt;/em&gt; this strikingly non-literal
aspect is indicative of any deeper symbolism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes, when I fail to pick up on metaphor, it's because religious
allegory is involved. Beyond tales of mere personal transcendence, my brain
just isn't wired that way. I can see that Klara is in many ways an innocent.
Free not only of wrongdoing, but also of wishing harm, and - being made, not
born - of original sin. On the literal level, this is emotionally
resonant, especially when Klara's heroic contribution to the family is
rewarded by being uncomplainingly discarded, like an appliance, at the end of
the book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But is this related to the other big clue about things I'm not picking up on -
the title? I'm at a loss of what to make about Klara's relationship with the
sun, which is a central plot point. Was Klara's bargain with her Sun god
literally answered by a special burst of healing light, that saved her family's
child from terminal illness? Certainly that is how Klara relates it. Could she
perhaps have been imagining this? Might the recovery have been fated to happen
anyway, and Klara's association with the burst of sunlight was all in her head?
But the text tells us that the rest of the household are awestruck by the
brilliance and beauty of that particular sunbeam, not just Klara. Later on, the
questions Rick asks of Klara show that, although he does not understand, he has
guessed the significance of the moment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So. Klara the innocent's anthropomorphized Sun god's healing powers are real,
and He answers her prayers to save the life of a child. And I don't know what
to make of that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, I'm in good company. A quick search does yield intelligent writing
about the book, but I don't see anyone coming up with aspects or metaphors
that I've entirely overlooked - although that is usually quite fruitful when I
search about other books that puzzle me. So I venture that I'm not the only one
who doesn't get it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: left"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>fiction</category><category>ishiguro</category><category>media</category><category>novel</category><category>science-fiction</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/klara-and-the-sun/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 04 Jan 2022 22:06:39 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Three Parts Dead</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/three-parts-dead/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Three Parts Dead cover" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2021/three-parts-dead-cover.webp"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Max Gladstone (2012).&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A loveable romp. Technical witchcraft. Lawyerly magic wielders. Murdered gods.
What's not to like?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But will I continue with the series? I think... not. Which is actually a good
thing - there are just
&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/189147.To_Your_Scattered_Bodies_Go"&gt;so&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/968902.Dying_Inside"&gt;many&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/26187256-the-thing-itself"&gt;other&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/36836025-the-electric-state"&gt;things&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/25372801-all-the-birds-in-the-sky"&gt;I'm&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/42036538-gideon-the-ninth"&gt;dying&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/13821.Lord_of_Light"&gt;to&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/13259270-free-will"&gt;read&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/50202953-piranesi"&gt;right&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/31379914-the-collapsing-empire"&gt;now&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: left"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>fantasy</category><category>media</category><category>novel</category><category>science-fiction</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/three-parts-dead/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 16 Dec 2021 05:16:46 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Creating Animated Meme GIFs on the Command-Line</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/creating-animated-meme-gifs-on-the-command-line/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Got sick of navigating the limitations of various online services to create
animated gif memes, finally figured out how to do it manually. Not a universal
process, just what worked for my situation. (Which is Ubuntu 21.10, "Impish".)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of of the ffmpeg invocations could probably be combined into one, but I
show the commands as I used them, as I was figuring each step out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;1. Download a video&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Starting from a video on YouTube:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/6-gJMs6DwuE" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To download this locally,
&lt;a href="https://github.com/ytdl-org/youtube-dl"&gt;install &lt;code&gt;youtube-dl&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;,
hit the YouTube &lt;em&gt;share&lt;/em&gt; button to grab the video's encoded URL,
and:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;youtube-dl https://youtu.be/6-gJMs6DwuE -o Ash.mp4
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This gives me an 850KB .mp4 video file.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;2. Split&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I only want the final few seconds. To remove the start of the video,
keeping from 6.5 seconds until the end:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;ffmpeg -hide_banner -i Ash.mp4 -acodec copy -vcodec libx264 -ss 00:00:06.5 Ash-split.mp4
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Args to ffmpeg are position sensitive. Specifying '-ss' (to split the file)
before the input ('-i') can't create the split at an accurate location, since
it has to guess whereabouts in the file the given timestamp will occur. But
putting it after the input (as done here) means it can split accurately on the
given timestamp, since the file has been processed by the time this arg gets
actioned, so accurate timestamp/frame conversion is known, at the cost of
having had to process even the parts of the video that are then discarded.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vcodec of libx264 is specified because, according to stackoverflow,
"&lt;a href="https://stackoverflow.com/questions/5651654/ffmpeg-how-to-split-video-efficiently#comment85070704_13289426"&gt;scenes in mp4 are broken&lt;/a&gt;", whatever that means,
and specifying "copy", as most people do, gives me an output with no video,
only audio.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This results in a three second, 217KB .mp4 video file. (the following is just an
image of it).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="ash-split.webp" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2021/ash-split.webp"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;3. Crop&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To crop out the black bars from the top and bottom:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;ffmpeg -hide_banner -i Ash-split.mp4 -vf 'crop=iw:365' Ash-split-crop.mp4
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here, we crop it to the input width "iw", and 365 high. In the absense of
any offset ordinates for the crop, ffmpeg defaults to centering them, so this
365 pixels are taken from the (spatial, vertical) middle of the video, which is
exactly what we want.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This results in a three second, 220KB .mp4 video file.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="ash-split-crop.webp" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2021/ash-split-crop.webp"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;4. Resize and convert to gif&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class="s s-Atom"&gt;ffmpeg&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s s-Atom"&gt;hide_banner&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s s-Atom"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;Ash&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s s-Atom"&gt;split&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s s-Atom"&gt;crop&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s s-Atom"&gt;mp4&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s s-Atom"&gt;vf&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s s-Atom"&gt;'scale=512:-1'&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;Ash&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s s-Atom"&gt;split&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s s-Atom"&gt;crop&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s s-Atom"&gt;resize&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s s-Atom"&gt;gif&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This results in a grainy-but-passable three second 750KB animated .gif:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="ash-split-crop-resize.gif" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2021/ash-split-crop-resize.gif"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The file size can be smaller, if you care, most easily by splitting a shorter
video clip, reducing the frame rate, or reducing the 'scale' in this step.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alternately, this could be done using ImageMagik's 'convert', but the result
of that was a very large (10MB) file and played very slowly, and I wasn't
immediately sure how to fix that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;5. Add text&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using Imagemagik's 'convert':&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;convert \
    Ash-split-crop-resize.gif \
    -coalesce \
    -font impact -pointsize 36 -fill white -stroke black -strokewidth 2 \
    -gravity north -annotate +0+0 'I can''t lie about your chances, but' \
    -gravity south -annotate +0+0 'you have my sympathies' \
    -layers Optimize \
    Ash-split-crop-resize-text.gif
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The '-coalesce' option removes all the .gif optimizations, then we apply the
text labels, then the '-layers' option re-applies optimizations. Without this
dance, the text is all twitchy and messy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Voilà. Imagine sending it to a co-worker who is taking on a difficult task,
like making changes to that thorny section of the codebase that nobody likes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="ash-split-crop-resize-text.gif" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2021/ash-split-crop-resize-text.gif"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>image</category><category>linux</category><category>terminal</category><category>til</category><category>video</category><category>youtube</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/creating-animated-meme-gifs-on-the-command-line/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 08 Dec 2021 21:32:10 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Subnautica: Below Zero</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/subnautica-below-zero/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;on Windows, published 2021&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;img alt="spoilers" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/spoilers.svg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://subnautica.fandom.com/wiki/Subnautica_Wiki"&gt;Subnautica&lt;/a&gt;,
and its icy sequel,
"&lt;a href="https://subnautica.fandom.com/wiki/Subnautica:_Below_Zero"&gt;Below Zero&lt;/a&gt;",
have perhaps been my favorite
games of the last few years. The majority of their run time takes place under
the colorful waters of an alien ocean. It's been a joy to sit side-by-size
with Zander for tense scuba cave dives, or piloting vehicles through
vertiginous underwater cave systems, headlights straining through the murk to
reveal wonders. It has inspired
&lt;a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/Subnautica_Below_Zero/comments/r82l3i/birthday_cake_no_spoilers/"&gt;cake&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Part of the games take place on land though. I &lt;em&gt;started&lt;/em&gt; drawing a map of Below
Zero's Glacial Basin region just to keep track of where we'd been. To make sure
we visited all the locations, found all the MacGuffins (I'm looking at &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt;,
pesky antidote), and experienced all that there was to experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But as those goals approached completion, I &lt;em&gt;finished&lt;/em&gt; drawing it because it
had become a therapeutic experience. Happily exploring away, mesmerised by the
scenery, avoiding hostile wildlife, uncovering the ruins of ancient alien
artifacts. Reckoning distances by eye, scribbling down what we found, updating
and correcting the map as we went. Being lost in the experience. Simply a joy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/Subnautica_Below_Zero/comments/qutkqz/hand_drawn_map_of_southern_glacial_region_wip/"&gt;Reddit is encouraging me&lt;/a&gt;
to tackle the tricky Actic Spires area, too. &lt;em&gt;&amp;lt;Rubs hands&amp;gt;...&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Subnautica screenshot" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2021/subnatica-below-zero-map-glacial-basin.png"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: left"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>map</category><category>media</category><category>videogame</category><category>windows</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/subnautica-below-zero/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 22 Nov 2021 22:24:22 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Starship Troopers</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/starship-troopers/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Starship Troopers cover" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2021/starship-troopers-cover.webp"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Robert Heinlein, 1959.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My first time reading this classic old Hugo winner. I'd seen the 1995 movie
many years ago, which is clearly a satire, highlighting the fascistic
tendencies of the dedicated military discipline required for humanity to
survive in a dog-eat-dog galaxy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But was that Heinlein's original intent? I don't detect that in my reading of
it. The text seems, to my eyes, to be a straight-up endorsement and
glorification of military discipline, corporal and capital punishment, and
withholding citizenship from people who haven't served in the military.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've seen people argue that, as an expert writer, Heinlein knew precisely what
he was doing, and didn't need to draw attention to his critiques of fascism in
order for an astute reader to realize that not everything espoused by the novel
is necessarily good, or corresponds with the author's viewpoint. We are still
discussing the novel 60 years later, and its relationship to fascism, so he has
achieved his goal of getting us to think about it. After all, didn't Heinlein
write this partway through his drafting of what would become &lt;em&gt;Stranger in a
Strange Land&lt;/em&gt;, which features hippy sexual freedom, and &lt;em&gt;Troopers&lt;/em&gt; itself
contains nods to racial and gender equality (albeit these are somewhat
ham-fisted.) Hence, say some, Heinlein was would not genuinely have intended to
advocate militaristic or fascist views.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm not convinced. It seems entirely possible that Heinlein was in favor of
sexual freedoms, while in other regards advocating staunch militarism. He
wrote &lt;em&gt;Troopers&lt;/em&gt; directly in response to the US suspending nuclear weapons
testing, which he wished to see resume. According to Wikipedia he stated at the
time that he used the novel to clarify his military and political views, such
as that the USA was too conciliatory in its dealings with China and the Soviet
Union. In the book, the "bugs" - alien enemies, are explicitly referred to as
communist, and depicted as mostly mindless drones, for which the only solution
is eradication.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So. I don't agree with the author's outlook, and wasn't convinced by the book's
interpretation of civics, and passages of moralizing. But it was an
interesting, albeit naturally dated, read, to see what successful military
SF looked like 60 years ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: left"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>fiction</category><category>media</category><category>novel</category><category>science-fiction</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/starship-troopers/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 20 Nov 2021 18:19:44 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>This Is How You Lose the Time War</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/this-is-how-you-lose-the-time-war/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="This Is How You Lose the Time War cover" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2021/this-is-how-you-lose-the-time-war-cover.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Amal El-Mohtar &amp;amp; Max Gladstone, 2019&lt;/em&gt; &lt;img alt="spoilers" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/spoilers.svg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's a marvellous literary romp, deploying the tropes and language of science
fiction to deliver a scintillatingly poetic payload of — dare I say it —
credible romance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The combatants in the Time War seek to bring about historical outcomes which
predispose those futures which will result in the generation of their own
particular civilisation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In one future, humans have embraced machine-oriented augmentation, uploads,
and all that that implies. In the other, transformation is wrought by
biological means, accepting humankind's role as a part of a natural ecosystem,
boostrapping the whole to greatness by a ruthless application of evolutionary
principles. Each finds the other repulsive, and their existence is mutually
exclusive. From our perspective, they appear equally awe-inspiring and terrible
to behold.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, as intriguing as all that is, it's not why we're here. Instead we get
the much more personal accounts of two omni-capable antagonists on the front
lines. Theirs is a subtle art, weaving probabilities of lasting change through
very human interventions - as well as wading knee deep in the dead when
occasion demands it, to tip the scales of pivotal battles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regarding each other with wariness and respect, from across the gulf of
realities, they battle up the threads and down the braids of innumerable
possible pasts and futures. Until they begin sending what can only be
characterized as &lt;em&gt;letters&lt;/em&gt; to each other, albeit often encoded in startlingly
— poetically — obscure ways, so as to remain secret from their enemies and
their masters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Around these letters are formed the novel's tight, alternating structure,
reminding me of Bank's &lt;em&gt;Use of Weapons&lt;/em&gt;. Before you know it, their respect for
each other's skills has grown to full-blown giddy all-out love. But where to,
from there? Their communications to date are already traitorous - grounds for
terminal repercussions. Nowhen in the multiverse are they safe from their
respective commanders. Losing the time war would mean they no longer — had
never — existed. Winning the time war would mean the same for their opposite
number.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At which point, the novel cleverly folds back on itself - these are consummate
masters of time, and subtle but decisive influence, after all - to perform an
act of escapology, hinting to us that all their previous acts and letters could
be re-construed as having left a trail, ready to be exploited once the moment
was right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's a long way from my usual preference of hard-as-nails SF, but I loved it
nonetheless.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: left"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>fiction</category><category>media</category><category>novella</category><category>science-fiction</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/this-is-how-you-lose-the-time-war/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 17 Nov 2021 20:49:26 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Children of Time</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/children-of-time/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Children of Time cover" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2021/children-of-time-cover.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Adrian Tchaikovsky (2015)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lots of people love this, and it was jolly enough, but it just isn't for me. A
couple of times I toyed with the idea of invoking my new policy of abandoning
any book that isn't absolutely knocking my socks off - something I haven't
previously been in the habit of.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's unfair of me to compare one book with another, but partly, I was irked by
featuring an alien planet of spiders, that being so reminiscent of Vernor
Vinge's 1999 novel &lt;em&gt;A Deepness in the Sky&lt;/em&gt; (and he can hardly be the first to
play with that.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be fair, Tchaikovsky's spider civilization definitely exhibits more
thought-out arachnid sensibilities, whereas Vinge's act more like a Dickensian
family drama - "Button up warm, childlings!" "Yes, Daddy!". But Vinge was there
first, and has such a high profile, being a sequel to a much-loved Hugo winner,
that it casts a shadow on anything else following on the same path.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Partly, also, I've been spoiled by hard science fiction from people like
Peter Watts - real scientists, who are devastatingly smart, and are not afraid
to dazzle their readers with it, even if that makes it a little hard going at
times. Something about Children of Time was just too easygoing for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: left"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>fiction</category><category>media</category><category>novel</category><category>science-fiction</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/children-of-time/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 10 Nov 2021 20:58:50 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Buried Giant</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/the-buried-giant/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="The Buried Giant cover" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2021/the-buried-giant-cover.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Kazuo Ishiguro, 2015&lt;/em&gt; &lt;img alt="spoilers" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/spoilers.svg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A mythical tale, set in post-Arthurian England. Author Kazuo Ishiguro, Nobel
prize winner for literature, is also famous for Klara and the Sun, Never Let
Me Go, and The Remains of the Day (yes, that one about butlers.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ishiguro moved from Japan to England as a young child, and his insightful
observation of English and Western culture and myth benefits from that
transplant's perspective - at once deeply at home in England, and also
an outsider to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The tale is populated by ragged peoples, affected by a pervasive amnesia.
Elderly couple Axl and Beatrice abruptly decide to leave their village of damp,
hobbit-like underground burrows to visit a son they'd forgotten they had.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Simlarly, other characters are inspired by a variety of classical sources, from
Beowulf to Arthur's knight and nephew Sir Gawain, now old and prone to quixotic
rants - hinting at the subconscious conflict his code of honor has with the
dark means by which he and other knights formerly helped Arthur achieve the
current uneasy peace between native Britons and invading Saxons, now occupying
villages across the land.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The journey is perilous, encountering roaming ogres and deadly pixies, not
to mention soldiers of the local lords, and deadly conflicts within the party
itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But any action is relayed with cool distance. Either through the pervasive
mental fog, or using expert fighters' clinical analysis of the minutia of
stance or grip, or by foretelling the ebb and flow of a battle by analysing the
terrain, then allowing the battle itself to take place off stage, only assumed
to have happened, by characters who weren't there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This muted indirectness is entirely in keeping with the ambiguous, dreamlike
style of the book, which is heightened by the sing-song formalism of the
characters' medieval speech, and the narrator's occasional surreal hint of
relating this tale to contemporaries who live in some other, unidentifiable,
historic time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The journey eventually comes to revolve around the dispatch - or defence - of a
dragon that is said to be the source of everyone's forgetfulness, and as this
goal approaches, vague fears surface of what might be remembered when the
mist lifts. Will Axl and Beatrice's treasured relationship survive the
revelations of their pasts? Will the longstanding truce in the land survive
the remembering of wartime battles and atrocities? Will Saxon resentment at
Arthur's desperate misdeeds be stoked into resumption of the violent war of
invasion? This is left unresolved by the novel's end, but as reader, we know
that the Saxons did ultimately conquer all of England, displacing the Britons
culturally and politically, and probably murdering a good number of them along
the way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Personally, I'm minded to think of ancient England here as being a root of
modern Western culture, and the mist as an allegory for the bland ignorance of
our own culture's atrocities. The deliberate forgetting, like the mist, clouds
all our conciousnesses, making it hard for us to remember who we are. Why we're
here. The silent resentment of crushed minorities and genocide survivors forms
a pressure, struggling against the placating narrative that everything's OK
now. But, contained, the pressure builds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Truly a buried giant, indeed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: left"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>fantasy</category><category>fiction</category><category>ishiguro</category><category>media</category><category>novel</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/the-buried-giant/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 25 Oct 2021 15:16:53 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Permanent Record</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/permanent-record/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Permanent Record" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2021/permanent-record-cover.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Edward Snowden, 2019&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I really enjoyed this memoir. The story is familiar, but intriguing to hear
in the characteristically articulate words of Snowden himself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He recounts growing up as a computer nerd in a family dedicated to military
service, punctuated by startling scenes such as being caught in the pandemonium
outside NSA headquarters as it was evacuated during 9/11, and the subsequent
overreach of surveillance capability that triggered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He describes the interesting parts of his ascent through jobs, and clearance
levels, within the intelligence community, and how he came to slowly suspect —
and later confirm — that the government was collecting all the communications
and transactions, from everyone who touched a phone or computer, in America and
across the world. A vast spying mechanism turned upon the populace, beyond the
wildest dreams of the Stasi, who only surveilled one third of their population.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At "Constitution Day" in the office, a forlorn desk in the cafeteria hands
out copies of the constitution, which his clearance had required that he, and
his colleagues, swear an oath to uphold. He quoted the 4th amendment to
colleagues:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;"The right of the people to be secure in their persons, houses, papers, and
effects, against unreasonable searches and seizures, shall not be violated."&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The responses were dead-eyed shrugs - yeah, sure, but what can you do? What
indeed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He describes the dangers of a government given too much power to spy on
the everyday lives of its citizens, and the crisis of conscience that slowly
lead to his decision to let the American people know that they were being spied
upon, and his planning of how to go about it. How he slowly accumulated the
hundreds of documents needed to reveal the full extent and capabilities of the
spying apparatus. The extraction of those documents, hidden on his person on
micro SD cards, concealed in places such as in a Rubik's cube he routinely
carried through security. The months long process of selecting journalists who
could both communicate the material coherently to the public, and vet the
public releases to eliminate the risk to our undercover personnel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His recounts the preparations for flight, tying up his affairs like a man about
to die. Emptying bank accounts, leaving cash for his girlfriend to find.
Leaving the house tidy and repaired. The necessity of flight, to avoid a show
trial, devoid of any meaningful defense. A whistle-blower is not allowed to
argue that their disclosures were civilly beneficial. Even now, when Snowden's
leaks have caused Congress to change laws regarding surveillance, or caused the
courts to strike down types of mass surveillance programs as illegal, or caused
both the Attorney General and the President of the United States to admit that
the resulting debate over mass surveillance was a crucial one for the public to
have. All these claims would be dismissed by the court as not just irrelevant,
but inadmissible, leading to a sentence of up to ten years per leaked document.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And finally, flight itself. A tense series of airplanes and delays, meeting the
selected journalists in Hong Kong, selected for being sufficiently disjoint
from Chinese rule so as not to taint his revelations with the suspicion of
having sold out to China, but still sufficiently lawful, and under the auspices
of the distant Chinese rule, that that the American government would not snatch
him off the street with impunity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The indulgence of the Hong Kong government fell apart, as the US filed for
extradition. He fled bound for Ecuador, but was pulled aside during a 20-hour
layover in a Moscow airport, for a conversation with Russian intelligence,
during which Snowden insists he will not work with them, he only wants to catch
his flight out. They reveal to him that he cannot leave, since the US State
department has cancelled his passport. He is stranded in Moscow airport for 40
days, and eventually granted temporary asylum in Russia. Eventually, his
girlfriend — who knew nothing about his plans — recovered from the shock of his
unannounced departure, moved out to Moscow to be with him, and then a year
later, they were married.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: both"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>law</category><category>media</category><category>memoir</category><category>non-fiction</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/permanent-record/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 10 Oct 2021 16:18:16 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>