<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>tartley.com</title><link>https://tartley.com/</link><description>Creating a website devoted to oneself has been described as the greatest act of hubris. Welcome aboard!</description><atom:link href="https://www.tartley.com/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2021 &lt;a href="mailto:tartley @ the domain tartley dot com"&gt;Jonathan Hartley&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 12 Dec 2021 17:19:10 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Creating Animated Meme GIFs on the Command-Line</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/creating-animated-meme-gifs-on-the-command-line/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Got sick of navigating the limitations of various online services to create
animated gif memes, finally figured out how to do it manually. Not a universal
process, just what worked for my situation. (Which is Ubuntu 21.10, "Impish".)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of of the ffmpeg invocations could probably be combined into one, but I
show the commands as I used them, as I was figuring each step out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;1. Download a video&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Starting from a video on YouTube:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/6-gJMs6DwuE" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To download this locally,
&lt;a href="https://github.com/ytdl-org/youtube-dl"&gt;install &lt;code&gt;youtube-dl&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;,
hit the YouTube &lt;em&gt;share&lt;/em&gt; button to grab the video's encoded URL,
and:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;youtube-dl https://youtu.be/6-gJMs6DwuE -o Ash.mp4
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This gives me an 850KB .mp4 video file.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;2. Split&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I only want the final few seconds. To remove the start of the video,
keeping from 6.5 seconds until the end:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;ffmpeg -hide_banner -i Ash.mp4 -acodec copy -vcodec libx264 -ss 00:00:06.5 Ash-split.mp4
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Args to ffmpeg are position sensitive. Specifying '-ss' (to split the file)
before the input ('-i') can't create the split at an accurate location, since
it has to guess whereabouts in the file the given timestamp will occur. But
putting it after the input (as done here) means it can split accurately on the
given timestamp, since the file has been processed by the time this arg gets
actioned, so accurate timestamp/frame conversion is known, at the cost of
having had to process even the parts of the video that are then discarded.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vcodec of libx264 is specified because, according to stackoverflow,
"&lt;a href="https://stackoverflow.com/questions/5651654/ffmpeg-how-to-split-video-efficiently#comment85070704_13289426"&gt;scenes in mp4 are broken&lt;/a&gt;", whatever that means,
and specifying "copy", as most people do, gives me an output with no video,
only audio.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This results in a three second, 217KB .mp4 video file. (the following is just an
image of it).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="ash-split.webp" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2021/ash-split.webp"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;3. Crop&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To crop out the black bars from the top and bottom:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;ffmpeg -hide_banner -i Ash-split.mp4 -vf 'crop=iw:365' Ash-split-crop.mp4
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here, we crop it to the input width "iw", and 365 high. In the absense of
any offset ordinates for the crop, ffmpeg defaults to centering them, so this
365 pixels are taken from the (spatial, vertical) middle of the video, which is
exactly what we want.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This results in a three second, 220KB .mp4 video file.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="ash-split-crop.webp" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2021/ash-split-crop.webp"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;4. Resize and convert to gif&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class="s s-Atom"&gt;ffmpeg&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s s-Atom"&gt;hide_banner&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s s-Atom"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;Ash&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s s-Atom"&gt;split&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s s-Atom"&gt;crop&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s s-Atom"&gt;mp4&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s s-Atom"&gt;vf&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s s-Atom"&gt;'scale=512:-1'&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;Ash&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s s-Atom"&gt;split&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s s-Atom"&gt;crop&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s s-Atom"&gt;resize&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s s-Atom"&gt;gif&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This results in a grainy-but-passable three second 750KB animated .gif:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="ash-split-crop-resize.gif" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2021/ash-split-crop-resize.gif"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The file size can be smaller, if you care, most easily by splitting a shorter
video clip, reducing the frame rate, or reducing the 'scale' in this step.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alternately, this could be done using ImageMagik's 'convert', but the result
of that was a very large (10MB) file and played very slowly, and I wasn't
immediately sure how to fix that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;5. Add text&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using Imagemagik's 'convert':&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;convert \
    Ash-split-crop-resize.gif \
    -coalesce \
    -font impact -pointsize 36 -fill white -stroke black -strokewidth 2 \
    -gravity north -annotate +0+0 'I can''t lie about your chances, but' \
    -gravity south -annotate +0+0 'you have my sympathies' \
    -layers Optimize \
    Ash-split-crop-resize-text.gif
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The '-coalesce' option removes all the .gif optimizations, then we apply the
text labels, then the '-layers' option re-applies optimizations. Without this
dance, the text is all twitchy and messy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Voilà. Imagine sending it to a co-worker who is taking on a difficult task,
like making changes to that thorny section of the codebase that nobody likes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="ash-split-crop-resize-text.gif" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2021/ash-split-crop-resize-text.gif"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>image</category><category>linux</category><category>terminal</category><category>til</category><category>video</category><category>youtube</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/creating-animated-meme-gifs-on-the-command-line/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 08 Dec 2021 21:32:10 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Subnautica: Below Zero</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/subnautica-below-zero/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;on Windows, published 2021&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;img alt="spoilers" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/spoilers.svg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://subnautica.fandom.com/wiki/Subnautica_Wiki"&gt;Subnautica&lt;/a&gt;,
and its icy sequel,
"&lt;a href="https://subnautica.fandom.com/wiki/Subnautica:_Below_Zero"&gt;Below Zero&lt;/a&gt;",
have perhaps been my favorite
games of the last few years. The majority of their run time takes place under
the colorful waters of an alien ocean. It's been a joy to sit side-by-size
with Zander for tense scuba cave dives, or piloting vehicles through
vertiginous underwater cave systems, headlights straining through the murk to
reveal wonders. It has inspired
&lt;a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/Subnautica_Below_Zero/comments/r82l3i/birthday_cake_no_spoilers/"&gt;cake&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Part of the games take place on land though. I &lt;em&gt;started&lt;/em&gt; drawing a map of Below
Zero's Glacial Basin region just to keep track of where we'd been. To make sure
we visited all the locations, found all the MacGuffins (I'm looking at &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt;,
pesky antidote), and experienced all that there was to experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But as those goals approached completion, I &lt;em&gt;finished&lt;/em&gt; drawing it because it
had become a therapeutic experience. Happily exploring away, mesmerised by the
scenery, avoiding hostile wildlife, uncovering the ruins of ancient alien
artifacts. Reckoning distances by eye, scribbling down what we found, updating
and correcting the map as we went. Being lost in the experience. Simply a joy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/Subnautica_Below_Zero/comments/qutkqz/hand_drawn_map_of_southern_glacial_region_wip/"&gt;Reddit is encouraging me&lt;/a&gt;
to tackle the tricky Actic Spires area, too. &lt;em&gt;&amp;lt;Rubs hands&amp;gt;...&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Subnautica screenshot" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2021/subnatica-below-zero-map-glacial-basin.png"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: left"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>map</category><category>media</category><category>videogame</category><category>windows</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/subnautica-below-zero/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 22 Nov 2021 22:24:22 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Starship Troopers</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/starship-troopers/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Starship Troopers cover" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2021/starship-troopers-cover.webp"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Robert Heinlein, 1959.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My first time reading this classic old Hugo winner. I'd seen the 1995 movie
many years ago, which is clearly a satire, highlighting the fascistic
tendencies of the dedicated military discipline required for humanity to
survive in a dog-eat-dog galaxy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But was that Heinlein's original intent? I don't detect that in my reading of
it. The text seems, to my eyes, to be a straight-up endorsement and
glorification of military discipline, corporal and capital punishment, and
withholding citizenship from people who haven't served in the military.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've seen people argue that, as an expert writer, Heinlein knew precisely what
he was doing, and didn't need to draw attention to his critiques of fascism in
the text in order for an astute reader to realize that not everything espoused
by the novel is necessarily good, or corresponds with the author's viewpoint.
We are still discussing the novel 60 years later, and its relationship to
fascism, so he has achieved his goal of getting us to think about it. After
all, didn't Heinlein write this partway through his drafting of what would
become &lt;em&gt;Stranger in a Strange Land&lt;/em&gt;, which features hippy sexual freedom, and
&lt;em&gt;Troopers&lt;/em&gt; itself contains nods to racial and gender equality (albeit these are
somewhat ham-fisted.) Hence, say some, Heinlein was would not genuinely have
intended to advocate militaristic or fascist views.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm not convinced. It seems entirely possible that Heinlein was in favor of
sexual freedoms, while in other regards advocating staunch militarism. He
wrote &lt;em&gt;Troopers&lt;/em&gt; directly in response to the US suspending nuclear weapons
testing, which he wished to see resume. According to Wikipedia he stated at the
time that he used the novel to clarify his military and political views, such
as that the USA was too conciliatory in its dealings with China and the Soviet
Union. In the book, the "bugs" - alien enemies, are explicitly referred to as
communist, and depicted as mostly mindless drones, for which the only solution
is eradication.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So. I don't agree with the author's outlook, and wasn't convinced by the book's
interpretation of civics, and passages of moralizing. But it was an
interesting, albeit naturally dated, read, to see what successful military
SF looked like 60 years ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: left"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>media</category><category>novel</category><category>science-fiction</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/starship-troopers/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 20 Nov 2021 18:19:44 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>This Is How You Lose the Time War</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/this-is-how-you-lose-the-time-war/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="This Is How You Lose the Time War cover" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2021/this-is-how-you-lose-the-time-war-cover.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Amal El-Mohtar &amp;amp; Max Gladstone, 2019&lt;/em&gt; &lt;img alt="spoilers" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/spoilers.svg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's a marvellous literary romp, deploying the tropes and language of science
fiction to deliver a scintillatingly poetic payload of — dare I say it —
credible romance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The combatants in the Time War seek to bring about historical outcomes which
predispose those futures which will result in the generation of their own
particular civilisation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In one future, humans have embraced machine-oriented augmentation, uploads,
and all that that implies. In the other, transformation is wrought by
biological means, accepting humankind's role as a part of a natural ecosystem,
boostrapping the whole to greatness by a ruthless application of evolutionary
principles. Each finds the other repulsive, and their existence is mutually
exclusive. From our perspective, they appear equally awe-inspiring and terrible
to behold.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, as intriguing as all that is, it's not why we're here. Instead we get
the much more personal accounts of two omni-capable antagonists on the front
lines. Theirs is a subtle art, weaving probabilities of lasting change through
very human interventions - as well as wading knee deep in the dead when
occasion demands it, to tip the scales of pivotal battles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regarding each other with wariness and respect, from across the gulf of
realities, they battle up the threads and down the braids of innumerable
possible pasts and futures. Until they begin sending what can only be
characterized as &lt;em&gt;letters&lt;/em&gt; to each other, albeit often encoded in startlingly
— poetically — obscure ways, so as to remain secret from their enemies and
their masters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Around these letters are formed the novel's tight, alternating structure,
reminding me of Bank's &lt;em&gt;Use of Weapons&lt;/em&gt;. Before you know it, their respect for
each other's skills has grown to full-blown giddy all-out love. But where to,
from there? Their communications to date are already traitorous - grounds for
terminal repercussions. Nowhen in the multiverse are they safe from their
respective commanders. Losing the time war would mean they no longer — had
never — existed. Winning the time war would mean the same for their opposite
number.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At which point, the novel cleverly folds back on itself - these are consummate
masters of time, and subtle but decisive influence, after all - to perform an
act of escapology, hinting to us that all their previous acts and letters could
be re-construed as having left a trail, ready to be exploited once the moment
was right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's a long way from my usual preference of hard-as-nails SF, but I loved it
nonetheless.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: left"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>fiction</category><category>media</category><category>novella</category><category>science-fiction</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/this-is-how-you-lose-the-time-war/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 17 Nov 2021 20:49:26 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Children of Time</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/children-of-time/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Children of Time cover" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2021/children-of-time-cover.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Adrian Tchaikovsky (2015)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lots of people love this, and it was jolly enough, but it just isn't for me. A
couple of times I toyed with the idea of invoking my new policy of abandoning
any book that isn't absolutely knocking my socks off - something I haven't
previously been in the habit of.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's unfair of me to compare one book with another, but partly, I was irked by
featuring an alien planet of spiders, that being so reminiscent of Vernor
Vinge's 1999 novel &lt;em&gt;A Deepness in the Sky&lt;/em&gt; (and he can hardly be the first to
play with that.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be fair, Tchaikovsky's spider civilization definitely exhibits more
thought-out arachnid sensibilities, whereas Vinge's act more like a Dickensian
family drama - "Button up warm, childlings!" "Yes, Daddy!". But Vinge was there
first, and has such a high profile, being a sequel to a much-loved Hugo winner,
that it casts a shadow on anything else following on the same path.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Partly, also, I've been spoiled by hard science fiction from people like
Peter Watts - real scientists, who are devastatingly smart, and are not afraid
to dazzle their readers with it, even if that makes it a little hard going at
times. Something about Children of Time was just too easygoing for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: left"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>media</category><category>novel</category><category>science-fiction</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/children-of-time/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 10 Nov 2021 20:58:50 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Buried Giant</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/the-buried-giant/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="The Buried Giant cover" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2021/the-buried-giant-cover.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Kazuo Ishiguro, 2015&lt;/em&gt; &lt;img alt="spoilers" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/spoilers.svg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A mythical tale, set in post-Arthurian England. Author Kazuo Ishiguro, Nobel
prize winner for literature, is also famous for Klara and the Sun, Never Let
Me Go, and The Remains of the Day (yes, that one about butlers.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ishiguro moved from Japan to England as a young child, and his insightful
observation of English and Western culture and myth benefits from that
transplant's perspective - at once deeply at home in England, and also
an outsider to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The tale is populated by ragged peoples, affected by a pervasive amnesia.
Elderly couple Axl and Beatrice abruptly decide to leave their village of damp,
hobbit-like underground burrows to visit a son they'd forgotten they had.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Simlarly, other characters are inspired by a variety of classical sources, from
Beowulf to Arthur's knight and nephew Sir Gawain, now old and prone to quixotic
rants - hinting at the subconscious conflict his code of honor has with the
dark means by which he and other knights formerly helped Arthur achieve the
current uneasy peace between native Britons and invading Saxons, now occupying
villages across the land.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The journey is perilous, encountering roaming ogres and deadly pixies, not
to mention soldiers of the local lords, and deadly conflicts within the party
itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But any action is relayed with cool distance. Either through the pervasive
mental fog, or using expert fighters' clinical analysis of the minutia of
stance or grip, or by foretelling the ebb and flow of a battle by analysing the
terrain, then allowing the battle itself to take place off stage, only assumed
to have happened, by characters who weren't there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This muted indirectness is entirely in keeping with the ambiguous, dreamlike
style of the book, which is heightened by the sing-song formalism of the
characters' medieval speech, and the narrator's occasional surreal hint of
relating this tale to contemporaries who live in some other, unidentifiable,
historic time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The journey eventually comes to revolve around the dispatch - or defence - of a
dragon that is said to be the source of everyone's forgetfulness, and as this
goal approaches, vague fears surface of what might be remembered when the
mist lifts. Will Axl and Beatrice's treasured relationship survive the
revelations of their pasts? Will the longstanding truce in the land survive
the remembering of wartime battles and atrocities? Will Saxon resentment at
Arthur's desperate misdeeds be stoked into resumption of the violent war of
invasion? This is left unresolved by the novel's end, but as reader, we know
that the Saxons did ultimately conquer all of England, displacing the Britons
culturally and politically, and probably murdering a good number of them along
the way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Personally, I'm minded to think of ancient England here as being a root of
modern Western culture, and the mist as an allegory for the bland ignorance of
our own culture's atrocities. The deliberate forgetting, like the mist, clouds
all our conciousnesses, making it hard for us to remember who we are. Why we're
here. The silent resentment of crushed minorities and genocide survivors forms
a pressure, struggling against the placating narrative that everything's OK
now. But, contained, the pressure builds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Truly a buried giant, indeed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: left"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>fantasy</category><category>fiction</category><category>media</category><category>novel</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/the-buried-giant/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 25 Oct 2021 15:16:53 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Permanent Record</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/permanent-record/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Permanent Record" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2021/permanent-record-cover.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Edward Snowden, 2019&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I really enjoyed this memoir. The story is familiar, but intriguing to hear
in the characteristically articulate words of Snowden himself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He recounts growing up as a computer nerd in a family dedicated to military
service, punctuated by startling scenes such as being caught in the pandemonium
outside NSA headquarters as it was evacuated during 9/11, and the subsequent
overreach of surveillance capability that triggered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He describes the interesting parts of his ascent through jobs, and clearance
levels, within the intelligence community, and how he came to slowly suspect —
and later confirm — that the government was collecting all the communications
and transactions, from everyone who touched a phone or computer, in America and
across the world. A vast spying mechanism turned upon the populace, beyond the
wildest dreams of the Stasi, who only surveilled one third of their population.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At "Constitution Day" in the office, a forlorn desk in the cafeteria hands
out copies of the constitution, which his clearance had required that he, and
his colleagues, swear an oath to uphold. He quoted the 4th amendment to
colleagues:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;"The right of the people to be secure in their persons, houses, papers, and
effects, against unreasonable searches and seizures, shall not be violated."&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The responses were dead-eyed shrugs - yeah, sure, but what can you do? What
indeed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He describes the dangers of a government given too much power to spy on
the everyday lives of its citizens, and the crisis of conscience that slowly
lead to his decision to let the American people know that they were being spied
upon, and his planning of how to go about it. How he slowly accumulated the
hundreds of documents needed to reveal the full extent and capabilities of the
spying apparatus. The extraction of those documents, hidden on his person on
micro SD cards, concealed in places such as in a Rubik's cube he routinely
carried through security. The months long process of selecting journalists who
could both communicate the material coherently to the public, and vet the
public releases to eliminate the risk to our undercover personnel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His recounts the preparations for flight, tying up his affairs like a man about
to die. Emptying bank accounts, leaving cash for his girlfriend to find.
Leaving the house tidy and repaired. The necessity of flight, to avoid a show
trial, devoid of any meaningful defense. A whistle-blower is not allowed to
argue that their disclosures were civilly beneficial. Even now, when Snowden's
leaks have caused Congress to change laws regarding surveillance, or caused the
courts to strike down types of mass surveillance programs as illegal, or caused
both the Attorney General and the President of the United States to admit that
the resulting debate over mass surveillance was a crucial one for the public to
have. All these claims would be dismissed by the court as not just irrelevant,
but inadmissible, leading to a sentence of up to ten years per leaked document.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And finally, flight itself. A tense series of airplanes and delays, meeting the
selected journalists in Hong Kong, selected for being sufficiently disjoint
from Chinese rule so as not to taint his revelations with the suspicion of
having sold out to China, but still sufficiently lawful, and under the auspices
of the distant Chinese rule, that that the American government would not snatch
him off the street with impunity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The indulgence of the Hong Kong government fell apart, as the US filed for
extradition. He fled bound for Ecuador, but was pulled aside during a 20-hour
layover in a Moscow airport, for a conversation with Russian intelligence,
during which Snowden insists he will not work with them, he only wants to catch
his flight out. They reveal to him that he cannot leave, since the US State
department has cancelled his passport. He is stranded in Moscow airport for 40
days, and eventually granted temporary asylum in Russia. Eventually, his
girlfriend — who knew nothing about his plans — recovered from the shock of his
unannounced departure, moved out to Moscow to be with him, and then a year
later, they were married.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: both"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>law</category><category>media</category><category>memoir</category><category>non-fiction</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/permanent-record/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 10 Oct 2021 16:18:16 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Manifold Garden</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/manifold-garden/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Manifold Garden screenshot" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2021/manifold-garden.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Windows, 2019&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was always going to turn my head, marrying a marvellous geometric engine
to an austere, flat-shaded renderer. Bewildering portals, seamlessly disguised
as humble doorways, are the simplest of its tricks. More pervasive, levels are
wraparound along all three spatial dimensions, as can be seen by the
disorienting arrays of geometry - the current level, infinitely repeated,
offset or re-oriented - marching to the vanishing points, dwindling to infinity
in all directions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is no mere trippy backdrop. Gravity can be trivially flipped to lie along
any cardinal axis, and one will routinely step off, into a yawning, infinite
abyss, to fall through the entire level, and beyond, through and amongst the
infinite constellations of geometry, airsteering all the way, to land,
unharmed, anywhere that's exposed to the direction you're falling from. It
becomes a form of teleportation, used to get from A to B almost as frequently
as simply walking around.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This non-Euclidean wrapping is baked deeply into the visuals, the engine, and
the gameplay. But for all that technical mastery, the puzzles themselves aren't
as deep and creative and varied as those in the ostensibly similar, but
less technically accomplished, &lt;em&gt;Antichamber&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having said that, there's something entirely appropriate in this. The puzzles
end up being as much rituals as a head-scratchers, holy spatial rites one
performs to unleash the deeply evocative visuals towards the end of each level
- a faceted and angular psychedelic, coupled with unnerving reformulations of
reality straight out of Farbrausch's
&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=wqu_IpkOYBg"&gt;Debris&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. By the final level,
this crescendos in scenes reminiscent of &lt;em&gt;2001: A Space Odyssey&lt;/em&gt;, profound in
both the intimacy of my commune with godhood, and in my continued inability to
understand what I had achieved. Created a universe, probably? Yeah, probably.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>completed</category><category>media</category><category>videogame</category><category>windows</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/manifold-garden/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 05 Oct 2021 03:16:08 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Glass Bead Game</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/the-glass-bead-game-by-hermann-hesse-1943/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="The Glass Bead Game cover" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2021/glass-bead-game-cover.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Hermann Hesse (1943). Translated from German to English with evident
devotion and expertise by Clara Winston &amp;amp; Richard Winston.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;img alt="spoilers" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/spoilers.svg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This novel is described by some as the culmination of Hesse's career, for
which he received a Nobel Prize for Literature. Many reviews on
&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/16634.The_Glass_Bead_Game"&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;
cite it as a life-changing novel, or as a singular all-time favorite book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I must confess with some sadness that I must have entirely missed the point. I
have not enjoyed it &lt;em&gt;at all&lt;/em&gt;. The number of books I failed to finish in my
life is surely less than five, and this very nearly became one of them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first half describes Knecht's education and career within the rarefied
academic atmosphere of some distant future European state's "pedagogical
province", wherein (exclusively male) scholars devote their time to
mastery of the titular game. This relies upon drawing deep relationships
between all fields of human study, such as music and biology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Knecht is talented and likeable, and rises effortlessly through the ranks,
without exhibiting any real volition of his own, other than being naturally
predisposed to study, and having an instinct for drawing out the best in
people. He is ultimately assigned to the highest office in the land, without
encountering any substantive antagonist or difficulty along the way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The mechanics of the game itself, about which all this ostensibly revolves, is
deliberately never explained, other than poetic references to glass beads
being used to exquisitely interrelate insights or concepts from multiple fields
of study.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This first half of the book bored me to absolute tears. If I had to find a
single word to describe Knecht, despite his diligence, it would be "inactive".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the halfway point through the book, this serenity is interrupted by
Knecht making the controversial decision to quit, not just from his exalted
post, but from the whole system over which it rules. He leaves the insular
academic province entirely, to begin a new life, subject to more real-world
constraints. Just at this very moment, as the narrative becomes interesting,
this section abruptly ends in a very unexpected manner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Out of the whole book, this moment resonates with me. Knecht has spent a life
devoted to scholarly thought, but after many decades he throws off the
expectations of that life to forge his own path. Mere days after that decision,
a moment of physical exertion proves to be his sudden undoing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Does this show that Knecht should have more highly valued the protections from
the physical world that his intellectual castle provided? That someone raised
in such a cosseted environment was unsuitable to face the rigors of the real
world? Or should I instead observe that, despite his ostensible success and
satisfaction with life, in waiting so long before daring to strike out on his
own, and then find days later that his time was up, Knecht has in some ways
wasted his life doing something other than what he really wanted to do?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Neither of these seem particularly compelling to me, nor sufficient for
the larger themes that I suspect the book might actually be grappling with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second half of the book contains various poems, written by Knecht when he
was younger, containing premonitions of his aspirations and his doubts. It ends
with three short tales, each describing an alternate life that Knecht might
have lived in other times. Apparently early drafts had these tales being
literal other lives Knecht was reincarnated into. But in the published book,
they are presented without context, and I think it is only by consensus
that they are commonly understood to be grouped with the earlier poems as
examples of Knecht's writing - his imagination of other lives he might have
lived.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I did not understand the relevance of these tales to the larger portion of
the book, other than the way they forcefully contrast with it, by immersing
Knecht in emotional and painful tales of life embedded within a wider society,
rather than abstractly observing its achievements from without. As such,
they force him into action, and to me they are more engaging for it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wikipedia informs me that each of the four tales of Knecht's life focuses on a
different basic aspect of analytical psychology: thinking (Magister Ludi),
sensation (The Rainmaker), intuition (Indian life) and feeling (The Father
Confessor). Similarly, several of the book's characters who had influence on
Knecht are thinly-veiled references to real world people, some famous such
as Friedrich Nietzsche, others being acquaintances of the author.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of which seems reasonable, but doesn't really help me understand what I
just read. Perhaps each tale of Knecht, in focussing on one human trait,
is lacking because it undervalues the other three. Perhaps. ¯\&lt;em&gt;(ツ)&lt;/em&gt;/¯&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>media</category><category>novel</category><category>science-fiction</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/the-glass-bead-game-by-hermann-hesse-1943/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 20 Aug 2021 18:37:25 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Keyboard CoolerMaster CK530's Missing Manual</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/keyboard-coolermaster-ck530s-missing-manual/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;I have a
&lt;a href="https://www.coolermaster.com/catalog/peripheral/keyboards/ck530/"&gt;CoolerMaster CK530&lt;/a&gt;
mechanical keyboard, which I love. It might have come with a small printed
manual, but if it did, I no longer have it, and I'm failing to find one online.
Here's are some things I've gleaned from experimentation.
If there's a manual I've overlooked, or if you have corrections,
&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/tartley"&gt;let me know&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://coolermaster.egnyte.com/dl/8NuIc843wQ/?"&gt;Quickstart guide&lt;/a&gt;
provides a list of key strokes, but no explanations. I've reproduced
the table here, with tweaks for understandability, and added more descriptions
below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Select a mode &lt;br&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;fn + F5&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Cycle modes.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;fn + F8&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Demo (automatically cycles through modes).&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Tweak mode &lt;br&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;fn + F1&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Cycle 8 color variations of the current mode.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;fn + F2&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Red level 0-9.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;fn + F3&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Green level 0-9.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;fn + F4&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Blue level 0-9.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;fn + F6&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Foreground color. (See &lt;a href="https://www.tartley.com/posts/keyboard-coolermaster-ck530s-missing-manual/#foreground-and-background-colors"&gt;below&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;fn + F7&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Background color.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;fn + Up&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Faster.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;fn + Down&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Slower.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;fn + Left&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Forwards.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;fn + Right&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Backwards.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;fn + F10&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;In "custom" mode, define color of each key.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Profiles &lt;br&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;fn + Esc&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Default profile&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;fn + 1&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Profile 1 (see mnemonic "P1" - "P4" on sides of these keys)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;fn + 2&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Profile 2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;fn + 3&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Profile 3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;fn + 4&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Profile 4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;fn + r&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Reset current profile to default appearance. (Hold 3 secs.)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;fn + e&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Reset all profiles to default appearance. (Hold 3 secs.)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Macros &lt;br&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;fn + F11&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Record a macro&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;fn + F12&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Delete macro&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;fn + PrtSc&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Single&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;fn + ScrLk&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Infinite loop&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;fn + Pause&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Repeat&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Media &lt;br&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;fn + Ins&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Play / pause&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;fn + Home&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Next track&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;fn + Del&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Stop&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;fn + End&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Previous track&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;fn + PgUp&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Volume up&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;fn + PgDown&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Volume down&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Lock &lt;br&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;fn + F9&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Cycle unlocked(off) / lock windows key(red) / lock whole keyboard(green)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many of these are self-explanatory. For the rest:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Using modes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;fn&lt;/code&gt; is the "Coolermaster" key, on the bottom row key between right Windows and
right Ctrl.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When holding &lt;code&gt;fn&lt;/code&gt;, several keys might light up, depending on the current
mode:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;ESC/1/2/3/4&lt;/code&gt; - one of these keys flashes white to show which profile
  (see &lt;a href="https://www.tartley.com/posts/keyboard-coolermaster-ck530s-missing-manual/#profiles"&gt;below&lt;/a&gt;) is currently in use.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If the current mode allows you to select a color to use, then &lt;code&gt;F2/F3/F4&lt;/code&gt;
  will light up to show the currently selected color's levels of
  red/green/blue.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If the current mode allows &lt;em&gt;two&lt;/em&gt; colors to be set (foreground &amp;amp; background),
  then one of &lt;code&gt;F6/F7&lt;/code&gt; will flash white, to show which is currently affected. (See &lt;a href="https://www.tartley.com/posts/keyboard-coolermaster-ck530s-missing-manual/#foreground-and-background-colors"&gt;below&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pressing &lt;code&gt;fn + F5&lt;/code&gt; cycles through:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Mode&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align="center"&gt;Foreground&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align="center"&gt;. Background&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align="center"&gt;. Reactive.&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1. All off&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="center"&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="center"&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="center"&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2. Static (all one color)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="center"&gt;✅&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="center"&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="center"&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3. Rainbow wave&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="center"&gt;✅&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="center"&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="center"&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4. Crosshair&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="center"&gt;✅&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="center"&gt;✅&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="center"&gt;✅&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5. Reactive fade&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="center"&gt;✅&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="center"&gt;✅&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="center"&gt;✅&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;6. Custom (see &lt;a href="https://www.tartley.com/posts/keyboard-coolermaster-ck530s-missing-manual/#custom-mode"&gt;below&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="center"&gt;✅&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="center"&gt;✅&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="center"&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;7. Stars&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="center"&gt;✅&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="center"&gt;✅&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="center"&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;8. Rain&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="center"&gt;✅&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="center"&gt;✅&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="center"&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;9. Color cycle&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="center"&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="center"&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="center"&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;10. Breathing&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="center"&gt;✅&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="center"&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="center"&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;11. Ripple&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="center"&gt;✅&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="center"&gt;✅&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="center"&gt;✅&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;12. Reactive punch&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="center"&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="center"&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="center"&gt;✅&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;13. Arcing&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="center"&gt;✅&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="center"&gt;✅&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="center"&gt;✅&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;15. Fireball&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="center"&gt;✅&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="center"&gt;✅&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="center"&gt;✅&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;16. Tornado (color spin)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="center"&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="center"&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="center"&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;17. Reactive tornado&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="center"&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="center"&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="center"&gt;✅&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;18. Water ripple&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="center"&gt;✅&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="center"&gt;✅&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="center"&gt;✅&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;19. Snake&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="center"&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="center"&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="center"&gt;✅&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Modes marked "reactive" react to key-presses. Mostly this lights up a pattern
around the pressed key. In the case of "snake", you can play using the arrow
keys.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span id="foreground-and-background-colors"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Foreground &amp;amp; background colors&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many of the modes have a foreground effect that you can change the color of.
For example, in the &lt;em&gt;all-one-color&lt;/em&gt; mode (officially called "static")
you can select the color with which all keys are lit, using &lt;code&gt;fn + F2/F3/F4&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of the modes also have a second color, the background, that you can set
separately. You can see if a mode offers this by selecting the mode and holding
&lt;code&gt;fn&lt;/code&gt;. If this mode offers two settable colors, then either &lt;code&gt;F6&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;F7&lt;/code&gt; will
flash white, to show you which one you are currently setting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Press &lt;code&gt;fn + F6/F7&lt;/code&gt; to choose foreground or background,
then use &lt;code&gt;fn + F2/F3/F4&lt;/code&gt; to set it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span id="custom-mode"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Custom mode&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Custom (mode #6 above) lets the user assign a different color to each key.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;First, cycle through modes using &lt;code&gt;fn + F5&lt;/code&gt; until you reach custom mode.
   It can be tricky to identify when you've reached it. Use the list of modes
   above to help.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;While in custom mode, press &lt;code&gt;fn + F10&lt;/code&gt; to edit key colors.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Select a color using &lt;code&gt;fn + F2/F3/F4&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Press all the keys you want lit in the selected color. Pressing the same key
   again turns it unlit.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Repeat steps 3 &amp;amp; 4 for other color/key combinations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finally, save to your current profile (see &lt;a href="https://www.tartley.com/posts/keyboard-coolermaster-ck530s-missing-manual/#profiles"&gt;below&lt;/a&gt;) by holding
   &lt;code&gt;fn&lt;/code&gt; and pressing your current profile key (whichever of &lt;code&gt;Esc/1/2/3/4&lt;/code&gt; is
   flashing white.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some wrinkles:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can't manage to set a color for the &lt;code&gt;fn&lt;/code&gt; key itself, which always appears
unlit in this mode.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The caps lock key is unlit in this mode, unless caps lock is on.
Similarly, scroll lock seems to always be unlit for me in this mode,
although it is lit in other modes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you try to assign a color to whichever one of &lt;code&gt;Esc/1/2/3/4&lt;/code&gt; is lit white,
to indicate the active profile, then nothing visible happens, but it is
working. You have to save (step 6 above).
Then you can see whether you successfully assigned the color,
or pressed the key one too many times and left it unlit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While editing key colors, if you wait, without exit/saving, pressing nothing
for a minute or so, then key color editing times out, cancelling all your
changes since step 2.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span id="profiles"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Profiles&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are five "profiles", each of which can be used to save the current
state of the keyboard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The profiles are accessed using &lt;code&gt;fn + 1/2/3/4/Esc&lt;/code&gt;. &lt;code&gt;Esc&lt;/code&gt; is the "default"
profile. Current keyboard settings (e.g. illumination mode and customized
colors) can be saved to one of the five profiles, and then loaded back later.
Are macros stored in a profile? Don't know.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The current profile is shown when you hold &lt;code&gt;fn&lt;/code&gt;, by one of &lt;code&gt;1/2/3/4/Esc&lt;/code&gt;
flashing white. While keeping FN pressed:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pressing the flashing profile key will save the keyboard state to your
  current profile.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pressing any of the other profile keys will LOAD that profile,
  losing the current keyboard state.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hence, to save changes to an arbitrary profile, you need to select that
profile &lt;em&gt;before&lt;/em&gt; making the changes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When turning the keyboard on (ie. Plugging the USB cable into a computer),
the active profile will be whichever one was last active.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>hardware</category><category>keyboard</category><category>manual</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/keyboard-coolermaster-ck530s-missing-manual/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jul 2021 18:41:50 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>