<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Made out of meat (Posts about animation)</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://www.tartley.com/categories/animation.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2023 &lt;a href="mailto:tartley @ tartley dot com"&gt;Jonathan Hartley&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 21 Sep 2023 19:38:55 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Wall-E</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/wall-e/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="wall-e" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2009/01/wall-e.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Director: Andrew Stanton&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I resisted for quite a while, expecting cloying superficiality. I was
wrong. Or at least I &lt;em&gt;like&lt;/em&gt; this kind of cloying superficiality. Clearly
made with love by a truly dedicated army of master artisans. Featuring
sound effects from the same guru sound guy who worked on the original
Star Wars, along with an animation team who watched every single Buster
Keaton and Charlie Chaplin movie over their lunchtimes, to inspire them
in the ways of visual story telling. With a hardcore &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/General_Products_(Larry_Niven)#General_Products_Hull"&gt;Larry
Niven&lt;/a&gt;
reference and a serious environmental message in the background to boot.
Huge fun. I watched it twice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rating: 8/10 - Thoroughly engaging, emotive and humorous.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: left"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>animation</category><category>environment</category><category>fiction</category><category>media</category><category>movie</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/wall-e/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2009 05:39:38 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Simpsons Movie / Goodbye Forever</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/the-simpsons-movie-goodbye-forever/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="The Simpsons Movie" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2008/05/simpsonsmovie.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is, of course,
no point whatsoever in me posting a belated review of the Simpsons
Movie, which I and everyone else gleefully watched many months ago now.
To the now long abandoned discussions of its merit I have absolutely
nothing of value to contribute.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, that shall not dissuade me from posting this one anyway, since
such posts as these are not, as you might assume, for the benefit of my
readership, few and benighted as they might be, but instead form an
attempt to chart my media consumption habits for my own retrospective
perusal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was with some dismay, therefore, that I noted that this inverted
system of priorities is mirrored in the Herculean task of my reading of
other people's posts. Simply put, I seem to be reading other people's
blogs in order to make them feel good, upping their stats, making
complimentary comments, showing an interest, etc, etc, rather than for
my own benefit. Once this cold fact had impinged upon my conciousness, I
had only one course of action left open: Cold Turkey. That's right. No
more Google Reader.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abandoning the hampster wheel should free up a considerable amount of my
time for other activities, and I am keen to quantify that process, so I
will be keeping detailed logs of my time usage for a few days prior and
post the switchover, to ascertain exactly how many hours I previously
spent looking at labelled pictures of cats, which I will henceforth
presumably be free to spend looking at &lt;em&gt;actual&lt;/em&gt; labels on cats (or
possibly labels on &lt;em&gt;actual&lt;/em&gt; pictures of cats, let's not get overly
ambitious.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a final layer of delicious irony, I shall of course be blogging
comprehensively about the entire experience, however your collective
reactions to that will remain forever unknown to me. Henceforth you
should consider me to be a purely one-way conduit of information.
Goodbye forever.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: both"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>animation</category><category>imho</category><category>media</category><category>movie</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/the-simpsons-movie-goodbye-forever/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 08 May 2008 17:48:12 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Adventures of Prince Achmed (1926) at Latitude</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/latitude/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.latitudefestival.co.uk" title="Latitude Festival"&gt;&lt;img alt="Latitude Festival" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2007/07/latitude.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's summertime again, even in sodden old England, and that means it's
festival season. True to its image as one of the newer and smaller
festivals in the UK, Latitude had a good-natured crowd, diverse music -
albeit without many big-name bands, was laid-back and eclectic, and not
too muddy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.tartley.com/files/2007/07/prince-achmed.jpg" title="Prince Achmed"&gt;&lt;img alt="Prince Achmed" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2007/07/prince-achmed.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The defining highlight for me was a showing of &lt;em&gt;The Adventures of
Prince Achmed&lt;/em&gt; (1926) (&lt;a href="http://imdb.com/title/tt0015532/"&gt;IMDB&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Adventures_of_Prince_Achmed"&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;),
a beautiful rendition of tales from Arabian Nights, using stop-motion
shadow-puppetry, accompanied by a haunting live musical soundtrack by &lt;a href="http://www.myspace.com/littlesparta"&gt;Little
Sparta&lt;/a&gt;. I've wanted to see the movie for
ages - it is the oldest surviving feature-length animation, and was brought
about by the dedication of one woman, &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lotte_Reiniger,"&gt;Lotte
Reiniger&lt;/a&gt; who single-handedly
constructed all the cutouts in the movie using nothing more than scissors, and
then animated them all by hand.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>animation</category><category>gig</category><category>media</category><category>movie</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/latitude/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 16 Jul 2007 15:48:46 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>