<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Made out of meat (Posts about aronofsky)</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://www.tartley.com/categories/aronofsky.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2023 &lt;a href="mailto:tartley @ the domain tartley dot com"&gt;Jonathan Hartley&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 23 Aug 2023 18:34:53 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Religion, at last.</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/religion-at-last/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Rohan and I finally understood the movie &lt;a href="https://www.tartley.com/posts/religion-at-last/the-fountain"&gt;The
Fountain&lt;/a&gt; last night. I say finally - Rohan
has only ever seen the first and last 15 minutes (oh, how apt!) It's
fair to say it blew our minds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SPOILERS. Big time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;foun-tain &lt;em&gt;noun&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A spring or source of water; the source or head of a stream.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The source or origin of anything. The beginning. &lt;em&gt;Genesis&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She finally taught him that they get reborn. That's why she wasn't
afraid of dying any more. That's why the two of them meet over and over
through history. That's why he is so tearfully happy to realise he is
about to die. Because death is their road to immortality. To be reborn.
To live forever.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is how the tree of life grants immortality - by allowing them to
realise this. Nothing has changed, other than their own knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The conclusion of his journey, to reach the nebula with the tree, is
just in time for the end of the universe, which then immediately leaps
back into being again, a new Creation, in the fires of which, the First
Father is sacrificed on the tree of life, which blossoms anew. The
circle is completed. The ring, which was lost, is now found.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She tries to tell him, to help him fulfil his destiny, but he has to
figure it out for himself, at the proper time. He has to die in the
heart of the nebula, that his ashes might seed the tree of life into
blossoming anew in the fires of a new creation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;| "What do you think about that?" She asks him.
| "About what?"
| "About death as a creative act."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Izzy and Tom will be reborn in this new universe, too, many times down
the centuries of history. They will live an infinite number of lives
together. Forever. So long as he finds his way to the end of all things,
to renew the cycle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;| "Finish it." She told him.
| "I'm trying. I don't know how." He replies.
| "You do. You will."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He is Adam, who sustained his unnaturally extended life to the year 2500
by subsisting on of the tree of life. She is his Eve, who partook of the
tree of knowledge at the beginning. The trees are literally the self
same plant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is why the same scenes happen over and over. Until, in one of the
interminable infinity of cascading universes, something different
happens. Tommy changes his mind. It's a bona fide miracle. He exercises
his free will, does something differently this time around - He bails
out of work, to go walk with Izzy in the first snow. He has learned that
he can't save her. That he cannot, must not try to save her. For only in
death do they find rebirth, and the immortality she has promised him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rational, male left-brained mind can only comprehend so much. It is
limited to knowledge within the domain of individual lives' observable
horizons. Each of these lives is punctuated by death, which is to lose
all knowledge, all memories. Delineated by such singularities, the
rational mind can never encompass the whole picture. To understand more,
one needs to go beyond what can be known. One must believe in the things
beyond the singularity, things that can never be known. You must have
faith.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am religious, and there is no God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update 30/04/2007:&lt;/strong&gt; I suppose that the climactic event at the nebula
doesn't have to represent the end / creation of whole universes. It
could merely (!) represent the star at the core of the nebula collapsing
beyond the &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chandrasekhar_limit"&gt;Chandrasekhar
limit&lt;/a&gt;, and undergoing
spontaneous nova as a result. The corresponding storyline interpretation
being that, rather than spawning new iterations of whole universes, Adam
is instead seeding life in the formation of new solar systems, and so
spreading life across the galaxy. &lt;em&gt;My Conquistador&lt;/em&gt;, she calls him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update 05/05/2007:&lt;/strong&gt; added the dictionary definition at the head of
the page, judiciously snipped from
&lt;a href="http://dictionary.reference.com/browse/fountain"&gt;dictionary.com&lt;/a&gt; and
from the corresponding entry on
&lt;a href="http://thesaurus.reference.com/browse/fountain"&gt;thesaurus.com&lt;/a&gt;, and
couldn't resist various wording improvements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update 2018:&lt;/strong&gt; The director has stated unambiguously that the above
is all wrong.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>aronofsky</category><category>fiction</category><category>media</category><category>movie</category><category>the-fountain</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/religion-at-last/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 29 Apr 2007 12:36:26 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Fountain</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/the-fountain/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th style="text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2007/03/the-fountain.jpg"&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;Tommy prepares for the ultimate lesson in personal mortality.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Writer/Director: Darren Aronofsky.Starring: Hugh Jackman, Rachel Weisz. (2006)&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href="http://imdb.com/title/tt0414993/"&gt;&lt;img alt="Internet Movie Database" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2007/03/imdb.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;What if you could live forever?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Writer and Director Darren Aronofsky has a fierce and original talent,
as amply demonstrated by his previous successes, &lt;em&gt;Pi&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Requiem for a
Dream&lt;/em&gt;. Had I realised that &lt;em&gt;The Fountain&lt;/em&gt; was another one of his, then
perhaps I would have been marginally more prepared for it. In actuality,
caught dozing my way through an aeroplane flight one sunny afternoon, I
was somewhat blindsided by this millennia-spanning story of love, death
and rebirth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The thing is, it doesn't feel like Aronofsky's previous titles. It does
feel a lot like other audacious, wildly sentimental tales, such as
Crowe's &lt;em&gt;Vanilla Sky&lt;/em&gt;, or Soderbergh's &lt;em&gt;Solaris&lt;/em&gt;. Doubtless it will
polarise viewers. Those of a more cynical bent will snigger at the
pretentious triple-stranded narrative, encompassing characters separated
by a thousand years, caught in the endless struggle for life amidst
death. Good friends of mine, no doubt, will leave theatres in droves,
gagging at the naïve rediscovery of the original Garden of Eden's tree
of life in the jungles of Guatemala, steeped in Aztec legends of
sacrifice and afterlife. Many will cringe at the grand and operatic
scope of the emotionally crushing, drug-inspired finale, as Hugh
Jackson, now a 25th century space-faring guru, full-lotuses headlong
into a nova for the ultimate lesson in personal mortality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But for every person who just can't stand a movie like this, there will
be others who are bold and foolish enough to fall head over heels for
its brand of unrepentantly teary-eyed intensity. For those bright-eyed
space cadets, who have immense reservoirs of willing suspension for a
story that is at once both enormous and intensely personal, who strive
to enlarge their conciousness, or to be unafraid of the darkness in our
hearts, and most especially for those who are or who ever have been in
love, I can unreservedly say that it's the most amazing film of the
year. And if you love it too, then then maybe one day we will find, that
"together, we can live &lt;em&gt;forever&lt;/em&gt;."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, maybe. But at the very least, it would make for a smashing film.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rating: 9/10&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>aronofsky</category><category>fiction</category><category>media</category><category>movie</category><category>science-fiction</category><category>the-fountain</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/the-fountain/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 13 Mar 2007 16:09:11 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>