<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>tartley.com (Posts about audiobook)</title><link>https://tartley.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://www.tartley.com/categories/audiobook.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2021 &lt;a href="mailto:tartley @ the domain tartley dot com"&gt;Jonathan Hartley&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 19 Oct 2021 11:37:31 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>The Hacker Crackdown : Law and Disorder on the Electronic Frontier</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/the-hacker-crackdown-law-and-disorder-on-the-electronic-frontier/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="The Hacker Crackdown" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2008/01/hacker-crackdown.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Bruce Sterling, &lt;a href="http://www.archive.org/search.php?query=hacker%20crackdown%20AND%20mediatype%3Aaudio%20AND%20collection%3Aopensource_audio"&gt;read aloud by Cory Doctorow&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Only the second audiobook I've bothered to listen to, and it seems to
work very well, especially when commuting, since you can continue
listening without interruption while leaving the tube and walking. (It's
taken me 36 years to figure this out? Genius.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cory does a fine job of reading, and I'm grateful to him for bringing
this important book to my attention. When he describes reading it on
it's publication in 1994 as 'life changing', I can understand why. It
describes the clash of cultures resulting from American law
enforcement's attempts to crack down on the hackers, crackers and
phreaks of the nascent cyberpunk underworld of the early '90s. Many of
the underlying issues have even more relevance today. Can taking a copy
of digital information be equated with stealing, given that the original
owner still retains their original copy? Or is it more analogous to
attempting to overhear a conversation which the speakers would rather
wasn't overheard? While some hackers have real criminal intent, there
are a significant proportion with a very strong ethic to do no harm, who
view their tinkering as merely the exploration of an online frontier,
filled with challenges and puzzles, and rewards of rich hordes of
information - the dispersal of which is not just a god-given right, but
actually a moral responsibility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When law enforcement agencies went after this crowd with a heavy-handed
and indiscriminate approach, teenagers still living with their parents
ended up in court facing years in prison, colossal fines and legal fees,
in some instances simply for simply republishing a document that was
already in widespread circulation. Innocents had tens of thousands of
dollars worth of computers seized and never returned, even though no
charges were ever filed against them. The resulting backlash formed the
beginnings of the Electronic Frontier Foundation, a philanthropic
organization devoted to defending the rights of individuals in the
online realm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This whole tale is laced with many entertaining insights into the quirks
and motives of the colorful individuals involved, and this makes the
whole thing an enjoyable romp through a serious topic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rating: 8/10 - I only wish I'd read it ten years ago&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: both"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>audiobook</category><category>book</category><category>culture</category><category>internet</category><category>law</category><category>media</category><category>non-fiction</category><category>software</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/the-hacker-crackdown-law-and-disorder-on-the-electronic-frontier/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 02 Feb 2008 22:15:49 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>