<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>tartley.com (Posts about audiobook)</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://www.tartley.com/categories/audiobook.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2022 &lt;a href="mailto:tartley @ the domain tartley dot com"&gt;Jonathan Hartley&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 19 Sep 2022 18:30:25 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Neuromancer</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/neuromancer/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Neuromancer cover" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2022/neuromancer-cover.webp"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by William Gibson, 1984&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The sky above the port was the color of television, tuned to a dead channel.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So opens William Gibson's debut novel, and it is to his eternal credit that we
all still remember the line now, nearly forty years later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The bartender’s smile widened. His ugliness was the stuff of legend. In an
age of affordable beauty, there was something heraldic about his lack of it.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike the majority of the beloved science fiction of my youth, Gibson's
poetic, literary style has only increased in my estimation over the subsequent
decades.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Cyberspace. A consensual hallucination experienced daily by billions of
legitimate operators, in every nation, by children being taught mathematical
concepts. A graphic representation of data abstracted from the banks of
every computer in the human system. Unthinkable complexity. Lines of light
ranged in the nonspace of the mind, clusters and constellations of data. Like
city lights, receding.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The poetic allusions to the consensual hallucination of cyberspace seem prosaic
now, but one has to remember this was written back when the internet connected
less than 1,000 hosts, accessed via text terminals on university campuses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;He'd made the classic mistake, the one he'd sworn he'd never make. He stole
from his employers. [...] They damaged his nervous system with a wartime
Russian mycotoxin. Strapped to a bed in a Memphis hotel, his talent burning
out micron by micron, he hallucinated for thirty hours. The damage was
minute, subtle, and utterly effective. For Case, who lived for the bodiless
exultation of cyberspace, it was the Fall. In the bars he'd frequented as a
cowboy hotshot, the elite stance involved a certain relaxed contempt for the
flesh. The body was meat. Case fell into the prison of his own flesh.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He introduced the world to cyberpunk, combining the fatalistic noire of Blade
Runner with the relentless dehumanizing advances of a libertarian tech
dystopia, to create a startlingly original warning of our possible future that
looks, as the decades tumble by, increasingly on-the-nose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Night City wasn’t there for its inhabitants, but as a deliberately
unsupervised playground for technology itself. Like a deranged experiment in
social Darwinism, designed by a bored researcher who kept one thumb
permanently on the fast-forward button. Biz here was a constant subliminal
hum, and death the accepted punishment for laziness, carelessness, lack of
grace, failure to heed the demands of an intricate protocol.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don't really do audiobooks, prefering the word on the page, but
I made an exception for this. There are several versions of Neuromancer as an
audiobook. The slightly abridged six-hour version &lt;a href="https://archive.org/details/NeuromancerReadByWilliamGibson"&gt;available for free at the
Internet Archive&lt;/a&gt;
is notable for two things: it is read by William Gibson himself, and it is an
extremely low quality rip from an audiocassette.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A year here and he still dreamed of cyberspace, hope fading nightly. All the
speed he took, all the turns he'd taken and the corners he cut in Night City,
and he'd still see the matrix in his dreams, bright lattices of logic
unfolding across that colourless void... The Sprawl was a long, strange way
home now over the Pacific, and he was no console man, no cyberspace cowboy.
Just another hustler, trying to make it through. But the dreams came on in
the Japanese night like livewire voodoo, and he'd cry for it, cry in his
sleep, and wake alone in the dark, curled in his capsule in some coffin
hotel, hands clawed into the bedslab, temper foam bunched between his
fingers, trying to reach the console that wasn't there.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The audio quality might make anyone immediately pass this version by. It isn't
just noisy, but features discernible wow and flutter - artifacts characteristic
of the stretching or uneven speed of its original tape based media.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;He closed his eyes. Found the ridged face of the power stud. And in the
bloodlit dark behind his eyes, silver phosphenes boiled in from the edge of
space, hypnagogic images jerking past like a film compiled of random frames.
Symbols, figures, faces, a blurred, fragmented mandala of visual information.
Please, he prayed, now- A gray disk, the color of Chiba sky. Now- Disk
beginning to rotate, faster, becoming a sphere of paler gray. Expanding- And
flowed, flowered for him, fluid neon origami trick, the unfolding of
distanceless home, his country, transparent 3D chessboard extending to
infinity. Inner eye opening to the stepped scarlet pyramid of the Eastern
Seaboard Fission Authority burning beyond the green cubes of Mitsubishi Bank
of America, and high and very far away he saw the spiral arms of the military
systems, forever beyond his reach. And somewhere he was laughing, in a
white-painted loft, distant fingers caressing the deck, tears of release
streaking his face.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I'd urge you to stick with it. To give it a chance. For the author's reedy,
Virginia-inflected voice has a cadence that holds the attention. A rhythm of
tone and emphasis that, for me, works considerably better than the practiced
glossiness of more recent, more professional recordings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;"Dixie?"&lt;br&gt;
"Yeah."&lt;br&gt;
"You ever try to crack an AI?"&lt;br&gt;
"Sure. I flatlined. First time. I was larkin', jacked up real high, out by Rio heavy commerce sector. Big biz, multinationals, Government of Brazil lit up like a Christmas tree. Just larkin' around, you know? And then I started picking up on this one cube, maybe three levels higher up. Jacked up there and made a pass."&lt;br&gt;
"What did it look like, the visual?"&lt;br&gt;
"White cube."&lt;br&gt;
"How'd you know it was an AI?"&lt;br&gt;
"How'd I know? Jesus. It was the densest ice I'd ever seen. So what else was it? The military down there don't have any thing like that. Anyway, I jacked out and told my computer to look it up."&lt;br&gt;
"Yeah?"&lt;br&gt;
"It was on the Turing Registry. AI. Frog company owned its Rio mainframe."&lt;br&gt;
Case chewed his lower lip and gazed out across the plateaus of the Eastern Seaboard Fission Authority, into the infinite neuroelectronic void of the matrix. "Tessier-Ashpool, Dixie?"&lt;br&gt;
"Tessier, yeah."&lt;br&gt;
"And you went back?"&lt;br&gt;
"Sure. I was crazy. Figured I'd try to cut it. Hit the first strata and that's all she wrote. My joeboy smelled the skin frying and pulled the trodes off me. Mean shit, that ice."&lt;br&gt;
" "And your EEG was flat."&lt;br&gt;
"Well, that's the stuff of legend, ain't it?'&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By the end of the second chapter, I'd stopped being bothered by the audio
quality, and by chapter three, it had become an intrinsic part of the
experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The moment, I mean the nanosecond, that one of those things starts figuring
out ways to make itself smarter, Turing’ll wipe it. Nobody trusts those
fuckers, you know that. Every AI ever built has an electromagnetic shotgun
wired to its forehead.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A distortion so thoroughly appropriate to the underlying material
it was as though Gibson had planned it this way all along, speaking directly to
me via a weak signal, projected through time through the noisy filters of this
obsolete electro-mechanical recording mechanism. The words at once clear and
irrevocably decayed, fuzzy sounding but still stark and unmistakable in their
meaning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;And the Flatline aligned the nose of Kuang's sting with the center of the
dark below. And dove. Case's sensory input warped with their velocity. His
mouth filled with an aching taste of blue. His eyes were eggs of unstable
crystal, vibrating with a frequency whose name was rain and the sounds of
trains, suddenly sprouting a humming forest of hair-fine spines. The spines
split, bisected, split again, exponential growth under the dome of the
Tessier-Ashpool ice.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Five out of five stars. A riveting performance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: left"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>audiobook</category><category>book</category><category>cyberpunk</category><category>media</category><category>novel</category><category>science-fiction</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/neuromancer/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Sep 2022 16:22:12 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Hacker Crackdown : Law and Disorder on the Electronic Frontier</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/the-hacker-crackdown-law-and-disorder-on-the-electronic-frontier/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="The Hacker Crackdown" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2008/01/hacker-crackdown.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Bruce Sterling, &lt;a href="http://www.archive.org/search.php?query=hacker%20crackdown%20AND%20mediatype%3Aaudio%20AND%20collection%3Aopensource_audio"&gt;read aloud by Cory Doctorow&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Only the second audiobook I've bothered to listen to, and it seems to
work very well, especially when commuting, since you can continue
listening without interruption while leaving the tube and walking. (It's
taken me 36 years to figure this out? Genius.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cory does a fine job of reading, and I'm grateful to him for bringing
this important book to my attention. When he describes reading it on
it's publication in 1994 as 'life changing', I can understand why. It
describes the clash of cultures resulting from American law
enforcement's attempts to crack down on the hackers, crackers and
phreaks of the nascent cyberpunk underworld of the early '90s. Many of
the underlying issues have even more relevance today. Can taking a copy
of digital information be equated with stealing, given that the original
owner still retains their original copy? Or is it more analogous to
attempting to overhear a conversation which the speakers would rather
wasn't overheard? While some hackers have real criminal intent, there
are a significant proportion with a very strong ethic to do no harm, who
view their tinkering as merely the exploration of an online frontier,
filled with challenges and puzzles, and rewards of rich hordes of
information - the dispersal of which is not just a god-given right, but
actually a moral responsibility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When law enforcement agencies went after this crowd with a heavy-handed
and indiscriminate approach, teenagers still living with their parents
ended up in court facing years in prison, colossal fines and legal fees,
in some instances simply for simply republishing a document that was
already in widespread circulation. Innocents had tens of thousands of
dollars worth of computers seized and never returned, even though no
charges were ever filed against them. The resulting backlash formed the
beginnings of the Electronic Frontier Foundation, a philanthropic
organization devoted to defending the rights of individuals in the
online realm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This whole tale is laced with many entertaining insights into the quirks
and motives of the colorful individuals involved, and this makes the
whole thing an enjoyable romp through a serious topic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rating: 8/10 - I only wish I'd read it ten years ago&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: both"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>audiobook</category><category>book</category><category>culture</category><category>doctorow</category><category>internet</category><category>law</category><category>media</category><category>non-fiction</category><category>software</category><category>stirling</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/the-hacker-crackdown-law-and-disorder-on-the-electronic-frontier/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 02 Feb 2008 22:15:49 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>