<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>tartley.com (Posts about biography)</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://www.tartley.com/categories/biography.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2021 &lt;a href="mailto:tartley @ the domain tartley dot com"&gt;Jonathan Hartley&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 04 Jun 2021 17:10:47 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Benjamin Franklin's Autobiography</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/benjamin-franklins-autobiography/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="iphone.jpg" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2007/12/iphone.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I read through this to assess the iPhone (many thanks to the
generosity and resourcefulness of a certain &lt;a href="http://amoral.org/"&gt;Mr
Smithson&lt;/a&gt;) as an eBook reader, and found it
surprisingly good - certainly the best device I've tried to date,
surpassing even the silky-screened PSP. The text is clear and relaxing
(better looking than the hurried mock-up I Gimped together on the left),
page turning or scrolling through chapters are both unobtrusive and
highly functional. The whole experience was very pleasing - I could read
comfortably off the iPhone for hours on end. I'm reminded of the post I
wrote back in '98: "I'm going to try out this new thing called
Napster..." The revolutions begins here - let the book-burning commence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As for the words themselves, they were a very entertaining read. Mr
Franklin is evidently a singularly able individual who led an
interesting life full of achievement. I'd never before taken stock of
just how very industrious he must have been to straddle so many spheres
of influence, a fact which he misses no opportunity to remind us of. His
every week is seemingly filled with some new scheme for relentless
self-improvement, impressing local dignitaries with his perspicacity and
diligence, or else compiling lists of virtues, so that he might
regularly apprise his behaviour in their light. I noted with wry
amusement the suggestion by a friend of his to add 'humility' to his
list, of which Franklin reports "I cannot boast of much success in
acquiring the reality of this virtue, but I had a good deal with regard
to the appearance of it." Quite.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, it is mean spirited of me to begrudge him that trifle in light
of his achievements, and in particular, the spirit of honesty and
justice with which he undertakes every aspect of his life. I'm a firm
believer that the winners write history, and have on more than one
occasion pondered the lofty ideals of the founding fathers as a superb
marketing spin to popularise an act of treason. However, whether it was
spin or not, the lofty ideals stuck, bequeathing us the better part of
the disposition of modern America, for which the Western world owes him
an unending debt of gratitude.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rating: 8/10. Hoorah Mr Franklin!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>biography</category><category>book</category><category>geek</category><category>media</category><category>non-fiction</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/benjamin-franklins-autobiography/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 19 Dec 2007 15:23:29 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>