<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>tartley.com (Posts about book)</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://www.tartley.com/categories/book.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2021 &lt;a href="mailto:tartley @ the domain tartley dot com"&gt;Jonathan Hartley&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 06 Oct 2021 15:41:59 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>The Glass Bead Game</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/the-glass-bead-game-by-hermann-hesse-1943/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="The Glass Bead Game cover" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2021/glass-bead-game-cover.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Hermann Hesse (1943). Translated from German to English with evident
devotion and expertise by Clara Winston &amp;amp; Richard Winston.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This novel is described by some as the culmination of Hesse's career, for
which he received a Nobel Prize for Literature. Many reviews on Goodreads
cite it as a life-changing novel, or as a singular all-time favorite book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I must confess with some sadness that I must have entirely missed the point. I
have not enjoyed it &lt;em&gt;at all&lt;/em&gt;. The number of books I failed to finish in my
life is surely less than five, and this very nearly became one of them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first half describes Knecht's education and career within the rarefied
academic atmosphere of some distant future European state's "pedagogical
province", wherein (exclusively male) scholars devote their time to
mastery of the titular game. This relies upon drawing deep relationships
between all fields of human study, such as music and biology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Knecht is talented and likeable, and rises effortlessly through the ranks,
without exhibiting any real volition of his own, other than being naturally
predisposed to study, and having an instinct for drawing out the best in
people. He is ultimately assigned to the highest office in the land, without
encountering any substantive antagonist or difficulty along the way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The mechanics of the game itself, about which all this ostensibly revolves, is
deliberately never explained, other than poetic references to glass beads
being used to exquisitely interrelate insights or concepts from multiple fields
of study.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This first half of the book bored me to absolute tears. If I had to find a
single word to describe Knecht, despite his diligence, it would be "inactive".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the halfway point through the book, this serenity is interrupted by
Knecht making the controversial decision to quit, not just from his exalted
post, but from the whole system over which it rules. He leaves the insular
academic province entirely, to begin a new life, subject to more real-world
constraints. Just at this very moment, as the narrative becomes interesting,
this section abruptly ends in a very unexpected manner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Out of the whole book, this moment resonates with me. Knecht has spent a life
devoted to scholarly thought, but after many decades he throws off the
expectations of that life to forge his own path. Mere days after that decision,
a moment of physical exertion proves to be his sudden undoing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Does this show that Knecht should have more highly valued the protections from
the physical world that his intellectual castle provided? That someone raised
in such a cosseted environment was unsuitable to face the rigors of the real
world? Or should I instead observe that, despite his ostensible success and
satisfaction with life, in waiting so long before daring to strike out on his
own, and then find days later that his time was up, Knecht has in some ways
wasted his life doing something other than what he really wanted to do?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Neither of these seem particularly compelling to me, nor sufficient for
the larger themes that I suspect the book might actually be grappling with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second half of the book contains various poems, written by Knecht when he
was younger, containing premonitions of his aspirations and his doubts. It ends
with three short tales, each describing an alternate life that Knecht might
have lived in other times. Apparently early drafts had these tales being
literal other lives Knecht was reincarnated into. But in the published book,
they are presented without context, and I think it is only by consensus
that they are commonly understood to be grouped with the earlier poems as
examples of Knecht's writing - his imagination of other lives he might have
lived.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I did not understand the relevance of these tales to the larger portion of
the book, other than the way they forcefully contrast with it, by immersing
Knecht in emotional and painful tales of life embedded within a wider society,
rather than abstractly observing its achievements from without. As such,
they force him into action, and to me they are more engaging for it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wikipedia informs me that each of the four tales of Knecht's life focuses on a
different basic aspect of analytical psychology: thinking (Magister Ludi),
sensation (The Rainmaker), intuition (Indian life) and feeling (The Father
Confessor). Similarly, several of the book's characters who had influence on
Knecht are thinly-veiled references to real world people, some famous such
as Friedrich Nietzsche, others being acquaintances of the author.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of which seems reasonable, but doesn't really help me understand what I
just read. Perhaps each tale of Knecht, in focussing on one human trait,
is lacking because it undervalues the other three. Perhaps. ¯\&lt;em&gt;(ツ)&lt;/em&gt;/¯&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>media</category><category>novel</category><category>science-fiction</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/the-glass-bead-game-by-hermann-hesse-1943/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 20 Aug 2021 18:37:25 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Self-Calm</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/self-calm/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Self Calm cover" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2021/self-calm-cover.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Chris DeLeon (2018)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Roman Emperor Marcus Auralias' notes, traditionally titled &lt;em&gt;Meditations&lt;/em&gt;,
are a foundational text for practical Stoicism. They comprise a multitude of
observations and recommendations, grouped into sections such as "Keeping
thoughts tranquil", and "Cooperation, collaberation and contribution". They
offer advice for living a contented life, with less regret, sorrow, anger and
fear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several translations exist, themselves dated from through the ages. This book
combines them, to synthesize a text which doesn't hew as precisely to the
original as a straight translation might, but is instead intended to have the
most relevance to modern ears.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Confession: It's taken me &lt;em&gt;months&lt;/em&gt; to get through it. Partly this is because
I've allowed myself to be distracted by more gaudy and immediate books along
the way. Partly it's because I found the best way to read this was &lt;em&gt;slowly&lt;/em&gt;.
Practically every paragraph is worth reflecting upon, to consider how it
applies to my own life, and ponder what practical, specific next steps are
implied.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I had to criticize, it would only be the superficial wrinkle that there's
a lot of repetition, such as hundreds of suggestions to not fear death.
Apparently the original documents were accumulated over decades of Auralias'
life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Genuinely life changing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can get the epub for free from
&lt;a href="https://gumroad.com/l/self-calm"&gt;the author's gumroad page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: left"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>history</category><category>media</category><category>non-fiction</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/self-calm/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 03 Jun 2021 12:38:57 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Fine Structure, by qntm</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/fine-structure-by-qntm/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Fine Structure cover" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2021/fine-structure-cover.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another fabulously enjoyable science fiction adventure from qntm. Like their
other novels, it does a tremendous job of exploring the implications and
consequences of big science fiction concepts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this case, it's a story of human superheroes, whose powers derive from
beings-beyond-comprehension, from the high-dimensional multiverse, the
Structure, within which our paltry three-plus-one spacetime is naught but an
embedded decal. Their struggles rewrite the fundamental physics of our
universe, to fashion it into an inescapable trap, denying humanity access to
advanced sciences, and to communion with the higher levels of the Structure.
Loved it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those like me with an epub fetish, you can buy &lt;em&gt;Fine Structure&lt;/em&gt; in many
formats, including Amazon links, EPUBs, or free-to-read online, &lt;a href="https://qntm.org/structure"&gt;at the
author's site&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: left"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>media</category><category>novel</category><category>science-fiction</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/fine-structure-by-qntm/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 24 May 2021 16:55:26 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Ed, by qntm</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/ed-by-qntm/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Ed cover" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2021/ed-by-qntm-cover.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It took me a few pages to shift gears to match the provocatively casual style,
but once I did, it quickly became an engrossing and endearing read.
The book collects a series of tiny but grand adventures, each riffing on one
of the titular Ed's fabulous new inventions or discoveries. Together these
form an arc which burns through combinations of high-concept SF ideas at an
unseemly rate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It reminded me of what I've fondly said about 200AD (the galaxy's greatest
comic), that somehow the superficiality of the medium allows
writers to experiment more wildly with form and content, throwing up a torrent
of creativity which, while sometimes uneven, generates moments of sheer
brilliance. I thought being a comic was an essential part of that formula. But
&lt;em&gt;Ed&lt;/em&gt; proves me wrong by achieving the same velocity of verve and vigor,
rendered in prose. A delight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Epilogue reminds me gleefully of
&lt;a href="https://worldbuilding.stackexchange.com/a/151964/13496"&gt;this stackoverflow worldbuilding answer&lt;/a&gt;
I gave a few months ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those like me with an epub fetish, you can buy &lt;em&gt;Ed&lt;/em&gt; in many formats,
including Amazon links, EPUBs, or free-to-read online,
&lt;a href="https://qntm.org/ed"&gt;at the author's site&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: left"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>epub</category><category>fiction</category><category>free-to-read</category><category>media</category><category>novella</category><category>science-fiction</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/ed-by-qntm/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 17 May 2021 15:48:53 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Ra, by qntm</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/ra-by-qntm/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Ra cover" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2021/ra-by-qntm-cover.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I bought all four of &lt;a href="https://qntm.org/fiction"&gt;qntm's books&lt;/a&gt;
when I discovered the fantastic
&lt;a href="https://www.tartley.com/posts/there-is-no-antimemetics-division/"&gt;There is no Antimemetics Division&lt;/a&gt;.
I didn't really expect to like all of them, sight unseen, but was delighted to
support an emerging author who had contributed to the genius of SCP. But then
the books that arrived turned out to be bloody brilliant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This one tells a tale in which magic was discovered to be real in the 1970s,
becoming a new, arcane branch of physics. From there, it piles on the twists
and raises the stakes at an enthralling and dizzying rate, demanding the
reader to keep up through many exciting layered reveals and escalating changes
of perspective. Absolutely smashing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like &lt;em&gt;Antimemetics&lt;/em&gt;, it scores points with me for including some female heroes,
who surmount challenges through some striking strengths of character &amp;amp;
expertise, rather than simply being the best at applied violence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those like me with an epub fetish, you can buy &lt;em&gt;Ra&lt;/em&gt; in many formats,
including Amazon links, EPUBs, or free-to-read online,
&lt;a href="https://qntm.org/ra"&gt;at the author's site&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: left"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>epub</category><category>fiction</category><category>free-to-read</category><category>media</category><category>novel</category><category>science-fiction</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/ra-by-qntm/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 15 May 2021 17:22:32 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>11/22/63, by Steven King</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/112263-by-steven-king/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Ra cover" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2021/112263-cover.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prompted by a conversation at work about favorite time travel stories,
I snagged this from the library.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;English school teacher Jake is roped into a dying man's plot to exploit a
mechanism of travelling back to 1958, from which, with many complications, he
waits out the intervening few years in order to prevent JFK's assassination.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I found it a page turner, certainly. But nonetheless I was slightly
disappointed, perhaps because of my reverence for such a successful author, who
I haven't actually read since my teens. Expectations of mastery clashed with
what, for me, felt like lowest-common-denominator style.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;King knows exactly what he intends - to use time travel as a hook on which to
hang a human tale of drama, aspiration and loss. He has no interest in my
personal predilections, such as messing with the logical conundrums of his
chosen time-travel mechanic, and he declares this straightforwardly. When the
main character asks "But what if I end up killing my own Grandfather?", his
mentor shoots him a look of incomprehension, replying "Why in hell would you
want to do a thing like that?" Subject closed, and fair enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: left"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>media</category><category>novel</category><category>science-fiction</category><category>time-travel</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/112263-by-steven-king/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 11 May 2021 18:23:19 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>There is no Antimemetics Division, by qntm</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/there-is-no-antimemetics-division/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left; padding-bottom: 1em"&gt;
&lt;img alt="There is No Antimemetics Division cover" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2021/there-is-no-antimemetics-division-cover.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I first became aware of this book when I noticed that the good folks over
at &lt;a href="http://www.scpwiki.com/"&gt;The SCP Foundation&lt;/a&gt; have kept themselves busy in
the years since I last looked over their peerless and endlessly enthralling
wiki of dry and tantalizing protocols with which to "Secure, Contain, and
Protect" a catalog of creepy anomalous artifacts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the arcs to break the churning surface of that crowdsourced
fictional millieu is that of the
&lt;a href="http://scp-wiki.wikidot.com/antimemetics-division-hub"&gt;Antimemetics Division&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;"An antimeme is an idea which, by its intrinsic nature, discourages people
from spreading it. Think of ideas that you wouldn't share - passwords,
taboos, shameful secrets.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Anomalous antimemes are another matter entirely. How do you contain
something you can't record, or remember? How do you fight an enemy when you
can never even know you're at war?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Welcome to the Antimemetics Division.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;No, this is not your first day."&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Intruiged, I started clicking around, and as is the way of SCP, discovered
many hours had passed. Shortly afterwards, I realized the arc has been
collected into this book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Occasional SCP entries, in the format we know and love, intertwine a short but
intense tale of memetic hazards, populated by a few of the Division's
finest - those rare individuals who can go from the standing start of a hint
that their memories can't be trusted, to a well-executed plan based upon
a stack of assumptions about what might be needed, and what might already have
been done that they can count upon, even though they no longer remember any of
it, without ever retaining any knowledge of their situation, or what they're up
against. I don't think I've ever been so impressed by the sheer depth of a
character's resourcefulness and initiative.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The journey does contain world-ending hellscapes, with some gore, which might
not be everyone's cup of tea. But it's short and somehow manages to stay light
in tone, so isn't emotionally arduous on that front.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Probably my favorite fiction of the year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those like me with an epub fetish,
you can buy &lt;em&gt;There is No Antimememtics Division&lt;/em&gt; in many formats,
including Amazon links, EPUBs, or free-to-read online,
&lt;a href="https://qntm.org/scp"&gt;at the author's site&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: left"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>epub</category><category>fiction</category><category>free-to-read</category><category>media</category><category>novel</category><category>science-fiction</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/there-is-no-antimemetics-division/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 10 May 2021 18:50:52 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Intelligence: A Very Short Introduction</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/intelligence-a-very-short-introduction/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Intelligence cover" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2021/intelligence-cover.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Ian J. Deary (1st Ed, 2001)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An expert's overview for the layman, describing how and why people differ in
their thinking powers, Very data driven, and by necessity, largely driven by
consideration of how to measure different aspects of intelligence, and
therefore what aspects intelligence can be teased apart into, such as working
memory, linguistic comprehension, perceptual organization, and speed of
operation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each chapter tackles a key scientific question, describing the experiments
that were done to determine the answers, showing the actual
key experimental datasets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Such questions include: Is intelligence determined by genes or the environment?
The answer is 50/50, although surprisingly, little of the environmental
influence is due to the family raising the child. Also, the effect of genetics
increases with age.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How does a person's intelligence change as they age? Some skills show a
straight decline from age 25 to 80, such as inductive reasoning, spatial
awareness, perceptual speed and verbal memory. Other skills show a peak in
middle-age, with only a small decline at high ages, such as verbal reasoning
and numerical ability. The amount of mental decline with age is highly variable
between different people. Those whose abilities decline the least have no
cardio issues or chronic disease, have high social class, live in complex and
stimulating environments, and are generally satisfied with life, and unstressed
through middle age.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Does intelligence, especially as measured using existing tests, correlate with
life outoutcomes such doing well at a job? Depending on the job, yes, a great
deal. What sort of tests are good for predicting who will do well? Work
samples, structured interviews, and psychometric tests all give slightly over
0.5 correlations. Which isn't stellar, but it's the best we've got. At the
other end of the scale, graphology (handwriting) and age rankings had no
correlation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's a short book, with a lively style, densely packed with important
conclusions, and descriptions of how the field has arrived at them. Edifying.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: left"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>cognition</category><category>media</category><category>non-fiction</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/intelligence-a-very-short-introduction/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 18 Jan 2021 11:58:23 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Structure of Scientific Revolutions</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/the-structure-of-scientific-revolutions/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;This post rescues content from a series of tweets I wrote in 2018.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="The Structure of Scientific Revolutions cover" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2020/the-structure-of-scientific-revolutions-cover.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Thomas S. Kuhn, 1962.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I loved &lt;em&gt;The Structure of Scientfic Revolutions&lt;/em&gt;.
It was recommended to me as having similar impact to undergraduate
classics like &lt;em&gt;Godel, Escher, Bach&lt;/em&gt;, or &lt;em&gt;The Blind Watchmaker.&lt;/em&gt; I'm going
to just summarize the content here, so: Spoilers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It begins by observing that discredited scientific theories, even those
which seem laughable today, such as phrenology, or the Ptolemaic model of the
heavens, were not crackpot theories with shaky evidence. Earnest, hardworking
practitioners refined them using sensible processes, which by the 17th century
were converging on the modern scientific method.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This process of "normal" science excels at the incremental refinement of
established scientific theories. But in practice, is unable to perform the
revolutionary transitions required to overcome outmoded theories and replace
them with others, no matter how bizarre and wrongheaded the initial theory
looks to us now with hindsight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what is the unarticulated process that is responsible for these
transitions, i.e. how do scientific revolutions happen? We have intuitive
visions of this occurring overnight. An individual experiment yields unexpected
results, contradicting conventional theory, while irrefutably supporting an
alternate theory to take its place. But in practice, this &lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; happens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At first, and often for years or centuries, no discrepancy between theory and
experiment is noticed, because the prevailing theories of the time have a
massive shaping effect on what questions it is valid to ask, what experiments
are deemed useful to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For practitioners to turn their backs on an established theory in such a time
is never productive. They are shunned for turning their backs on science
itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We see this vividly today with homeopaths (my own example, not the book's).
Often, and incorrectly, homeopathy is mocked because the theories sound
ridiculous to one steeped in a conventional understanding of chemistry.
People will jeer at how total dilution can 'obviously' have no effect,
or at the idea of water exhibiting some sort of 'memory'. But such jeering is
as scientifically illiterate as the quacks it contends with. The argument from
personal incredulity has no place in determining scientific truth. No newer
theory makes sense in the light of the more limited, and often contradictory,
paradigm that it eventually replaces. The only useful criteria is to try it
out. &lt;em&gt;Does it actually work?&lt;/em&gt; This is the axis upon which homeopathy should be
judged. (and upon which it has decisively been found wanting.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All contradictions to conventional science suffer a similar ignominious
treatment, regardless of how right they might later turn out to be. Before any
revolution of theory can overturn conventional understanding, the stage
must be set, the community prepared.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The process begins as the incremental advances of "normal" science gradually
increase the scope and precision of accepted theories. Until this point,
measurements in which experiment does not conform to theory are either ignored
as erroneous artifacts, or are dismissed as indicative of some separate,
unknown phenomena. They are never interpreted to mean prevailing theory is
wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However the growing scope &amp;amp; precision of theory and measurement gradually
uncovers more of these discrepancies, or reveals them in finer detail.
Eventually they become too prominent to ignore, and a kind of phase transition
occurs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eventually, the discrepancies become so prominent and concerning that they
are judged to be a valid area of study in themselves, rather than just annoying
aberrations. Leading practitioners devote themselves to the task. Foundations
of the specialisation that were once accepted without question now come under
scrutiny.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To partially explain the discrepancies, people introduce many incompatible
variations on current theories. The once unified field divides into cliques,
supporting different theoretical variations. The field, formerly a united mass,
calves into fragments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If one of these variations on existing theory manages to explain all
observations, then this gradually gains mindshare, until the whole community
has migrated to this new, incrementally improved theory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, in cases where a truly revolutionary change is required, such
incrementalism is insufficient, and none of the theoretical variations are
fully successful in explaining all observations. The factions' differing
underlying assumptions give them no common ground upon which to arbitrate their
differences, so their debates are irreconcilable. The fragments are melting,
into a churning liquid of disagreement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This state is notably similar to the state of a nascent field before any
established scientific theories have taken hold.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All is chaos, with different groups supporting different ideas, agreeing on
nothing. The field is in turmoil, its practitioners in genuine emotional
distress. Their personal identities are undermined. What does it mean to be a
practitioner when nobody can agree on what the field even is? Is what we do
even &lt;em&gt;science&lt;/em&gt; at all? A crisis has arrived. We are at boiling point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kuhn compares this to individuals in psychological experiments, given cunningly
contradictory sensual stimuli. At first they don't notice anything wrong about
a brief glimpse of a playing card showing a red king of clubs. As the length of
their glimpse expands, and the stimulation becomes more intrusive, the subject
starts to hesitate, and stumble on words. Suddenly it impinges on their
consciousness, and they cry out, distressed, uncertain of even basic facts. "My
God! What did I see? Are clubs always red? What's happening here?"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kuhn also compares scientific revolutions to their social and political
counterparts, in a chillingly familiar passage:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Political revolutions aim to change political institutions in ways that
those institutions themselves prohibit. Their success therefore necessitates
the partial relinquishment of one set of institutions in favor of another, and
in the interim society is not fully governed by institutions at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Initially it is crisis alone that attenuates the role of political
institutions [...] In increasing numbers, individuals become increasingly
estranged from political life, and behave more &amp;amp; more eccentrically within
it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, as the crisis deepens, many individuals commit themselves to [...] some
new institutional framework. At that point, society is divided into competing
camps or parties, one seeking to defend the old institutional constellation,
others seeking to institute some new one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once that polarization has occurred, &lt;em&gt;political recourse fails&lt;/em&gt;. Because
they differ about the political matrix within which political change is to be
achieved and evaluated, and acknowledge no common supra-institutional framework
for adjudication of differences, the parties to a revolutionary conflict must
finally resort to the techniques of mass persuasion, often including force."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At any point, the &lt;em&gt;boldest&lt;/em&gt; practitioners, often those with least invested in
the previous status quo, such as the relatively young, or those entering from
adjacent fields, will introduce strikingly different sets of theories. But only
now that the stage is set, amongst such distressing chaos, is the community
ready to entertain truly revolutionary ideas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Occasionally, one of these new ideas will succeed in explaining all the
observations, but in order to do so, it requires incommensurable changes in the
underlying philosophy of the field, from the axiomatic definitions, to the set
of questions that are valid to ask. One can no longer ask, of a spherical
Earth, "What happens if you fall off?"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Notably, many revolutionary changes are not an unalloyed good. Gains in
explicative power in one area are often balanced by losses elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As in evolution, the new theory is not necessarily more &lt;em&gt;correct&lt;/em&gt;, so much as
it is a better fit for the current circumstances, i.e. providing greater
predictive power in an area that is currently pertinent. Maybe scientific
progress is more obviously useful to society in that area, or instruments are
more capable of making measurements in that area. The two often coincide,
since influences are are unable to detect or manipulate are also unlikely to
be of much direct use to society. So as the social and technological context
evolves, so does the relative fitness of potential competing paradigms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nobody understands this trade-off more deeply than the field's most
invested practitioners, who feel the losses of losing the old model most
keenly, and therefore may resist the new paradigm for the remainder of their
careers. The new paradigm will not achieve total dominance until the field is
populated by a whole new generation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am reminded of the dark priesthood of command-line programmers, although
I note with no little joy that our merry band includes some of the best and
brightest of the next generation (as judged by my own paradigm's criteria.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: left"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>media</category><category>non-fiction</category><category>politics</category><category>science</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/the-structure-of-scientific-revolutions/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 14 Jun 2020 14:02:22 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Swamp Thing, Vol 1: Saga of the Swamp Thing</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/swamp-thing/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Swamp Thing cover" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2019/06/swamp-thing-vol-1.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Alan Moore, Jogn Totleben, &amp;amp; Steve Bissette&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moore's deconstruction of existing characters continues. Originally Swamp Thing
was Alec Holland, miraculously transformed by an infusion of artificially
stimulated plant matter. When Alan Moore takes over the writing, Swamp Thing's
ostracization and existential dread is compounded by the discovery that this
origins story has been a delusion all along. Alec Holland was killed outright
in the accident, and an accumulation of plant matter grew around his decaying
form, integrating the physical remains of his memories into a creature that
yearned to recapture its human form, but was never human in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: both"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>comic</category><category>fiction</category><category>media</category><category>science-fiction</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/swamp-thing/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 24 Jun 2019 02:50:43 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>