<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>tartley.com (Posts about IMHO)</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://www.tartley.com/categories/cat_imho.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2020 &lt;a href="mailto:tartley@tartley.com"&gt;Jonathan Hartley&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a rel="license" href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/"&gt;&lt;img alt="Creative Commons License" style="border-width:0" src="https://i.creativecommons.org/l/by-nc-sa/4.0/88x31.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" property="dct:title"&gt;tartley.com&lt;/span&gt; by &lt;a xmlns:cc="http://creativecommons.org/ns#" href="https://www.tartley.com" property="cc:attributionName" rel="cc:attributionURL"&gt;Jonathan Hartley&lt;/a&gt; is licensed under a &lt;a rel="license" href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/"&gt;Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International License&lt;/a&gt;.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 11 Jun 2020 19:39:42 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>I am such a child</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/2010/7/10/i-am-such-a-child.html</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dear Julio,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many thanks for considering me for this opportunity. I feel as though my
skills are a good match for the position, and would like you to consider
my application.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I feel as though this is the start of a new phase in life for me, as
though I have really rounded a corner. I have not used a computer, but
my nephew says he will meet me tomorrow afternoon to teach me how to do
it. Also, my therapist says that my bouts of incoherent rage will
continue to diminish, so that will be good in my new job. My probation
for stealing from my previous employer is almost up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am high, but I can absolutely have this under control and be
completely sober by Monday, when I trust you will call me at your
earliest convenience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Best regards,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jonathan Hartley&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;-------- Original Message --------&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Subject:   offer number 078
  Date:      Fri, 9 Jul 2010 17:28:46 -0500
  From:      &lt;a href="mailto:tartley@tartley.com"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  To:        &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My name is Julio YEPES, I am a hiring manager with ...&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>IMHO</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/2010/7/10/i-am-such-a-child.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 10 Jul 2010 18:36:20 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Great Resolver IDE Anecdote</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/2010/5/4/the-great-resolver-ide-anecdote.html</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Found myself telling this story yet again, so I figured I should just
post it here and start linking to it, rather than remembering, retyping
and re-embellishing it every time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ever since we started at &lt;a href="http://www.resolversystems.com/"&gt;Resolver&lt;/a&gt;,
developers have been free to choose their own IDE (Integrated
Development Environment, although some of the ones I'm going to talk
about aren't so integrated, so I guess you should just read 'IDE' herein
to mean 'development environment').&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like herding cats, this of course resulted in everyone choosing a
different IDE. At one peak, we had fourteen people, and about ten
different IDEs. Sigh. To our incredulity though, this worked fine, and
everyone was happy. So far, so good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We pair program, so we see a lot of each other's IDEs. In fact, we end
up learning them all pretty thoroughly. Spending eight hours a day,
every day, using someone else's IDE, with a bona-fide expert in that IDE
sitting in your lap, guiding you through it, will tend to do that. After
a few months, we all knew every IDE out there back-to-front. An example
of how pairing spreads knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every so often, someone would change their mind about their chosen IDE.
Having been educated about the alternatives, they would decide to
switch. This was also fine, and everyone continued to be happy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, after a few months of this, an interesting thing happened.
Gradually, one by one, twelve of our fourteen people each decided, of
their own accord, to switch to using either Vi or Emacs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I regard this of an example of pairing not just spreading knowledge, but
spreading &lt;em&gt;enlightenment&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They each had realised that although these hallowed text editors didn't
have some of the more advanced features they'd come to expect from an
IDE, such as auto-completion or 'go to definition', they were flexible
and powerful enough that one could add such features yourself. To do so
is a rite of passage for an experienced programmer, akin to Luke
building his own lightsaber - so that it's customized to his precise
needs, and he understands each nuance of its behaviour.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More than that, all the conveniences of a traditional IDE made it very
convenient to do only what the authors of the IDE had envisaged. To do
anything else was made very difficult. If you wished to use a different
compiler, or write in a different language than those prescribed by your
IDE vendor, you were out of luck, and would have to learn an entirely
different IDE to do that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;"We shape our tools and afterwards our tools shape us."&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Marshall McLuhan ('The media is the message' guy)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On one project, or two, this might seem a trivial restriction. Extended
over the course of a lifetime, the conveniences shields a developer from
learning anything other than how to drive an IDE, and the restrictions
become blinkers, crippling their scope and abilities. The IDE is a
cage... for your &lt;em&gt;mind&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2010/05/matrix_morpheus_red_blue_pill.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The outliers are worth noting: We still use Visual Studio on rare
occasions, for the lovely built-in GUI designer. The irrepressible
Michael Foord loves Wing, and stuck with that. Will Reade, our tame
brainiac, stuck with transparent simplicity of the lightweight but
surprisingly useful TextPad. Go figure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update&lt;/strong&gt;: The coda to the outliers is also interesting. Nowadays we're
embedded in a huge mission to free our codebase from embedded win32
controls, so that we might have a chance of running under Mono, and
hence on other platforms. It would be nice if we could escape Windows
Forms altogether - I understand WPF would let us display our GUI on the
web. Writing this post makes me wonder - if we hadn't been using Visual
Studio's convenient GUI designer all along, is it remotely possible that
we might have considered our choice of GUI layer more thoroughly? If we
hadn't been entranced by the "obviously right" convenience of the Visual
Studio GUI designer, might our minds have been free enough to have made
this decision right the first time around?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>IMHO</category><category>Software</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/2010/5/4/the-great-resolver-ide-anecdote.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 04 May 2010 17:56:47 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>A Layman's Philosophical Musings</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/2009/10/10/a-laymans-philosophical-musings.html</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;A quick response to to polymath Chris DeLeon's thoughtful post
&lt;a href="http://cdgdl.com/lessons/philosophy.html"&gt;exhorting the virtues of
Philosophy&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A position of ignorance&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Right off the bat I should qualify all this by saying that I don't know
anything about Philosophy. I've never studied it. It seems at times to
be an alien mismatch to the sensibilities of my left-brained mind, and
worse, one that claims to be about logic and reasoning, topics that
ostensibly should be right up my alley. I read Bertrand Russel's
&lt;em&gt;History of Western Philosophy&lt;/em&gt; last year, and although that was a
fabulous, educational romp through the field, &lt;a href="https://www.tartley.com/history-of-western-philisophu"&gt;my complaints about
it&lt;/a&gt; still stand. Now I'm reading a second
book, &lt;em&gt;Think : A Compelling Introduction to Philosophy&lt;/em&gt; by Simon
Blackburn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Process&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The process of &lt;em&gt;thinking about things&lt;/em&gt; is a valuable and worthwhile
endeavour. Some people enjoy it, some people don't. Amongst those who
enjoy it, it becomes an end unto itself, and thought and discussions
typically stray towards the more abstract, the more meta, the more
foundational. Anyone who has gleefully participated in a pub discussion
about religion, death, reality, consciousness, government, or any of a
million other topics has participated in this process. It is joyful,
sometimes enlightening, entertaining, and refines the individual's
ability to meaningfully reason on all kinds of topics, from the abstract
to the prosaic. In this sense, and especially from the perspective of
the individual's active participation in the activity, I'm all in favour
of philosophy. Presumably this is why I have been drawn back to read
this second book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Content&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If anything, I have had more objections to &lt;em&gt;Think&lt;/em&gt; than I had to
Russel's book. At first, I thought that my issue was simply that the
discussed historical philosophers produced curiously shoddy work. Their
premises seem shaky. Their arguments full of holes at best. Their
conclusions entirely suspect. While there are some genuinely insightful
ideas and arguments, they are often mutually contradictory, and the
signal to noise is terrible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chris points out the importance of reading a decent translation of the
original sources to gain enough insight to benefit from the arguments,
and in this I defer to his experience. There certainly are some
historical philosophers who seem to make a lot more sense to me than the
others. I had not expected to have to pick and choose based so much upon
my own personal preferences, so in some way my frustration here is
perhaps indicative of an expectation mismatch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As for &lt;em&gt;Think&lt;/em&gt;, as I continue to read, it has slowly dawned on me that
perhaps this impression is actually because the author himself is an
appalling philosopher (sorry Simon!) Every few pages he makes what seems
to me like a terrible logical blunder. If this were correct, that would
presumably make his interpretation of historical philosophers equally
suspect, and perhaps this is why they so often seem simply ludicrous to
me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I realise it is arrogant and bonkers for me to assume I can outclass the
author, a man apparently of considerable knowledge and experience, at
his own game. But this is how it seems to me, so what am I to make of
that?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It seems to me that there are only three possibilities:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Professor Blackburn's thinking is entirely defective. I am sure this
    cannot be the case. He is a professor of his subject, his book,
    while quite understandably not comparable to Russel, has garnered
    great reviews on Amazon and in the press, for whatever that's worth.
    As a layman I shall accord him the deference that is entirely his
    due.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;My own thinking is entirely defective. This is, of course, entirely
    possible, however distasteful it may be to me. How would I know? In
    defence of my sanity, I note that I seem to get by, more or less, in
    everyday life. Or at least, I don't seem to be any more confounded
    by the state of the world than the people around me.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Perhaps, then, the problem lies not solely with myself, but is
    shared by us all. Perhaps human reasoning as expressed in the
    English language is generally not sufficiently precise, well-defined
    or powerful to support consistent philosophical arguments of the
    type that are being put forward. More generally, we aren't remotely
    as good at thinking as we think we are. Pretty much I'm saying
    that (1) and (2) are both true, but that both the professor and I
    can derive some comfort from the idea that the same applies to
    pretty much everybody else.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Method&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is, of course, a method for dealing with the unreliability of our
thoughts and perceptions - the scientific method, in its many forms and
manifestations. I have friends who claim that the scientific method came
out of philosophy, and while I have some reservations about the truth of
this in the day-to-day reality of individual practitioners, of course in
an abstract sense I can see that this lineage is real.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Application of the scientific method would be the normal way out of the
morass of imprecise thoughts that, to date, characterise the majority of
philosophy for me. Some aspects of ancient philosophy have proven
tractable in this regard. These are the subjects that have subsequently
calved off from philosophy to form whole new fields and sciences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, this has the curious effect of diluting the perceived value
of philosophy. As soon as the application of the scientific method lets
thinkers actually gain any traction and start to make real progress on
their topic, we immediately snip that subject off from the realm of
philosophy and give it a different name. Astronomy and cosmology,
biology and psychology, chemistry, physics, and many more. Philosophy
proper, then, consists of the left over bits - the topics upon which the
scientific method has not proven applicable, and hence upon which no
meaningful progress can be made.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chris, and discussion with friends, has helped me see that in this
dismissal, I was overlooking the value of philosophy as an incubator for
other fields. This is of course critical to the development of human
civilisation, and of interest to historians of the respective fields.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What it isn't&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I'm left with is the impression that my minor experiences of
philosophy would have been much improved if my expectations had been
very different at the outset.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My layman's impression of philosophy from the outside was that it
claimed to be the study of tremendously insightful reasoning done by
some of the most powerful minds in history. This expectation was
naturally bound to lead me to be disappointed when my initial foray led
me to discover that many philosophers, particularly ancient ones,
distorted as they are by translation and interpretation, cultural
mismatch, and lack of my modern knowledge of the world, appear to my
sensibilities to be pretty poor. I hope to improve on this situation by
taking on board Chris' advice about choosing particular philosophers who
resonate for me personally, together with the idea of studying
particular translations of original works, rather than quick summaries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition, I had an expectation that all this intense thought might
lead to some more definitive and objective conclusions. However ancient
philosophers acted without the benefit of the scientific method, and
modern philosophy is pruned of topics to which the scientific method is
applicable. As a result, there is much bad mixed in with the good. Even
the good parts cannot be trusted as a guide to any sorts of truth, since
choosing 'the good parts' seems to be a subjective process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This seems inevitable, since without the benefit of the scientific
method, there is no utility function to be used as feedback, by which
ideas could be judged and one school of thought meaningfully compared
against another. There can be no definitive winners or losers, and
without competition, ideas cannot improve by evolution. Instead, each
contributor adds their own voice to the mutually contradictory babble,
and it is left to the reader to sift through for the parts of value.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The lack of an objective means to prune the discussion of its less
worthy branches mean that many philosophers are deified, their writings
sacrosanct and studied for generations, even in cases where they were
clearly absolutely wrong. (Plato's thoughts about the shapes of atoms,
for example.) I accept that study of historical and ancient philosophers
is valid for the perspective it gives on the &lt;em&gt;process&lt;/em&gt; of philosophy,
and as a study of the &lt;em&gt;history&lt;/em&gt; of philosophy itself. However, I am
appalled that so much of their actual, specific writings are studied and
discussed in so much detail, in the same way I would be mortified by the
prospect of scholars spending centuries reviewing the specifics of what
me and my friends said in our philosophical discussions in the pub.
There may be some value in there, but I came to this expecting a précis
of the best minds in the world, not a mishmash of sometimes incoherent
ideas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Upshot&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've done a lot of bitching, but don't take it as a wholesale rejection.
In addition to the things I complain about, there are also a bunch of
really great, stimulating ideas. I just didn't expect to have to do so
much searching and interpretation to find them. Rather, interpret the
above as the painful transitions in my understanding of what philosophy
&lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt;, which parts of it are likely to be of value to me, and what I
should expect from it. Thanks to Chris for his significant contributions
towards my continuing education on this.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>IMHO</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/2009/10/10/a-laymans-philosophical-musings.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 10 Oct 2009 20:09:20 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Copyright and the crowdsourcing of promotional materials</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/2009/8/29/copyright-and-the-crowdsourcing-of-promotional-materials.html</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;There was &lt;a href="http://blog.facebook.com/blog.php?post=110636457130"&gt;a
rumour&lt;/a&gt; that
Facebook was allowing third-party advertisers to use user's photos in
promotional materials. I imagine a photo of me and my friends enjoying
Bacardi responsibly being scraped for use in an advert.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It turns out that rumour is false. But it's not totally groundless -
it's based on the fact that some third-party Facebook applications were
behaving in this way. Facebook put a stop to it, and are to be commended
for that. In the general case, though, it's entirely believable that
this sort of thing may still happen, on Facebook or elsewhere, and it's
fascinating for me to think about why I personally have an objection to
it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I mean, if some company does use your photo in their promotions, then of
course some people would feel this is a privacy issue simply because
they are shy about having their personal photos widely disseminated
outside their immediate social circle - pasted up on billboards or
whatever - and they have a negative emotional reaction to that, and
that's understandable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many people, however, would instead have a &lt;em&gt;positive&lt;/em&gt; emotional
reaction. If my photo of me and friends enjoying Bacardi was chosen to
be used in an ad, it would actually be kinda cool and funny. However, I
*still* would object to them doing it. Even though I'm not losing
anything on this deal, and in fact I'm gaining an amount of amusement
and notoriety, I still don't want Bacardi to reap the benefit. Why is
that?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For me, it's this: Bacardi, who incidentally, have done nothing wrong -
they are my hypothetical example. In fact, let's just call them BigCorp
instead. BigCorp expect to be able to use my photo, without
reciprocating in kind. If I had tried to use BigCorp's images or music
or logo, for my own purposes, and it had come to their attention, then
they would have sued me into the ground.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It may be that they had little choice in the matter. That they were
merely acting in a way that they perceived the prevailing legal and
commercial environment obliged them to do. Regardless, the upshot from
my perspective is that they would have sued me into the ground.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that isn't cool. There is a groundswell of resentment in me for the
way our cultural heritage - all the music and t.v. and movies and images
and adverts and logos that surround us, the things that have come to
form our whole cultural milieu, have been prised from our fingers, by
gradually increasing legal boundaries, such that none of us as
individuals, owns it any more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Copyright used to be of limited scope. It was designed to prevent the
wholesale appropriation of creative works such as books, which were
being copied and republished and sold by third parties unconnected with
the author. This is a fairly obnoxious behaviour, and one I'm prepared
to condemn, and I accept that introducing copyright to prevent it seems
like a good idea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, since the 1970's the scope of what copyright is applicable to
has expanded and expanded, way beyond its original remit. Instead of
being triggered by the commercial activity of a large book
(re)publishing entity, it is now triggered and invoked by the tiniest of
non-commercial personal behaviours, not just publishing books, but
giving a song to a friend, or drawing a comic for your blog in your
bedroom that incorporates the distinctive likeness of a character you
like.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Things that used to be common and socially acceptable (eg. giving an
album you like to a friend) are now clearly illegal and can get you sued
for your life savings plus draconian life-changing conditions. We can no
longer give the songs we like to our friends. We can't post parts of our
culture on YouTube. We can't put it on our blogs, or use it in any way
we feel like. We have been unwillingly converted into pure consumers of
culture, instead of participants. We have been robbed of something we
used to have.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I strongly agree with Banksy, who feels that if any corporate image or
logo or advert is shoved into my face in a public space (e.g.
billboards, but also tv or on the web), then it is, from that moment on,
mine to do with as I wish. If I wish to appropriate the image, or
augment it with daubings of my own, then why should anyone have the
right to stop me? (*huge separate discussion reqd here to justify this,
obviously. Maybe later.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But this, obviously, has been utterly repudiated by the copyright
industry, acting in concert with BigCorp lobbyists, has used legal
strong-arm tactics to deny me the ability to so much as sing happy
birthday in my own restaurant without paying royalties, never mind
ripping off BigCorp advertising materials to form my own pastiche. I
resent that. I've been putting up with it for years, and in return
BigCorp has earned my ill-will on this topic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So in answer to the question "Can Facebook's partners use your photos
for promotional purposes? It'll be funny and cool!" I have to reply "No
you can't. I agree that it would be kinda funny and cool, but on this
topic you have seriously annoyed me. We are not friends. You cannot use
my photos. Now piss off."&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>IMHO</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/2009/8/29/copyright-and-the-crowdsourcing-of-promotional-materials.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 29 Aug 2009 18:08:59 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Letter to my Member of European Parliament : Proposed Copyright Extension</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/2009/3/19/letter-to-my-member-of-european-parliament-proposed-copyright-extension.html</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thursday 19 March 2009&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dear Baroness Ludford, (&lt;strong&gt;Update&lt;/strong&gt;: This was sent to all eleven of my
MEPs)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am writing with reference to the European Parliament's vote on
copyright extension for sound recordings, due to take place on March
23rd.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you know, this is a complex issue, but I shall try my best to keep
this short, I know you must be busy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Amongst the justification for this particular extension to the term of
copyrights, is the idea that artists need more protection, particularly
towards the end of their lives when their income from royalties might
dry up as their copyrights expire.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is misleading in the extreme. Under the current 50 year term, an
artist recording at age 25 will be protected until age 75, and any
artist who records throughout their lifetime will be protected until
many decades beyond their death.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is no need whatsoever to extend the term in order to benefit or
incentivise artists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, as everyone knows, artists in practice almost never end up
owning the copyrights to their own works - the labels do. While artists
and labels are aligned in the desire to sell as many records as
possible, they are in direct opposition when it comes to dividing up the
proceeds. The majority of the income from sales goes to the labels,
because they have such an overwhelmingly dominant position of power in
the relationship. No label is reliant upon any individual artist, while
every artist is very much dependant on their label, to whom they are
tied by contract for many years. Strengthening copyright only
strengthens the position of the copyright owner, ie. the labels, at the
expense of what little leverage the artist may have. Extending the term
of copyright only enhances the labels' income, not the artists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is not the role of copyright to be a protectionist measure to support
labels who are having to adjust their business models in these times of
great change. The last thing we need to do is to construct laws which
chain Europe's creative industries to last-century modes of operation,
at precisely a time when the current tumult will reveal as yet undreamed
of exciting new ways of doing business.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you know, copyright is intended to stimulate the creation of new
creative works, by enabling the artist to earn an income from their own
creations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There exists significant evidence to suggest that stronger copyright may
actually inhibit the production of creative work, by allowing
monopoly-level profits to be reaped from ever smaller amounts of
creative output. The composer Verdi is notable for suddenly decreasing
his creative output when copyright laws over music were introduced in
18th century Italy - his personal correspondence indicates that he
simply had to work less because he was earning more from his earlier
compositions. (note that he retained copyright over his own work.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Similarly, there is the very vital and oft-overlooked influence of the
creative environment which our society fosters. It could well be that
freedom to borrow and build upon inspiration from other artists is a
vital input to the engines of creativity, and to encourage fledgling
artists. By way of anecdotal evidence I say it would not be very
controversial to suggest that the last great English composer of the
Baroque period was Handel, who coincidentally died around the same year
copyright over music was introduced in England. After that, there is a
dearth of truly top-class composers from England, right up until the
20th century. Meanwhile Germany, too preocupied with invasions and
reforging of the nation to introduce copyright laws over music, went on
to produced greats like Bach, Mozart and Beethoven, in a succession of
creative gear-shifts which formed the romance and classical eras, all
done with no copyright over music. *1&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I apologise if I have been unable to express my points very succinctly,
but I hope I have made given you some reasons to consider rejecting this
extension of the copyright term, or at least to consider assessing it in
the light of evidence over its theorised effects, rather than the
deliberately misleading suppositions put forward by those representing
the special interests who stand to directly benefit from the proposal at
the expense of artists and of the rest of society.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With all my gratitude and respect for the work you and your fellow MEPs
have done and will continue to do to resolve these issues,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yours sincerely,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jonathan Hartley&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;*1 See this February 2009 Harvard paper which notes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"An attempt to determine the impact of legal changes on entry into
composing is inconclusive. The paper shows, however, that a golden age
of musical composition nevertheless occurred in nations that
lackedcopyright protection for musical works."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=1336802"&gt;http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=1336802&lt;/a&gt;
The paper is summarised persuasively in an online news article here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.techdirt.com/articles/20090308/1022324034.shtml"&gt;http://www.techdirt.com/articles/20090308/1022324034.shtml&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>IMHO</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/2009/3/19/letter-to-my-member-of-european-parliament-proposed-copyright-extension.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 19 Mar 2009 19:32:20 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Evolved for suboptimal decision making?</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/2008/5/13/evolved-for-suboptimal-decision-making.html</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2008/05/prisoners-dilemma.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I *should* be searching out and evaluating Python geometry libraries.
But I keep getting these niggling impulses to start hammering out my own
vector, polygon and quaternion classes. Possibly in C. Ohdear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why is it so much easier, or at least so much more appealing, to start
beavering away on your own code, rather than to take the sensible
approach of evaluating existing libraries? A couple of hours searching
could save you days, weeks or months of work, and libraries written and
used by several people will undoubtedly be of higher quality as well -
it should be a no-brainer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's easy enough to conjure up subjective justifications for it on a
personal level, but to my mind they rarely hold up to scrutiny. Reading
and understanding other people's code is said to be harder than churning
out some according to your own vision, but surely the depth of
understanding required to use a module should surely be substantially
less than it would take to write it? Likewise, curiosity, obsessiveness,
a sense of personal achievement play a part, but these motives are
deeply subjective, and cannot be used to argue the case that 'rolling
your own' is an efficient or rational decision, merely an enjoyable (or
compulsive) one. Expectations of quality also contribute - everyone
thinks that their own code is better. But this is rarely really the
case, and experienced practitioners recognise it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a deeper level, then, why does some part of us allow these inadequate
justifications to hold sway? Even if rationally, we know it doesn't make
sense, why does it feel so &lt;em&gt;desirable&lt;/em&gt;? What I'm really asking is, why
have we been evolved to want to build our own, even though it is so
clearly the wrong thing to do?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What if we are tuned, as individuals, to prematurely settle on our own
idiosyncratic approach? The net result would be that, for any given
problem, a flurry of individuals would each set out in different
directions, regardless of what results others might have already
achieved. Viewed as a group activity, this starts to sound a little
saner. Such a dispersion of individuals would rapidly and thoroughly
explore all the corners of the problem space. Compared to the situation
where we all just build cumulatively on what everyone else has done
before, the chances of any one individual finding an optimal answer is
low, but the chances of someone in the group finding it is greatly
increased.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's a survival-of-the-group trait, that each of us is evolved to pick a
wrong-looking answer, and then expend ourselves beavering away to prove
it. Oh dear indeed.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>IMHO</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/2008/5/13/evolved-for-suboptimal-decision-making.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2008 18:12:22 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Only Joking!</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/2008/5/9/only-joking.html</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;I haven't really stopped reading everyone else's posts. Cold turkey?
God, you're a bunch of douchebags.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>IMHO</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/2008/5/9/only-joking.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 09 May 2008 15:14:22 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Simpsons Movie / Goodbye Forever</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/2008/5/8/the-simpsons-movie-goodbye-forever.html</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="The Simpsons Movie" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2008/05/simpsonsmovie.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is, of course,
no point whatsoever in me posting a belated review of the Simpsons
Movie, which I and everyone else gleefully watched many months ago now.
To the now long abandoned discussions of its merit I have absolutely
nothing of value to contribute.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, that shall not dissuade me from posting this one anyway, since
such posts as these are not, as you might assume, for the benefit of my
readership, few and benighted as they might be, but instead form an
attempt to chart my media consumption habits for my own retrospective
perusal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was with some dismay, therefore, that I noted that this inverted
system of priorities is mirrored in the Herculean task of my reading of
other people's posts. Simply put, I seem to be reading other people's
blogs in order to make them feel good, upping their stats, making
complimentary comments, showing an interest, etc, etc, rather than for
my own benefit. Once this cold fact had impinged upon my conciousness, I
had only one course of action left open: Cold Turkey. That's right. No
more Google Reader.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abandoning the hampster wheel should free up a considerable amount of my
time for other activities, and I am keen to quantify that process, so I
will be keeping detailed logs of my time usage for a few days prior and
post the switchover, to ascertain exactly how many hours I previously
spent looking at labelled pictures of cats, which I will henceforth
presumably be free to spend looking at &lt;em&gt;actual&lt;/em&gt; labels on cats (or
possibly labels on &lt;em&gt;actual&lt;/em&gt; pictures of cats, let's not get overly
ambitious.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a final layer of delicious irony, I shall of course be blogging
comprehensively about the entire experience, however your collective
reactions to that will remain forever unknown to me. Henceforth you
should consider me to be a purely one-way conduit of information.
Goodbye forever.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>IMHO</category><category>Movies</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/2008/5/8/the-simpsons-movie-goodbye-forever.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 08 May 2008 17:48:12 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Long Overdue LinkedIn Backlash</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/2008/3/18/the-long-overdue-linkedin-backlash.html</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="UnRecommend" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2008/03/linkedin.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We've all known this for a long time, but I don't remember anyone
actually saying it out loud: Have you ever noticed how it's always the
most industrious LinkedIn users who are the very last people you'd
actually recommend in a genuine network of trust?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most ruthless networkers, climbing every last tenuous connection
like an insidious vine. Grasping for unearned advantage at every node.
Can you introduce me to so-and-so? If you link to me, I'll have over 500
connections, think how popular that will make me look. My preciousss
connectivity. Somehow, this kind of behaviour also correlates well with
other repugnant activities, like spamming. Some people just have no
conception of how their actions change the world around them for better
or worse, and hence act as though they had no responsibilities to the
community around them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One final spam this morning broke the camel's back. I've asked him not
to do it before, both personally, and via the captcha screen he
disingenuously filled in to get onto my whitelist. So it's time for
LinkedIn to start pulling its weight. I notice there is no mechanism to
add a &lt;em&gt;negative&lt;/em&gt; recommendation via LinkedIn, so I've been forced to add
him as a connection and then leave a suitable-worded positive one.
Hopefully it still conveys my intended semantic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It may be that publicly dissing a recruiter is not the wisest of career
moves, and maybe James will get retaliatory. I weighed that up for a
while, and decided I can risk that. I don't operate on appearance. I
operate on substance. I can take it. Some things are right, and some
things are wrong, and It's time to take a stand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, even this is a half-hearted measure - I think James needs
to approve it for it to be attached to his profile, and that seems
unlikely from my perspective. Who knows, though? Maybe he's actually a
stickler for accurate representation who relishes feedback.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So this got me thinking. Forget LinkedIn - it's clearly designed to
appeal to vacuous self-congratulators. What attributes would we want
from a *real* network of trust? Clearly some mechanism for leaving
public negative feedback would be one of them. Can that be done in a way
that can't be abused? What else does it need?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>IMHO</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/2008/3/18/the-long-overdue-linkedin-backlash.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 18 Mar 2008 21:09:57 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Actual vs Perceived threats (aka People are Crazy)</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/2008/2/23/actual-vs-perceived-threats-aka-people-are-crazy.html</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.susannahertrich.com/html/humansanimals.html"&gt;&lt;img alt="Actual vs Perceived threats" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2008/02/0aelecrtromshjoi9.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.susannahertrich.com/html/humansanimals.html"&gt;Susanna
Hertrich&lt;/a&gt; has an
art / thesis project to artificially stimulate people's threat
perceptions (by giving them goosebumps, or making hairs stand on end) in
response to &lt;em&gt;actual&lt;/em&gt; threats, as opposed to perceived ones. It's a topic
that I'm unnaturally preoccupied with, since the most egregious examples
of the disparity between the two seem to intrude on my life every day.
My opinions about whether any given threat is real or illusiory seem to
differ from almost everyone, but I'm going to stubbornly cling to the
idea that everyone else is crazy. Take the entry on 'terrorist attack'
as an example (see diagram.) Public reactions to the topic remind me of
nothing so much as a stirred-up ants nest, a psychotic, ineffectual
frenzy.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>IMHO</category><category>Refried</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/2008/2/23/actual-vs-perceived-threats-aka-people-are-crazy.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 23 Feb 2008 21:51:54 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>