<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>tartley.com (Posts about Graphics)</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://www.tartley.com/categories/cat_graphics.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2020 &lt;a href="mailto:tartley@domain tartley dot com"&gt;Jonathan Hartley&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 11 Jun 2020 21:33:53 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Use light-opacity RGBA to fix halo artifacts along edges of textures</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/2010/1/3/use-light-opacity-rgba-to-fix-halo-artifacts-along-edges-of-textures.html</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is a quick post in response to the Vimeo video post &lt;a href="http://vimeo.com/8444889"&gt;Getting Rid of
White Halos in Transparent Textures&lt;/a&gt; by
FlashBang Studios (creators of the awesome &lt;a href="http://blurst.com/raptor-safari/"&gt;Offroad Velociraptor
Safari&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks to FlashBang for the video - the fix you describe, and the
plugins you use to achieve it, are good to know about. If I'm
interpreting the cause of the white haloes you describe correctly, then
your fix applies to more than just Unity development.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, you might want to know that there is an alternative solution to
this problem. This alternative solution requires small code changes, and
is possibly slightly trickier to get your head around, but possibly has
a small advantage in that it requires no ongoing effort by the artists
(e.g. applying and undoing plugin actions to color transparent pixels)
once in place. I don't use Unity, so this might not apply in that
environment, but just in case, here goes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The alternative solution is to save textures using &lt;em&gt;light-opacity RGBA&lt;/em&gt;
(a.k.a. &lt;em&gt;pre-multiplied alpha&lt;/em&gt;), and then blend them in the engine using
a more appropriate OpenGL blending mode. I learned about this from
&lt;a href="http://http://groups.google.com/group/pyglet-users/tree/browse_frm/thread/7647b57bdec45235/60d2c57881b873e1?rnum=11&amp;amp;q=premultiplied+alpha&amp;amp;_done=%2Fgroup%2Fpyglet-users%2Fbrowse_frm%2Fthread%2F7647b57bdec45235%3Ftvc%3D1%26q%3Dpremultiplied%2Balpha%26#doc_bb176dcbd759ea4c"&gt;Brian Fisher's post on the pylget
forums&lt;/a&gt;.
I aim to paraphrase his explanation of it here in order to cement my own
understanding of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To elaborate, as I understand it, the issue is caused by the bilinear
interpolation between the RGBA of your transparent pixels, and your icon
texture color. For example, for various transparencies of purple on top of 
a blue background:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;| &lt;span style="background-color: #0088ff; padding: 1em;"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2010/01/opaque-purple.png" title="opaque-purple"&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;strong&gt;icon&lt;/strong&gt; (1, 0, 1, 1) fully opaque purple
| &lt;span style="background-color: #0088ff; padding: 1em;"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2010/01/halfwhite-purple.png" title="halfwhite-purple"&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;strong&gt;interpolation&lt;/strong&gt; (1, 0.5, 1, 0.5) half-transparent whitish-purple
| &lt;span style="background-color: #0088ff; padding: 1em;"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2010/01/transparent-white.png" title="transparent-white"&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;strong&gt;background&lt;/strong&gt; (1, 1, 1, 0) fully transparent white&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(&lt;em&gt;Update: I think some CSS nuance has been lost in a website migration. On
quick glance, this doesn't seem to look like I expect it to, any more.&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The intermediate color isn't actually very close to white, but in
contrast to the pure purple it abuts against, it's significantly paler,
and causes the 'white looking halo' effect around the edge of the purple
icons, as shown in the video.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that changing the color of the transparent pixels, from white to
black for example, does not fix the problem - it just changes the color
of the haloes from white to black.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The video shows how to fix this, using a technique that I infer is very
common - change your transparent pixels to be the same color as whatever
colors they abut against. The background pixels are now
fully-transparent purple, giving us:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;| &lt;span style="background-color: #0088ff; padding: 1em;"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2010/01/opaque-purple.png" title="opaque-purple"&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;strong&gt;icon&lt;/strong&gt; (1, 0, 1, 1) fully opaque purple
| &lt;span style="background-color: #0088ff; padding: 1em;"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2010/01/halftransparent-purple.png" title="halftransparent-purple"&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;strong&gt;interpolation&lt;/strong&gt; (1, 0, 1, 0.5) half-transparent whitish-purple
| &lt;span style="background-color: #0088ff; padding: 1em;"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2010/01/transparent-white.png" title="transparent-purple"&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;strong&gt;background&lt;/strong&gt; (1, 0, 1, 0) fully transparent purple&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So now the interpolation ends up being half-transparent pure purple.
This eliminates the white halo artefact, as demonstrated in the video.
The only minor downside is that the artist has to make sure the
transparent pixels are saved with the correct RGB values, and the plugin
demonstrated in the video helps to automate this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The alternative solution, is to modify the RGBA values in the texture,
by pre-multiplying the RGB values by the A value. ie:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class="err"&gt;R = R * A&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="err"&gt;G = G * A&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="err"&gt;B = B * A&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(where all values range from 0.0 to 1.0)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This can either be done in the saved texture file (eg. 3d Studio Max
writes TGA files this way.) Or, if you'd rather continue to use standard
RGBA values in your saved texture files, then your application could do
this transformation when loading image files from disk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To use these alternate RGBA values in a texture, we have to display them
on screen using a different OpenGL blending mode. We switch from using
the traditional:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;dest&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;src&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;alpha&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;dest&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;alpha&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;to using this instead:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;dest&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;src&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;dest&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;alpha&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Note how the difference between the two is that the src is no longer
multiplied by the src alpha during blend. This is no longer required,
because we have already done this multiplication in the RGBA of the src
texture itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Storing RGBA values in this format is known as &lt;em&gt;light-opacity RGBA,&lt;/em&gt; and
it gives us a new interpretation of the meaning of the RGBA values.
Previously, the RGB told us the color of the texture's pixel, but did
not tell us how much this color would be used to affect the destination.
We have to look at the alpha to determine that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, using the new
blending mode, we can interpret the RGB values to literally mean how
much R and G and B is added to the destination. Similarly, the A value
is now only used to diminish whatever existing color is currently at the
destination. It is not used to scale the source RGB before applying it
to the destination. The A value can now be interpreted to mean 'what
proportion of the existing destination color is visible through the
overwritten source color'.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This implies that for pixels to be fully transparent, ie to have no
effect on the destination, they must have an RGB of 0. So we must always
use (0, 0, 0, 0) to represent fully transparent pixels. Note how with
the new interpretation of RGBA, these are not 'black' transparent
pixels, they are literally 'no-color' transparent pixels. This obviously
has a neat logical correposondance to what 'pure transparency' really
means.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The pixels around the edge of the purple icon still get the same
interpolation process, resulting in the same RGBA values as would have
been calculated before, but now we have a different interpretation of
what those values mean:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;| &lt;span style="background-color: #0088ff; padding: 1em;"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2010/01/opaque-purple.png" title="opaque-purple"&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;strong&gt;icon&lt;/strong&gt; (1, 0, 1, 1) - pure purple that fully overwrites the previous color
| &lt;span style="background-color: #0088ff; padding: 1em;"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2010/01/halftransparent-purple.png" title="halftransparent-purple"&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;strong&gt;interpolation&lt;/strong&gt; (0.5, 0, 0.5, 0.5) - half-bright purple mixed with 50% of the prev dest color
| &lt;span style="background-color: #0088ff; padding: 1em;"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2010/01/transparent-white.png" title="transparent-white"&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;strong&gt;background&lt;/strong&gt; (0, 0, 0, 0) - fully transparent (no color)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The interpolated color is now blended with the previous destination
color using the new OpenGL blend mode:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;dest&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;src&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;dest&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;alpha&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The existing destination color is scaled by (1 - alpha), ie, is reduced
to half intensity, and then the RGB from our interpolated texture (0.5,
0, 0.5) is added to it. This results in a half-transparent purple - even
though the transparent pixels in our texture had no purple at all in
them. This results in a perfect blend between the transparent and pure
purple colors. No haloes are visible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update&lt;/strong&gt;: It crosses my mind to mention that the halo artefacts will
be visible whenever textures are scaled, rotated, or positioned using
sub-pixel co-ordinates. If you only ever display unrotated textures, at
integer pixel co-ords, and at normal size, then you won't run into this
problem. Since the icons on the radar on FlashBang's video don't seem to
be scaled or rotated, maybe they could sidestep the problem by just
displaying the icons at integer pixel co-ordinates? I don't really know
anything about how their code works though, so I might be talking
nonsense here.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>Graphics</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/2010/1/3/use-light-opacity-rgba-to-fix-halo-artifacts-along-edges-of-textures.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 03 Jan 2010 21:33:10 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>