<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>tartley.com (Posts about civilisation)</title><link>https://tartley.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://tartley.com/categories/civilisation.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2023 &lt;a href="mailto:tartley @ the domain tartley dot com"&gt;Jonathan Hartley&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 03 Aug 2023 20:27:27 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Collapse: How Societies Choose to Fail or Survive</title><link>https://tartley.com/posts/collapse-how-societies-choose-to-fail-or-survive/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="collapse.jpg" src="https://tartley.com/files/2008/01/collapse.jpg" title="collapse.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Jared Diamond&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A brilliant tome from the same bloke who penned &lt;em&gt;Guns, Germs and Steel&lt;/em&gt;.
This time he examines the flip side of the equation - what
characteristics cause civilisations to fail? From the statues of Easter
Island to the Mayan Ruins, the world is replete with the abandoned
relics of cultures that collapsed. Diamond examines seven examples of
societies whose members all died or dispersed, sometimes over a period
of just a few years, leaving their hauntingly abandoned habitats,
looking for the common factors which lead to their demise. The
implications for our own culture are serious. Do we have more in common
with these failed civilisations, or with the ones that exhibited
long-term stability? Will our own skyscrapers one day stand as
hauntingly abandoned monuments amongst jungle or desert? It's a serious
message, and the immediate conclusion looks a little grim, as our rabid
consumerism and resource consumption is anything but steady-state.
However, Diamond finds a silver lining, presenting his conclusions as a
message of hope. We are the first civilisation to have a global reach,
and to have knowledge of ancient societies that have gone before, so
while the stakes are higher than ever, so is our ability to forsee the
consequences of our actions, and to change our course before it's too
late.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rating: 8/10 - a fascinating and important read.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: both"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>civilisation</category><category>media</category><category>non-fiction</category><category>sustainability</category><guid>https://tartley.com/posts/collapse-how-societies-choose-to-fail-or-survive/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 30 Jan 2008 17:22:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>