<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>tartley.com (Posts about cognition)</title><link>https://tartley.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://www.tartley.com/categories/cognition.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2021 &lt;a href="mailto:tartley @ the domain tartley dot com"&gt;Jonathan Hartley&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 19 Oct 2021 11:37:32 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Intelligence: A Very Short Introduction</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/intelligence-a-very-short-introduction/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Intelligence cover" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2021/intelligence-cover.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Ian J. Deary (1st Ed, 2001)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An expert's overview for the layman, describing how and why people differ in
their thinking powers, Very data driven, and by necessity, largely driven by
consideration of how to measure different aspects of intelligence, and
therefore what aspects intelligence can be teased apart into, such as working
memory, linguistic comprehension, perceptual organization, and speed of
operation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each chapter tackles a key scientific question, describing the experiments
that were done to determine the answers, showing the actual
key experimental datasets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Such questions include: Is intelligence determined by genes or the environment?
The answer is 50/50, although surprisingly, little of the environmental
influence is due to the family raising the child. Also, the effect of genetics
increases with age.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How does a person's intelligence change as they age? Some skills show a
straight decline from age 25 to 80, such as inductive reasoning, spatial
awareness, perceptual speed and verbal memory. Other skills show a peak in
middle-age, with only a small decline at high ages, such as verbal reasoning
and numerical ability. The amount of mental decline with age is highly variable
between different people. Those whose abilities decline the least have no
cardio issues or chronic disease, have high social class, live in complex and
stimulating environments, and are generally satisfied with life, and unstressed
through middle age.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Does intelligence, especially as measured using existing tests, correlate with
life outoutcomes such doing well at a job? Depending on the job, yes, a great
deal. What sort of tests are good for predicting who will do well? Work
samples, structured interviews, and psychometric tests all give slightly over
0.5 correlations. Which isn't stellar, but it's the best we've got. At the
other end of the scale, graphology (handwriting) and age rankings had no
correlation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's a short book, with a lively style, densely packed with important
conclusions, and descriptions of how the field has arrived at them. Edifying.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: left"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>cognition</category><category>media</category><category>non-fiction</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/intelligence-a-very-short-introduction/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 18 Jan 2021 11:58:23 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Blink: The Power of Thinking Without Thinking</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/blink/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Blink, cover" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2007/07/blink.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Malcome Gladwell (2005)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blink is by the same guy who wrote &lt;em&gt;Tipping Point&lt;/em&gt;, which I never read,
and was another foolish airport buy, induced by the sheer peer pressure
of it being popular. It features enough content to fill three or four
fairly interesting blog posts about the under-utilised ability of the
subconscious mind to come to rapid decisions which are sometimes
inordinately useful but rarely trusted in our left-brain dominated
society. This was then padded out to the length of an entirely
unnecessary paperback. 3/10.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: both"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>cognition</category><category>media</category><category>non-fiction</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/blink/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 22 Jul 2007 05:11:08 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>