<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Made out of meat (Posts about comedy)</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://www.tartley.com/categories/comedy.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2024 &lt;a href="mailto:tartley @ tartley dot com"&gt;Jonathan Hartley&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 04 Oct 2024 14:52:17 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Ferris Bueller's Day Off</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/ferris-buellers-day-off/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Ben Stein in Ferris Bueller's Day Off" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2023/ferris-bueller.webp"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Directed and written by John Hughes, 1986.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0091042"&gt;IMDB&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, way back in my teen years, we had a VHS tape of this, which friends and I
played and played and played, probably racking up more rewatches than any other
movie in my life. So it was a pleasure to break it out for our 11 year-old,
some some 37 years later (!), to see whether it still holds up, and find that
it really does.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By chance this was the week after we'd just watched &lt;em&gt;The Blues Brothers&lt;/em&gt;, so we
got to compare and contrast two movies set in Chicago - a privileged white
story, and a poverty stricken, largely colored one, which even share scenes
filmed in the very same restaurant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back then, I had no idea who Ben Stein was, so it was amusing to see him now
and suddenly join the dots. Apparently his infamous "voodoo economics" speech
had no script and was ad-libbed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reviewing Rooney's comical attempts to break into the Buellers' house made me
realize for the first time that this was Hughes' dry-run at what would become
&lt;em&gt;Home Alone&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had always been frustrated that I'd never been able to lay my hands on the
"&lt;em&gt;You're not dying&lt;/em&gt;" song that Cameron plays while sick in his bedroom (i.e. here's the few seconds
of it
&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6mcFGW0RjAo&amp;amp;t=70s&amp;amp;autoplay=1"&gt;on Youtube&lt;/a&gt;,
exactly as it appears in the movie.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now we have the Internet, I can see that this failure wasn't exactly my fault -
there is no such song. The few bars we hear were whipped up by Ira Newborn
specially for the film, based on an old Louis Armstrong song,
&lt;a href="https://youtu.be/fHbC8Nhd46s?autoplay=1"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Let My People Go&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Fortunately for us,
one man was obsessed about it enough to actually recreate a full length
song based on the snippets from the movie. Here is Daniel Simone's
&lt;a href="https://youtu.be/MDEXlOk_suM?autoplay=1"&gt;Let My Cameron Go&lt;/a&gt;,
full of a lush Pink Floyd sound, and ripe with the sort of ecstatic
anticipation that even Roger Waters would be proud of.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Duly &lt;a href="https://www.tartley.com/posts/download-audio-from-youtube/"&gt;added to my rotation&lt;/a&gt; for next time I'm sick.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: left"&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>comedy</category><category>fiction</category><category>media</category><category>movie</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/ferris-buellers-day-off/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 27 Sep 2023 15:01:22 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Daniel Kitson</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/daniel-kitson/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="regentsparkopenairtheatre.jpg" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2007/06/regentsparkopenairtheatre.jpg"&gt;
&lt;img alt="kitson.jpg" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2007/06/kitson.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Daniel's usual brand of heartfelt, bittersweet, dorky, whimsically
playful stand-up, in the delightful environs of Regent's Park Open Air
Theatre, with the Junior Penns &amp;amp; co, and Hallie visiting from Minnesota.
More cynical souls were untouched, but Hallie and I loved it.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>comedy</category><category>media</category><category>theater</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/daniel-kitson/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 11 Jun 2007 20:40:35 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Hot Fuzz</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/hot-fuzz/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Cleaning up the aisles" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2007/02/hotfuzz1.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Director: Edgar Wright.
Writer: Edgar Write, Simon Pegg.
Starring: Simon Pegg and his mates.
2007.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://uk.imdb.com/title/tt0425112/"&gt;&lt;img alt="Internet Movie Database" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2007/03/imdb.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Big Cops. Small Town. Moderate Violence.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A romping lampoon of American buddy cop homoeroticism and Agatha
Christie alike, which follows the plight of over-achieving hardass
metropolitan cop (Pegg) forcably relegated to the gentile surroundings
of an idyllic village. (I particularly liked the dreaded journey to the
countryside, as represented by a close-up of the signal bars on Pegg's
phone falling to zero, but that probably says more about my own urban
snobbery than anything else.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In keeping with its loveably teenage approach and unapologetically
English style, it provides a few golden moments which are absolutely
classic. However, one can't help but be distracted from time to time by
the fact that it has been crafted more with an endearing enthusiasm than
with incisive skill. The barrage of snap shots and hyperkinetic editing
tries just a little too hard, and by the third climax of the finale, the
whole thing has perhaps outstayed its welcome just a little.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you like Simon Pegg (&lt;em&gt;Sean of the Dead&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Spaced&lt;/em&gt;), then this is very
much more of the same. Otherwise forgettable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rating: 6/10&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>comedy</category><category>fiction</category><category>media</category><category>movie</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/hot-fuzz/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Feb 2007 17:00:51 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>