<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>tartley.com (Posts about comic)</title><link>https://tartley.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://www.tartley.com/categories/comic.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2022 &lt;a href="mailto:tartley @ the domain tartley dot com"&gt;Jonathan Hartley&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 06 Jan 2022 20:08:18 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>The Incal</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/the-incal/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="The Incal 4 cover" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2022/the-incal-4-cover.webp"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="clear: right; float: right"&gt;
&lt;img alt="The Incal The Fall " src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2022/the-incal-the-fall.webp"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="clear: right; float: right"&gt;
&lt;img alt="The Incal The Fall " src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2022/the-incal-divinity.webp"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="clear: right; float: right"&gt;
&lt;img alt="The Incal 4 cover excerpt" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2022/the-incal-4-cover-part.webp"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;written by Alejandro Jodorowsky, art by Jean Giraud (aka Mœbius), 1980-88&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This creative pairing also worked together on the unproduced 1970s movie of
Dune, the one that was to have featured Salvador Dali, and presumably would
have been pretty trippy - I mean, &lt;em&gt;even more&lt;/em&gt; trippy than the David Lynch
one turned out to be. Mœbius has had a long and glorious career, knighted
for his art in his native France, and he worked on other movies such as
Alien, Tron, The Fifth Element, and The Abyss.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I grabbed this in the English translation from the original French, having been
intrigued by the &lt;em&gt;Pocket Essential Alan Moore&lt;/em&gt;'s description of it as a
contender for "the best comic in the medium's history".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Echoes of all of these are visible throughout the consistently stunning
artwork of The Incal, and it has been explicitly noted as an influence
throughout the genre, from the expansive decayed futurescapes of Akira and
Blade Runner, to the flamboyant visuals of the Star Wars prequels, and
even the concept of that iconic technological terror, the "War Star", which can
atomize a solar system in seconds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The writing really swings for the fences, a sprawling tale of a reluctant
hero's journey, taking in societal commentary, intergalactic travel, spiritual
transformation, iconic representations of good and evil, and a deep thread of
mysticism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For me, it does have a very evident "foreign" feeling - small social nuances
with which I'm unfamiliar. Equally clearly, this is part of its exotic charm.
And while the story touches on, perhaps even consists of, deep themes, it
doesn't so much articulately explore them, but instead simply incorporates
them. This is not a comic for people who are not already comic fans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In lesser hands, it might have been undisciplined. But wherever the story
roams, the artwork is endlessly enthralling. I especially liked the touch of
protagonist, John DiFool, starting out distinctly ugly, but being rendered more
handsomely on the rare occasions he manages to get in touch with his more noble
aspects. Jodorowsky manages to keep it all together, bringing it around to a
splendidly satisfying theatrical close. &lt;em&gt;Bravo!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: both"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>comic</category><category>fiction</category><category>media</category><category>science-fiction</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/the-incal/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 05 Jan 2022 19:56:03 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Demon</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/demon/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Demon cover" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2021/demon-cover.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Jason Shiga (2016)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm just discovering the works of &lt;a href="http://www.shigabooks.com"&gt;Jason Shiga&lt;/a&gt;,
creator of mathematically-inspired nonlinear comic-books, e.g. stories drawn
on complex origami structures, that can be folded in various ways to represent
either branching story-lines, or else to manage state such as 'inventory'.
Construction of these more elaborate paper constructions doesn't scale,
(ie. I'm not likely to ever own one) but you can try some of his other
creations on the web.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is &lt;a href="http://www.shigabooks.com/index.php?page=001"&gt;Demon&lt;/a&gt;,
a regular linear web-comic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The storyline is 'math-inspired' too, in the same way that the movie &lt;em&gt;Primer&lt;/em&gt;
is - intense, absolute, ruthless, narrative exploration of logical
implications, while continually, dizzyingly, escalating to the next level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: left"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>comic</category><category>fiction</category><category>free-to-read</category><category>media</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/demon/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 31 May 2021 16:08:52 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Swamp Thing, Vol 1: Saga of the Swamp Thing</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/swamp-thing/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Swamp Thing cover" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2019/06/swamp-thing-vol-1.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Alan Moore, Jogn Totleben, &amp;amp; Steve Bissette&lt;/em&gt; &lt;img alt="spoilers" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/spoilers.svg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moore's deconstruction of existing characters continues. Originally Swamp Thing
was Alec Holland, miraculously transformed by an infusion of artificially
stimulated plant matter. When Alan Moore takes over the writing, Swamp Thing's
ostracization and existential dread is compounded by the discovery that this
origins story has been a delusion all along. Alec Holland was killed outright
in the accident, and an accumulation of plant matter grew around his decaying
form, integrating the physical remains of his memories into a creature that
yearned to recapture its human form, but was never human in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: both"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>comic</category><category>fiction</category><category>media</category><category>moore</category><category>science-fiction</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/swamp-thing/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 24 Jun 2019 02:50:43 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Miracleman, books 1, 2 &amp; 3</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/miracleman/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Miracleman cover" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2019/06/miracleman.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Alan Moore, Alan Davies, &amp;amp; John Totleben.&lt;/em&gt;  &lt;img alt="spoilers" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/spoilers.svg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I spent a little time digging out earlier works of Alan Moore. These
inter-library loans didn't disappoint.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Originally published as &lt;em&gt;Marvelman&lt;/em&gt; by Mick Anglo, from
1954-59. Legal battles rebranded the character as &lt;em&gt;Miracleman&lt;/em&gt; in 1985.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The opening pages reprint one of those campy early stories, involving
primary-colored moralizing while flying around to punch time-travelling Nazi
super-scientists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They then continue with Alan Moore's postmodern 1980s reboot. This recasts the
simplistic tales of the original period as a placating dream, fed to a captured
Miracleman by his nemesis. His hokey origins story is similarly re-ploughed. The
ensuing tales are dark and introspective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One thread follows the emotional stresses placed on Miracleman when incarnated
as his human alter-ego, the frail and fallible half of a godlike being. He's
unable to conceive a child with his wife, although &lt;em&gt;Miracleman&lt;/em&gt; can, and
succumbs to self-loathing and jealousy, culminating in a touching scene in
which he climbs a mountain, leaves a forlorn monument, and changes into
Miracleman one last time, never to change back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, this is more uneven than Moore's later works. Yes, it's unashamedly an
underwear-on-the-outside superhero story. But nonetheless I loved it, and
scenes like the above stayed with me for months.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also this month:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Atrocity Archive&lt;/strong&gt; by Charles Stross. The conceit of Lovecraftian horror
rationalized to a mathematical or computable topic is appealing to me, and
kept the pages turning, but I didn't ultimately find it life-changing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Nightwings&lt;/strong&gt; by Robert Silverberg. A fantastical far-future tale of humanity
split into occupational castes, guarding the world against prophesied
invasion. Not my thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: both"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>comic</category><category>fiction</category><category>media</category><category>moore</category><category>science-fiction</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/miracleman/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 20 Jun 2019 15:17:46 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>From Hell</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/from-hell/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="From Hell" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2007/07/fromhellsm.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Alan Moore (author), Eddie Campbell (artist) (1989)&lt;/em&gt; &lt;img alt="spoilers" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/spoilers.svg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moore has almost single-handedly transformed the definition of the comic
industry in the last 20 years, and this fetishistically researched
comic-book dramatisation of the dark and macabre Jack the Ripper murders
is no exception to his visionary high standards. Moore plunges headlong
into the sensational conspiracy theory that Royal Physician, Dr. William
Gull, killed East End prostitutes to silence the story of an
illegitimate royal baby, under the direct orders of the implacable Queen
Victoria herself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr Gull regards his mission as the great work of his life, which will
not only quash the threat to the crown, but also fulfil ancient pagan
destinies, reasserting the male dominance over matriarchy that began
when the Romans reclaimed London and slew Queen Boadicea. Gull knows
this because he has knelt before his God, who told him just what needed
to be done. As a doctor, Gull knows that these visions are madness,
brought about by his stroke of the previous year. As a man, however, he
responds that "If this is madness, who'd be sane?", and, embracing the
subjective reality of his hallucinations, he goes about his work with
gusto, confiding along the way in his witless coachman and reluctant
accomplice, Nettley.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Dr Gull and coachman Nettley" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2007/07/boadicea-died-sm.jpg" title="Dr. Gull &amp;amp; coachman Nettley"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The story is a tapestry, woven on many levels. The iniquities of wealth
and power are richly depicted as the poverty-stricken residents of the
East End are contrasted with the powers-that-be, who move swiftly and
decisively to ensure that Gull is never caught nor found out, for fear
of scandal, even while he goes on killing with impunity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The appalling violence of the murders and dismemberment of the victims
is shown in unflinching detail, one pivotal 34-page chapter "The Best of
all Tailors", consisting solely of the actions of Gull, a renowned
surgeon, with his victim in a tiny, squalid room, which made me
profoundly grateful that the sketches are only in black-and-white.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Such graphic nastiness is not for no reason. Gull is convinced that the
act of violence is a pivotal part of the ancient and grisly prophesies
he is enacting. Under the psychological strain of each successive
murder, Gull experiences increasingly vivid hallucinations, symptoms of
his condition. But then, something altogether strange starts to happen.
As his visions become more vivid, Gull begins to experience glimpses of
the future. Visions of our time. At times and places where people have
historically claimed to have seen the ghost of Jack the Ripper, Moore
cunningly reverses the perspective, allowing Gull to see them also. By
the end, Gull's visions have him stalking the sterile hallways of the
modern world in blood-soaked shirtsleeves, roaring at oblivious office
workers, exhorting them to look up and remember the history from which
our century was birthed in blood. The ancient magic that Gull raved
about was real, while we have lost our connection to our violent and
animal past, and with it, our very humanity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Nettley's coach - harbinger of doom." src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2007/07/coach-sm.png" title="Nettley's coach - harbinger of doom."&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rating: 10/10.
Cor blimey it's a classic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: both"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>comic</category><category>fiction</category><category>media</category><category>mental-health</category><category>moore</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/from-hell/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 22 Jul 2007 03:34:22 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>