<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>tartley.com (Posts about dina)</title><link>https://tartley.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://tartley.com/categories/dina.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2023 &lt;a href="mailto:tartley @ the domain tartley dot com"&gt;Jonathan Hartley&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 03 Aug 2023 20:27:27 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Dina font as an OTF.</title><link>https://tartley.com/posts/dina-as-otf/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;The Dina font, converted to an OpenType Font (see screenshots at the bottom of
the page):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href="https://tartley.com/files/2020/Dina-v2.93-otf.tar.gz"&gt;&lt;span class="emoji"&gt;📦&lt;/span&gt; Dina-v2.93-otf.tar.gz&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://gitlab.gnome.org/GNOME/pango/issues/386"&gt;Pango dropped support for naive bitmap fonts&lt;/a&gt;
in v1.44 -- i.e. from Ubuntu 20.04, &lt;em&gt;Focal&lt;/em&gt;, onwards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So all bitmap fonts need to be converted into a format that will render,
ie. a vector format such as OpenType that allows bitmaps to be embedded.
(Not a conversion of the bitmap into an outline, losing the advantages of
the crisp, tiny bitmaps.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For most bitmap fonts, this conversion will be done for you, by packagers
or font authors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But you'll need to do it yourself for any peripheral fonts that you love
more than your distribution does. Here's how I did it for my
&lt;a href="http://www.dcmembers.com/jibsen/download/61/"&gt;beloved Dina&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;1. Identify the font file.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="code"&gt;&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;fc-list&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;|&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;grep&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;Dina
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;2. Convert.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use either command line tools, or fontforge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;2.1 Using fontforge&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A GUI tool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Open up fontforge, paste the font path in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;File / generate fonts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Select:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Left dropdown: "OpenType (CFF)"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Right dropdown: "In TTF/OTF"&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Generate&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The results have some problems. I'm using it in gnome-terminal:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;People converting other fonts report issues with ugly gaps between
  characters. But I don't see that, perhaps because it's a monospace font?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The converted font is invisible in font selection dialogs, making it look
  like the process did not work. But once selected, by clicking around blindly,
  then the font displays fine in applications.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using a font size which is not defined in the font displays a blank terminal,
  instead of falling back to some other font.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using ctrl-+/- to select font sizes cycles through three of the four
  defined sizes. I don't know why it skips one. But all four are usable if
  you explicitly select a size.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;2.2 Using command-line tools&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The process is described at
https://fedoraproject.org/wiki/BitmapFontConversion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ubuntu's released version of fonttosfnt (1.0.4) produces unusable results:
* Only the 1st and 2nd smallest font sizes are preserved.
* In the 2nd smallest size, all variations are too bold, so that 'bold'
  variations look 'double-bold'. (Italics looks really ugly too, this may
  just be a result of the enboldening.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TODO: Consider trying the latest fonttosfnt (1.1.0)
https://gitlab.freedesktop.org/xorg/app/fonttosfnt
or at least filing an issue there to try and get some help.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;3. Install&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Copy to &lt;code&gt;~/.local/share/fonts&lt;/code&gt; (or &lt;code&gt;~/.fonts&lt;/code&gt;, right?)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;fc-cache -f&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The result&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know, it doesn't look like much.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://tartley.com/files/2020/terminal-dina-small-ll.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But compare it with a regular vector font. Here's Ubuntu Mono, the &lt;em&gt;best&lt;/em&gt; of
the vector fonts I could find at these sizes. Blurry and inconsistent and hard
to read:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://tartley.com/files/2020/terminal-ubuntumono-small-ll.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>dina</category><category>fonts</category><category>linux</category><category>terminal</category><guid>https://tartley.com/posts/dina-as-otf/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2020 20:51:33 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>My Fonts Look Crap. I blame Windows and ATI.</title><link>https://tartley.com/posts/my-fonts-look-crap-i-blame-windows-and-ati/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;I know, I &lt;em&gt;know&lt;/em&gt;. But I use Windows for 8 hours a day at work. So what
do you do?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's the poster-boy for programmer-friendly fonts, your friend and
mine, everyone loves him, &lt;strong&gt;Inconsolata&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://tartley.com/files/2010/01/inconsolata-11.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="inconsolata-11" src="https://tartley.com/files/2010/01/inconsolata-11.png" title="inconsolata-11"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don't know about you, but to me that looks unutterably crap. Wonky and
irregular. On the right of the orange line is what it looks like with
ClearType turned off. Meh. Presumably I'm doing it wrong, somehow, but
unless I figure out how, Inconsolata can fuck right off.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So then I fire up the trusty fallback, &lt;strong&gt;Consolas&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://tartley.com/files/2010/01/consolas-10.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="consolas-10" src="https://tartley.com/files/2010/01/consolas-10.png" title="consolas-10"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is better, certainly, but the letters look cramped. For the number
of visible lines in a window that size, the letters are awful small.
Again, on the right of the line is ClearType turned off - which in this
case distinctly worse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I continue peering at a succession of monospaced idiocy, eventually
ending up on &lt;strong&gt;DejaVu Sans Mono&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://tartley.com/files/2010/01/deja-vu-sans-mono-9.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="deja-vu-sans-mono-9" src="https://tartley.com/files/2010/01/deja-vu-sans-mono-9.png" title="deja-vu-sans-mono-9"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This still isn't perfect, but it's the best I can find. Note that it
bears out my impression of Consolas being cramped - even though the
letters are substantially larger, we still manage to fit an extra line
of text in. This time, turning ClearType off (right of the line) makes
it a little crisper, and a little more wonky, but not much.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This isn't just in Vim. It looks like this in all applications. I've
tried running the &lt;a href="http://www.microsoft.com/typography/ClearTypePowerToy.mspx"&gt;ClearType Tuning
Powertool&lt;/a&gt;,
to no avail. Admittedly, all these fonts start to look a damn sight
better when I increase the size a few notches. But that's bugger all use
really, isn't it? Maybe I should be digging out some mono fonts designed
especially to be viewed at small sizes? Oooh, now that's actually not a
bad idea: How about those Android fonts everyone's banging on about?
&lt;strong&gt;Droid Sans Mono:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://tartley.com/files/2010/01/droid-sans-mono-101.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="droid-sans-mono-10" src="https://tartley.com/files/2010/01/droid-sans-mono-101.png" title="droid-sans-mono-10"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This isn't bad, but does contain all the old 'zero vs upper-case O' and
'one versus lower-case L' ambiguities. I think I'll stick with DejaVu
Sans Mono.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Does Inconsolata work OK on Windows for everyone else?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update&lt;/strong&gt;: Gerry suggested trying out Proggy Fonts (thanks!). These are
bitmap fonts (unless you want to do without extended characters) so they
won't scale. Nevertheless, here's how some representative fonts from
there look. First up, &lt;strong&gt;Proggy Clean slashed zero:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://tartley.com/files/2010/01/proggy-clean-sz.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="proggy-clean-sz font" src="https://tartley.com/files/2010/01/proggy-clean-sz.png" title="proggy-clean-sz"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I love the crisp clarity of a pixel-perfect bitmap font with no scaling
or anti-aliasing. On the downside, I have a feeling that the characters'
shapes aren't quite as well-formed and beautiful as &lt;em&gt;DejaVu&lt;/em&gt;. Not sure
whether or not this would bug me. Next up, &lt;strong&gt;Proggy Opti:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://tartley.com/files/2010/01/proggy-opti.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="proggy-opti font" src="https://tartley.com/files/2010/01/proggy-opti.png" title="proggy-opti"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Color me impressed. &lt;em&gt;Opti&lt;/em&gt; still has the wonderful pixel-perfect clarity
of &lt;em&gt;Proggy Clean&lt;/em&gt;, and manages to fit four extra lines of text into the
same sized window. Obviously in order to achieve this, the characters
are smaller than &lt;em&gt;Deja Vu&lt;/em&gt;, but this is no bad thing. I would have liked
to scale Deja Vu down a tad from the size you see it above, but if I
try, the letters start to become a little distorted and indistinct. I
might well give Opti a spin for a few days, see how it wears on me.
Thanks for the suggestion Gerry!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update:&lt;/strong&gt; Nowadays I use &lt;a href="https://github.com/ProgrammingFonts/ProgrammingFonts/tree/master/Dina"&gt;Dina&lt;/a&gt;,
a monospaced bitmap font created by some obsessive with a penchant for
microscopic fonts. It's absolutely perfect.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>dina</category><category>fonts</category><category>geek</category><category>mswin-dev</category><category>software</category><guid>https://tartley.com/posts/my-fonts-look-crap-i-blame-windows-and-ati/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 21 Jan 2010 02:21:09 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>