<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>tartley.com (Posts about doctorow)</title><link>https://tartley.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://tartley.com/categories/doctorow.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2023 &lt;a href="mailto:tartley @ the domain tartley dot com"&gt;Jonathan Hartley&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 07 Jul 2023 01:59:32 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Do a bit of helping out at EuroPython</title><link>https://tartley.com/posts/do-a-bit-of-helping-out-at-europython/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Are you a &lt;a href="http://python.org"&gt;Python&lt;/a&gt; geek?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For starters - you should totally be going to
&lt;a href="http://www.europython.eu/"&gt;EuroPython&lt;/a&gt; at the end of June. Python
conferences like this attract brilliant presentations from some real
community and industry heavyweights. This year we've got &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tony_Hoare"&gt;Professor Sir
Tony Hoare&lt;/a&gt; (that's the creator
of &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quicksort"&gt;quicksort&lt;/a&gt; to you, amongst a
venerable lifetime's worth of other
things); &lt;a href="http://blogs.msdn.com/hugunin/"&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://craphound.com/"&gt;Cory
Doctorow&lt;/a&gt; (everyone's favourite science-fiction
author, blogger and all-round geek activist), &lt;a href="http://www.mindviewinc.com/Index.php"&gt;Bruce
Eckel&lt;/a&gt; (author and renowned
technical communicator); plus Dr Sue Black from code-breaking hothouse
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bletchley_park"&gt;Bletchley Park&lt;/a&gt;. The
&lt;a href="http://www.europython.eu/talks/timetable/"&gt;veritable horde&lt;/a&gt; of over 100
exciting and interesting talks makes up probably the strongest line-up
EuroPython has ever had.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Best of all, Python conferences like this one are organised and run at a
grass-roots level. By enthusiasts, for enthusiasts, making them quite
the most fun, educational and interestingly social conferences I've ever
been to. Personally, I love the resultant absence of overriding
commercial agendas - everything is done purely for the benefit of the
delegates, and is pervaded by the community values that made you love
Python in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One upside of this is that the conference is cheap - only £190 to
attend. Interested enthusiasts can easily pay their own way. As a
result, this is one of the few technical conferences that still has a
robust attendance this year - both of presenters and delegates. Many
others have been decimated or even cancelled altogether.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a downside though, and here's the rub:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The good folks organising EuroPython in their spare time are desperately
short of volunteers to be session chairs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you're going to EuroPython, you could help out! Yes, YOU! You could
sign up for the sessions you want to watch anyway, so you shouldn't miss
anything. Just imagine the warm and fuzzies! The KUDOS of a roomful of
eyes. The POWER of cutting off over-running speakers in mid-flow*. The
WARMTH of a deftly-cupped microphone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(*anyone cutting the power on Sir Tony will be duly ejected from the
premises)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Responsibilities are described in loving detail here:
&lt;a href="http://wiki.europython.eu/SessionTeam"&gt;http://wiki.europython.eu/SessionTeam&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please think about it, and if you fancy it, sign up soon (on the wiki
page above) because we're currently all a-flutter wondering how the heck
we're going to manage this. :-)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks!&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>doctorow</category><category>geek</category><category>python</category><category>software</category><guid>https://tartley.com/posts/do-a-bit-of-helping-out-at-europython/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 09 Jun 2009 20:13:40 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Makers</title><link>https://tartley.com/posts/makers/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Makers cover" src="https://tartley.com/files/2009/makers-cover.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Cory Doctorow&lt;/em&gt; (not yet published.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://craphound.com/"&gt;Cory&lt;/a&gt; very kindly brought an early manuscript of
this as a gift to &lt;a href="http://www.voidspace.org.uk/"&gt;Michael&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href="http://www.gilesthomas.com/"&gt;Giles&lt;/a&gt; and I when we met him a while ago,
and I've been wracked with guilt ever since because I apparently lost it
soon after. Thankfully, it recently turned up (on
&lt;a href="http://babbageclunk.com/"&gt;Christian&lt;/a&gt;'s desk - my fault!) last week, so
I happily finished it pronto.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's his best fiction yet! He must be honing his abilities with
practice. \o/ Michael do you want it next?.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Christian doesn't like my subjectivity-proof rating system, so this one
is specially for him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rating:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;10/10 if you want a lightly styled but deeply speculative and engrossing
story that winds a like a sightseeing tour around the social and
personal ramifications of the ways in which modern technology is
changing the way people interact, organise and get things done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;0/10: If you aren't interested in the ways society is changing under our
feet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: both"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>culture</category><category>doctorow</category><category>fiction</category><category>internet</category><category>media</category><category>novel</category><category>science-fiction</category><guid>https://tartley.com/posts/makers/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 18 Apr 2009 22:10:31 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Trans-Speculative Ramblings</title><link>https://tartley.com/posts/trans-speculative-ramblings/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;If you're not a wild-eyed loon, you're unlikely to appreciate this post.
Bear with me a moment, while I establish some context.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Cory Doctorow" src="https://tartley.com/files/2007/07/cory-doctorow.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So &lt;a href="http://www.craphound.com/"&gt;here's the esteemed Cory Doctorow&lt;/a&gt;. His
recent[*1] post at Locus, &lt;a href="http://www.locusmag.com/Features/2007/07/cory-doctorow-progressive-apocalypse.html"&gt;The Progressive Apocalypse and Other
Futurismic
Delights&lt;/a&gt;,
outlines the parallels between the progressive Enlightenment ideals of
human progress, and the science fiction hot topic of &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_singularity"&gt;the
singularity&lt;/a&gt;. Accelerating
rates of change, empowered by self-improving general artificial (or
post-human) intelligence, eventually reaches a point at which society -
or the individual - can do anything it wants to. Since, by that point,
society is so educated and well-adjusted, so &lt;em&gt;enlightened&lt;/em&gt;, its goals
are those things that bring yet more progress and joy and compassion
into the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Describing this as a 'Rapture of the Nerds' (&lt;a href="http://www.acceleratingfuture.com/steven/?p=21#comment-181"&gt;not by Ken
MacLeod&lt;/a&gt;) is
evocative - but it distracts from the important fact that the &lt;em&gt;true&lt;/em&gt;
singularity is a rapture for everyone. The singularity is only for nerds
right now because the nerds are the only ones who get it yet. I posit
that one of the most prominent effects of enlightenment - coupled with
the availability of resources that such enlightenment would allow - is
the freedom to indulge in fairly advanced morality, encompassing an
overwhelming realisation of the importance that no concious being gets
left behind. Incidentally, this is of course the reason why advanced
civilisations tend to
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Sublimed"&gt;sublime&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;en masse&lt;/em&gt;, without
leaving detectable offshoots mooching around in our universe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyhow, I'm distracting myself. The important thread I'm groping for
here is the literal equivalence Cory alludes to between the science
fictional singularity, and the biblical judgement day - the trump and
the shout, the culmination of all things human, at which point it
becomes our turn to sublime, overcoming the restrictions of the physical
universe, to take our place in the mind of God Almighty, the living and
the dead alike. Or at least those of the dead who had sufficient
foresight to have had their state vector preserved, at any rate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still with me? Singularity = Judgement Day. Got it? Ok.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://sentientdevelopments.blogspot.com"&gt;&lt;img alt="George
Dvorsky" src="https://tartley.com/files/2007/07/georgedvorsky.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, over here, we have
&lt;a href="http://sentientdevelopments.blogspot.com"&gt;George Dvorsky&lt;/a&gt;,
who recently[*1] referenced an old post of his, &lt;a href="http://sentientdevelopments.blogspot.com/2006/03/our-non-arbitrary-universe.html"&gt;Our non-arbitrary
universe&lt;/a&gt;,
in which he talks about possible explanations for the extraordinarily
unlikely state we find the universe to be in, while attempting to steer
clear of the slippery fish that is the strong anthropic principle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One prominent hypothesis is that the universe's operational parameters
have been tuned with excruciating finesse by a process of natural
selection, which could be brought about by universes being
self-replicating entities. The replication of universes could therefore
be theorised, by some mechanism that is completely unknown. This would
lead us to expect that universes be tuned for maximal rate of
reproduction, whatever that would entail. So why, George asks, does our
universe appear to be tuned to be so patently &lt;em&gt;biophilic&lt;/em&gt;, ie. conducive
to life? All these innumerable cosy blobs of matter basking in the glow
of lovely stars, all consisting of an entertaining mixture of quite the
most engaging set of chemicals one could ever wish to meet, and so on
and so forth, down to the infinitesimal balancing acts of forces that
conspire to make nuclear physics work in such a jolly interesting way,
and enough spatial dimensions to make interactions interesting without
so many as to subject them all to the tiresome severity of a whole
family of inverse to-the-ninth laws.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It might simply be that efficiently-replicating universes are
coincidentally also biophilic. Certainly there are some characteristics
that seem to be equally desirable for either condition, such as
universes that are both large and long-lived. However, George discusses
the idea of this not merely being a coincidental convergence, but
causal, due to life playing a role in helping universes to replicate -
hence universes teeming with life will go on to reproduce more,
dominating the natural selective process to create more universes which
are ever more suitable to life. This could come about if life plays some
part in the reproduction of its host universe. Perhaps if intelligent
life deliberately causes its host universe to replicate. Who wouldn't
want to become God, once we'd figured out how to spawn realities at
right-angles to... er... reality?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;. . .&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, I'd like to take a moment here to catch our breath. I'm well aware
that we're out on a limb of speculation that is extended so far beyond
the realms of anything resembling genuine hypothesis that we cannot
consider this to be anything other than a poetic fantasy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And yet. I can't help but play with the idea of linking the two concepts
in my mind. Imagining post-singular civilisations discovering a
mechanism by which disjoint bubbles of time and space can be pinched off
from our own. Perhaps it can be done under some conditions that already
occur naturally, deep in the heart of stars, or in the wrenching
oscillations of time and space that wreath a galactic-mass black hole.
Or perhaps this is brought about by some conjunction of circumstance
that has never occurred before, at least not for all of &lt;em&gt;this&lt;/em&gt;
universe's timeline.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first such bubbles are stillborn. Empty and degenerate, lacking
coherence enough for either spatial or temporal dimensions, they
collapse in spans of time that can barely be considered to exist at all.
But the unimaginable intellect of planetary sized masses converted
entirely into hyper-spatially networked hive-minds examines the
new-found discovery, with an absolute, unerring insight, but also with
wisdom, and with compassion. Options are considered, consequences
charted, and at the speed of thought vast resources of matter and energy
are focussed on replicating the experiment. Enlarging it. Seeding the
discontinuities with precisely the right twist of quantum instability
for each of the nascent realities to spew forth their own internal
fountains of time and space, matter and energy. Riding the feedback of
previously uncharted mathematics to inflate each successive genesis to
greater and greater energies, weaving ever more intricate internal
structures into the harmonious interplay of forces that comprise their
innermost workings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A pause. Awed by their achievements, overcome by the assimilation of the
fields of science they have uncovered, and humbled by their potential,
the intelligences stop to take stock. To survey their possibilities.
Then, inevitably, fulfilling a manifest destiny as old as time itself,
leveraging the qualities of the space gifted to them by their own,
infinitely distant forebears, they initialise a final push, building on
the properties of their own universe to create one still greater. A
leviathan, containing an unthinkable torrent of creation, bright enough
to light a sky with its echoes forever.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's the whole "Let there be light" number. Humanity gets to literally
&lt;em&gt;become&lt;/em&gt; God. And the funny thing is, such a creator is not only imbued
with all the properties of a traditional new-testament Christian style
God, ie. wisdom and compassion and love, but we simultaneously tie
together the Judgement Day of one civilisation's culmination with the
Genesis of another's reality. Each successive generation irrevocably
separated from their own God by being at right angles to their reality,
and yet tied in chains stretching back unbroken through the countless
histories of innumerable universes, by the bonds of direct, causal
creation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyhow, it's all very derivative, and I stole one irresistible phrase
from &lt;a href="http://www.strangehorizons.com/2006/20060904/house-f.shtml"&gt;Benjamin
Rosenbaum&lt;/a&gt;,
but it would make for a smashing short science fiction story, don't you
think?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Note *1: I wrote most of this months ago, but never got around to
hitting 'Post', so forgive the no-longer accurate references to 'recent'
events.)&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>doctorow</category><category>geek</category><category>imho</category><category>write</category><guid>https://tartley.com/posts/trans-speculative-ramblings/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 09 May 2008 05:27:05 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Someone Comes to Town, Someone Leaves Town</title><link>https://tartley.com/posts/someone-comes-to-town-someone-leaves-town/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Someone Comes to Town, Someone Leaves Town" src="https://tartley.com/files/2008/02/someone-comes-to-town.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Cory Doctorow&lt;/em&gt; &lt;img alt="spoilers" src="https://tartley.com/files/spoilers.svg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I just don't know about this one. I really wanted to like it. It starts
out with an interesting, down-to-earth story about a guy establishing
himself in a new neighbourhood, setting up an open wireless mesh net
across the neighbourhood, back in a day when this was still a &lt;em&gt;really
cool idea&lt;/em&gt;. This tale is then peppered with initially disconcerting non-literal
sounding references to his family, such as the cliffs and caves of his Father,
the mountain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps I embarked upon it too casually. It was certainly engaging, but
by the last few pages I began to suspect that threads of the plot had
eluded me. For example, I had entertained the idea that the fantasy
elements of the story were actually the product of the main character's
stated intention to write a book, which is otherwise only mentioned in
passing here and there. However, the fantasy is woven extremely tightly
together with the realistic aspects of the story, such that I can't
discern any clear boundary to distinguish between the two. So I'm left
wondering if parts of the book didn't actually happen, and if so, which
parts? I should have anticipated someone like &lt;a href="http://craphound.com"&gt;Mr
Doctorow&lt;/a&gt; would have to be a terrific smarty-pants
in the narrative department, and I doubtless should have paid more
attention along the way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rating: 6/10 - One to revisit, maybe, if I like his other stuff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update 12th Feb:&lt;/strong&gt; Coincidentally, I just read a short story by Cory,
&lt;em&gt;I Row-boat&lt;/em&gt;, which despite the awful titular pun, I really liked.
However, I've read a bunch of discussion about &lt;em&gt;Someone Comes to
Town...&lt;/em&gt;, and I don't seem to have missed much that anyone else has been
getting out of it. So while I'm looking forward to other stuff by him,
I'm sticking by my low rating for this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: both"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>doctorow</category><category>fiction</category><category>media</category><category>novel</category><guid>https://tartley.com/posts/someone-comes-to-town-someone-leaves-town/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 08 Feb 2008 07:01:37 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Hacker Crackdown : Law and Disorder on the Electronic Frontier</title><link>https://tartley.com/posts/the-hacker-crackdown-law-and-disorder-on-the-electronic-frontier/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="The Hacker Crackdown" src="https://tartley.com/files/2008/01/hacker-crackdown.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Bruce Sterling, &lt;a href="http://www.archive.org/search.php?query=hacker%20crackdown%20AND%20mediatype%3Aaudio%20AND%20collection%3Aopensource_audio"&gt;read aloud by Cory Doctorow&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Only the second audiobook I've bothered to listen to, and it seems to
work very well, especially when commuting, since you can continue
listening without interruption while leaving the tube and walking. (It's
taken me 36 years to figure this out? Genius.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cory does a fine job of reading, and I'm grateful to him for bringing
this important book to my attention. When he describes reading it on
it's publication in 1994 as 'life changing', I can understand why. It
describes the clash of cultures resulting from American law
enforcement's attempts to crack down on the hackers, crackers and
phreaks of the nascent cyberpunk underworld of the early '90s. Many of
the underlying issues have even more relevance today. Can taking a copy
of digital information be equated with stealing, given that the original
owner still retains their original copy? Or is it more analogous to
attempting to overhear a conversation which the speakers would rather
wasn't overheard? While some hackers have real criminal intent, there
are a significant proportion with a very strong ethic to do no harm, who
view their tinkering as merely the exploration of an online frontier,
filled with challenges and puzzles, and rewards of rich hordes of
information - the dispersal of which is not just a god-given right, but
actually a moral responsibility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When law enforcement agencies went after this crowd with a heavy-handed
and indiscriminate approach, teenagers still living with their parents
ended up in court facing years in prison, colossal fines and legal fees,
in some instances simply for simply republishing a document that was
already in widespread circulation. Innocents had tens of thousands of
dollars worth of computers seized and never returned, even though no
charges were ever filed against them. The resulting backlash formed the
beginnings of the Electronic Frontier Foundation, a philanthropic
organization devoted to defending the rights of individuals in the
online realm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This whole tale is laced with many entertaining insights into the quirks
and motives of the colorful individuals involved, and this makes the
whole thing an enjoyable romp through a serious topic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rating: 8/10 - I only wish I'd read it ten years ago&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: both"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>audiobook</category><category>book</category><category>culture</category><category>doctorow</category><category>internet</category><category>law</category><category>media</category><category>non-fiction</category><category>software</category><category>stirling</category><guid>https://tartley.com/posts/the-hacker-crackdown-law-and-disorder-on-the-electronic-frontier/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 02 Feb 2008 22:15:49 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>