<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>tartley.com (Posts about essays)</title><link>https://tartley.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://tartley.com/categories/essays.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2023 &lt;a href="mailto:tartley @ the domain tartley dot com"&gt;Jonathan Hartley&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 12 Apr 2023 01:02:46 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Brief Interviews with Hideous Men</title><link>https://tartley.com/posts/brief-interviews-with-hideous-men/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left; padding: 1em"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Brief Interviews With Hideous Men cover" src="https://tartley.com/files/2014/01/brief-interviews-with-hideous-men.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by David Foster Wallace (1999)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A collection of creative essays, varying from playful to unflinchingly
uncomfortable, shot through with Wallace's typical humour and
introspection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've tended to love and hate his &lt;a href="https://tartley.com/infinite-jest"&gt;other&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="https://tartley.com/everything-and-more"&gt;writing&lt;/a&gt; in equal measure, but with such
ferocity that I unreservedly place him amongst my very favourite
authors. There wasn't even much for me to hate in this one, relatively
lacking as it is in labyrinthine footnotes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A couple of the essays left me cold (&lt;em&gt;Tri-Stan: I Sold Sissee Nar to
Ecko&lt;/em&gt; springs to mind - presumably I'm missing the point entirely),
but most of them I found thoroughly engaging and
thought provoking. I'm tempted to read up on those that seemed most
challenging to me (&lt;em&gt;Church Not Made With Hands&lt;/em&gt;, say), and give them
another try.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's been a while. Rating:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;0/10 if you don't want to delve deeply into sometimes uncomfortable
subjects, such as depression, unconventional sex acts, and rape.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;10/10 if you like to be stretched, or at least stirred around, in
interesting directions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: both"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>essays</category><category>fiction</category><category>media</category><category>wallace</category><guid>https://tartley.com/posts/brief-interviews-with-hideous-men/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2014 02:51:51 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Hackers and Painters</title><link>https://tartley.com/posts/hackers-and-painters/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="" src="https://tartley.com/files/2008/08/hackers__painters2.jpg"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Paul Graham (2004)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'd already stumbled across many of the &lt;a href="http://www.paulgraham.com/articles.html"&gt;individual
essays&lt;/a&gt; that this is comprised
of, but it was still hugely entertaining and educational to discover
some of Graham's essays that I hadn't read yet. He covers a wide variety
of topics, and inevitably for such a collection, the components vary in
quality, but generally they are extremely engaging. I only regret having
to grab them in dead-tree format since I lost my iPhone. Ohdeary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rating: 8/10 - a brilliant read&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: both"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>culture</category><category>essays</category><category>geek</category><category>internet</category><category>media</category><category>non-fiction</category><category>startups</category><guid>https://tartley.com/posts/hackers-and-painters/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 27 Aug 2008 20:06:48 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Portable Jung</title><link>https://tartley.com/posts/the-portable-jung/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="" src="https://tartley.com/files/2008/05/portable-jung.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Carl G. Jung (Author), Joseph Campbell (Editor), R. F. C. Hull (Translator) (written 1920s &amp;amp; '30s, published 1971)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I didn't quite know what to make of Jung when KT first handed me this
collection of his essays, many moons ago. Some sort of 19th-century
lunatic Freudian psycho-analyst who was a dab hand with a ouija board
and sang the praises of ritual sacrifices to the almighty triple-headed
hermaphrodite goddesses, right? Something like that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So it was good to discover that Dr. Jung isn't the wild-eyed loon that
I'd written him off as. His attitude is entirely credible and
scientific, and while he may &lt;em&gt;invoke&lt;/em&gt; triple-headed hermaphrodite
goddesses, he does so in an entirely respectable and deeply pertinent
way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His essays are prefaced by a short biography to set the works in a
meaningful social and personal context. Of particular entertainment
value is the ongoing deterioration of his relationship with Freud, and
the corresponding divergence of their theories. This culminated in
Freud's desperate plea for Jung's cooperation in ensuring that 'the
sexual theory' be established as an unchallengeable axiom in the
explanation of all human behaviours. This didn't strike Jung as being
particularly scientific, and obviously speaks volumes about Freud -
lifelong adulterer - as both a person and a theorist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of the essays themselves, some of them resonated more for me than
others. I very much liked his explanation of the nature of the
subconscious necessarily being the polar opposite to the conscious ego,
since all perceptions which do not fit in with the beliefs or attitudes
of the conscious mind are dismissed and repressed. This is a natural and
normal reaction, and it helps us to maintain a consistent and useful
world-view. However, those repressed memories are not erased - they are
simply being ignored by the concious mind. The subconscious appears to
have unfettered access to these repressed fragments. In situations where
the conciousness exercises wilful determination, this leads to a
stressful state of cognitive dissonance, in which the subconscious
comprises a roiling mass of all the impressions and emotions that the
concious mind has rejected. Hence, the tendancy for people to maintain a
strident outward appearance which is completely at odds with, and
arguably exacerbates, pent-up inner demons. For some reason, the
examples that spring to my mind are priests molesting altar boys, or
maybe catholic schoolgirls. Not sure if that's a reflection of modern
organised religion or my own state of mind, oh well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Equally interesting is Jung's theory of the collective unconscious -
that the religions, myths and legends of the world are united by a
handful of common themes, or archetypes, not because of
cross-pollination of ideas, but because these themes are an expression
of psychological commonalities between all human minds - seems credible
and useful. I still have some reservation in accepting Jung's particular
menagerie of archetypes as definitive. He may have distilled them from
many years studying the world's religions and mythologies, but if you
throw enough noise at a filter the result ends up being characteristic
of the filter (ie. Jung himself) rather than the noise. However, the
validity of the idea in general, and of some of fundamental archetypes,
seems unarguable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He carefully avoids any explicit judgement of whether any religions or
myths have any basis in objective reality. Such judgements, he rightly
notes, are beyond the ability of the scientific method to evaluate.
However, he provides the potential to categorise them all as simply
being phenomena of human psychology - ie. they are entirely in our head.
This is a double-edge sword, however, for this seeming dismissal
rebounds poetically upon us. What were once distant and faintly heard
mythologies, are now given a deep and highly personal significance, as
they are nothing less than the worldy manifestations of the innermost
workings of our own minds, which each of us would fail to heed at our
peril.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are other sections which I didn't find so compelling, such as his
concept of synchronicity, but overall it was thoroughly enjoyable and
insightful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rating: 8/10&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: both"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>essays</category><category>media</category><category>non-fiction</category><category>psychology</category><guid>https://tartley.com/posts/the-portable-jung/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 May 2008 18:51:13 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>