<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Made out of meat (Posts about essays)</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://www.tartley.com/categories/essays.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2023 &lt;a href="mailto:tartley @ the domain tartley dot com"&gt;Jonathan Hartley&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 23 Aug 2023 18:34:54 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Ur-Fascism</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/ur-fascism/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Ur-Fascism cover" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2023/ur-fascism-cover.webp"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Umberto Eco, 1995.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eco's prose has left me in the dust on occasion in the past. I missed so many references, or failed to keep up with the relentlessly nested layers of meaning, that I was simply holding on for the ride. This essay matches Eco's characteristically dense, intellectual prose, studded with foreign phrases, and references to contemporary thinkers, historical movements and causes and revolutions and dictatorships, and their antecedents. But it is short, and perhaps in contrast to the flourishes of brilliance that comprise his fiction, this is a factual piece, and is written to be understood rather than to dazzle. It begins by establishing Eco's credentials to speak on this topic, with the first of several entrancing first-hand indications of what it was like to grow up as an intellectual young child in Italy under Mussolini, and the revelations that followed at the opening up of his world at the end of WWII.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He differentiates between the truly totalitarian fascism of, say, Nazism, which subordinated all of life to the state, with the looser, less coherent Italian fascism, noting that this did not derive from any increment of tolerance, merely the absence of a sufficiently encompassing underlying philosophy. Despite this, it is the Italian mode, which was the first right wing dictatorship in modern history, from which subsequent dictators seem to have drawn most stylistic inspiration, and from which our generic term of "fascism" derives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last half of the essay describes how fascism means different things in different contexts, but the various incarnations through history have exhibited sufficiently overlapping sets of symptoms as to glean a family resemblance. Eco enumerates 13 identifying traits, noting that the presence of even one of them can be sufficient to allow fascism to coagulate around it. Mostly for my own benefit, (with my own parenthesised observations) they are, briefly:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fascism incorporates a cult of tradition. This can be deployed as an automatic refutation of any undesirable new ideas, enshrining in their place the immutable wisdom of a mythical past. In addition, traditionalism undermines the perceived value of learning in itself - pre-emptively thwarting troublesome intellectuals. This anti-intellectual received wisdom, in order to provide whichever justifications are required of it, requires the syncretistic combination of various ancient beliefs. As a result it must tolerate contradictions. Indeed, the more stark they are, the better they serve the purpose of selecting followers who will obediently think whatever they are told.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rejection of modernism. This is a powerful recruiting tool, enabling the fascist to leverage any dissatisfaction of the populous, laying claim to the emotionally appealing universal solution of a regression to simpler, happier times, while simultaneously rewinding societal progress in equality or liberty. While Nazis and fascists love their technology, this is a superficial tool, used in support of a deeply regressive project, namely the restoration of power to those with the strength and the will to take it. This irrationality goes hand in hand with anti-intellectualism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Value vigor and action above reflection. Thinking is emasculation. Culture is suspect insofar as it aligns with any sort of critical theory or values. Regard centers of analysis or learning such as libraries or universities with suspicion for harboring - or even indoctrinating - people of opposing political viewpoints. Again, this is deeply intertwined with (1) &amp;amp; (2), and its prevalence pre-emptively defuses any kind of mainstream understanding or critique.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of the above make it inevitable that any given fascist regime will be rife with internal contradictions.  While modernity achieves its intellectual prowess through the nurturing of diverse thought, fascism cannot possibly withstand any critical analysis. Hence, disagreement is treason.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fascist appeal to popularity exploits and exacerbates the natural fear of &lt;em&gt;the other&lt;/em&gt;, and hence is always inherently racist. Expect demonization of immigrants, foreigners, other nation states, as well as other marginalized groups, taking advantage of whatever local contemporary biases and fears might be present.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The above exploitation takes the form of an appeal to the frustrations of the middle class - or whichever class can be most useful and readily mobilized by persuasion that their problems are caused by some identifiable other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Modernity genuinely does disintegrate traditional social bonds, along with sources of identity and meaning. Fascism's solution to this is to unify the disaffected under the only remaining banner common to them all, that of patriotism and nationalism. This unity is strengthened by emphasis on the country's enemies, and especially by conspiracy theories of secret international plots against the nation. Followers must feel besieged (as Trump advised the January 6th crowd that "America is under siege"). Eco makes special mention, in the U.S, of Pat Robertson's &lt;em&gt;The New World Order&lt;/em&gt;, but potential sources of conspiracy are innumerable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Followers can be riled into frenzy of humiliation at their enemies' wealth or power. Jews control the
world and its money. Instead of coastal liberals, refer to coastal elites. But at the same time, the instinct to action requires that enemies can easily be defeated. Hence enemies are simultaneously too weak and too strong. Herein lies one of fascism's greatest weaknesses, responsible for several lost wars, in that it is constitutionally incapable of objectively assessing an enemy's strength.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Goad followers into violent action with rhetoric not just of a struggle for survival, but by declaration that life is struggle, and hence pacifism is conspiring with the enemy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While fascism appeals for the participation of the population by promising empowerment for the majority, its naked power lust is a fundamentally aristocratic endeavor. The leader takes power from those too weak to oppose  him, disdaining both conquered rivals and the subjugated population. Power struggles within the Party are vicious, and the party rides roughshod over the citizens, who likewise are leagues above the disenfranchised. The hierarchy is strict, steep, and ruthless. Elitism abounds, as does fear of losing one's status.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The redress of modernity's threadbare social fabric, by emphasizing nationalism and strength, further erodes interpersonal solidarity. Each individual must becomes their own hero. Strong, independent, and utterly without recourse in times of need. The cult of the hero is intimately entwined with a cult of death. Having only the narrow causes of the nation and the Party to live for, the hero yearns for a heroic death - or, better, to demonstrate their power and status by sending others to their death.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The preeminent will to power, so often frustrated in an aristocratic, dog-eat-dog social order, manifests alternately in things like machismo, disdain for women, and phallic fetishization of weapons. Repressed insecurity breeds an outward contempt for unconventional sexuality, including chastity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Under fascism, the people have no innate rights, and hence no material preferences or expression. Instead, the leader pretends to interpret the Will of the People. This charade requires the party apparatus to select and amplify some emotional response of the people, and present it as representative, so that the party can be empowered to act on behalf of that supposedly majority. Consider the amplifications of manufactured outrage about culture war issues, so that elected representatives are empowered to act decisively on their own preferences, against the majority of the population's wishes. This leads directly to confrontation with institutions such as a parliament. Fascism will therefore cast aspersions on any properly functioning parliament's legitimacy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All fascisms make use of their own varieties of NewSpeak, using an impoverished vocabulary and syntax, in order to limit the instruments for critical reasoning. This may appear in apparently innocent forms, from schoolbooks to popular talk shows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>essays</category><category>media</category><category>non-fiction</category><category>politics</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/ur-fascism/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 12 Jul 2023 00:41:42 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Brief Interviews with Hideous Men</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/brief-interviews-with-hideous-men/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left; padding: 1em"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Brief Interviews With Hideous Men cover" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2014/01/brief-interviews-with-hideous-men.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by David Foster Wallace (1999)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A collection of creative essays, varying from playful to unflinchingly
uncomfortable, shot through with Wallace's typical humour and
introspection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've tended to love and hate his &lt;a href="https://www.tartley.com/infinite-jest"&gt;other&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.tartley.com/everything-and-more"&gt;writing&lt;/a&gt; in equal measure, but with such
ferocity that I unreservedly place him amongst my very favourite
authors. There wasn't even much for me to hate in this one, relatively
lacking as it is in labyrinthine footnotes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A couple of the essays left me cold (&lt;em&gt;Tri-Stan: I Sold Sissee Nar to
Ecko&lt;/em&gt; springs to mind - presumably I'm missing the point entirely),
but most of them I found thoroughly engaging and
thought provoking. I'm tempted to read up on those that seemed most
challenging to me (&lt;em&gt;Church Not Made With Hands&lt;/em&gt;, say), and give them
another try.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's been a while. Rating:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;0/10 if you don't want to delve deeply into sometimes uncomfortable
subjects, such as depression, unconventional sex acts, and rape.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;10/10 if you like to be stretched, or at least stirred around, in
interesting directions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: both"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>essays</category><category>fiction</category><category>media</category><category>wallace</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/brief-interviews-with-hideous-men/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2014 02:51:51 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Hackers and Painters</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/hackers-and-painters/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2008/08/hackers__painters2.jpg"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Paul Graham (2004)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'd already stumbled across many of the &lt;a href="http://www.paulgraham.com/articles.html"&gt;individual
essays&lt;/a&gt; that this is comprised
of, but it was still hugely entertaining and educational to discover
some of Graham's essays that I hadn't read yet. He covers a wide variety
of topics, and inevitably for such a collection, the components vary in
quality, but generally they are extremely engaging. I only regret having
to grab them in dead-tree format since I lost my iPhone. Ohdeary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rating: 8/10 - a brilliant read&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: both"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>culture</category><category>essays</category><category>geek</category><category>internet</category><category>media</category><category>non-fiction</category><category>startups</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/hackers-and-painters/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 27 Aug 2008 20:06:48 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Portable Jung</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/the-portable-jung/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2008/05/portable-jung.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Carl G. Jung (Author), Joseph Campbell (Editor), R. F. C. Hull (Translator) (written 1920s &amp;amp; '30s, published 1971)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I didn't quite know what to make of Jung when KT first handed me this
collection of his essays, many moons ago. Some sort of 19th-century
lunatic Freudian psycho-analyst who was a dab hand with a ouija board
and sang the praises of ritual sacrifices to the almighty triple-headed
hermaphrodite goddesses, right? Something like that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So it was good to discover that Dr. Jung isn't the wild-eyed loon that
I'd written him off as. His attitude is entirely credible and
scientific, and while he may &lt;em&gt;invoke&lt;/em&gt; triple-headed hermaphrodite
goddesses, he does so in an entirely respectable and deeply pertinent
way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His essays are prefaced by a short biography to set the works in a
meaningful social and personal context. Of particular entertainment
value is the ongoing deterioration of his relationship with Freud, and
the corresponding divergence of their theories. This culminated in
Freud's desperate plea for Jung's cooperation in ensuring that 'the
sexual theory' be established as an unchallengeable axiom in the
explanation of all human behaviours. This didn't strike Jung as being
particularly scientific, and obviously speaks volumes about Freud -
lifelong adulterer - as both a person and a theorist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of the essays themselves, some of them resonated more for me than
others. I very much liked his explanation of the nature of the
subconscious necessarily being the polar opposite to the conscious ego,
since all perceptions which do not fit in with the beliefs or attitudes
of the conscious mind are dismissed and repressed. This is a natural and
normal reaction, and it helps us to maintain a consistent and useful
world-view. However, those repressed memories are not erased - they are
simply being ignored by the concious mind. The subconscious appears to
have unfettered access to these repressed fragments. In situations where
the conciousness exercises wilful determination, this leads to a
stressful state of cognitive dissonance, in which the subconscious
comprises a roiling mass of all the impressions and emotions that the
concious mind has rejected. Hence, the tendancy for people to maintain a
strident outward appearance which is completely at odds with, and
arguably exacerbates, pent-up inner demons. For some reason, the
examples that spring to my mind are priests molesting altar boys, or
maybe catholic schoolgirls. Not sure if that's a reflection of modern
organised religion or my own state of mind, oh well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Equally interesting is Jung's theory of the collective unconscious -
that the religions, myths and legends of the world are united by a
handful of common themes, or archetypes, not because of
cross-pollination of ideas, but because these themes are an expression
of psychological commonalities between all human minds - seems credible
and useful. I still have some reservation in accepting Jung's particular
menagerie of archetypes as definitive. He may have distilled them from
many years studying the world's religions and mythologies, but if you
throw enough noise at a filter the result ends up being characteristic
of the filter (ie. Jung himself) rather than the noise. However, the
validity of the idea in general, and of some of fundamental archetypes,
seems unarguable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He carefully avoids any explicit judgement of whether any religions or
myths have any basis in objective reality. Such judgements, he rightly
notes, are beyond the ability of the scientific method to evaluate.
However, he provides the potential to categorise them all as simply
being phenomena of human psychology - ie. they are entirely in our head.
This is a double-edge sword, however, for this seeming dismissal
rebounds poetically upon us. What were once distant and faintly heard
mythologies, are now given a deep and highly personal significance, as
they are nothing less than the worldy manifestations of the innermost
workings of our own minds, which each of us would fail to heed at our
peril.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are other sections which I didn't find so compelling, such as his
concept of synchronicity, but overall it was thoroughly enjoyable and
insightful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rating: 8/10&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: both"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>essays</category><category>media</category><category>non-fiction</category><category>psychology</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/the-portable-jung/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 May 2008 18:51:13 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>