<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>tartley.com (Posts about free-to-read)</title><link>https://tartley.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://www.tartley.com/categories/free-to-read.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2022 &lt;a href="mailto:tartley @ the domain tartley dot com"&gt;Jonathan Hartley&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 20 Mar 2022 04:21:58 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Demon</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/demon/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Demon cover" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2021/demon-cover.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Jason Shiga (2016)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm just discovering the works of &lt;a href="http://www.shigabooks.com"&gt;Jason Shiga&lt;/a&gt;,
creator of mathematically-inspired nonlinear comic-books, e.g. stories drawn
on complex origami structures, that can be folded in various ways to represent
either branching story-lines, or else to manage state such as 'inventory'.
Construction of these more elaborate paper constructions doesn't scale,
(ie. I'm not likely to ever own one) but you can try some of his other
creations on the web.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is &lt;a href="http://www.shigabooks.com/index.php?page=001"&gt;Demon&lt;/a&gt;,
a regular linear web-comic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The storyline is 'math-inspired' too, in the same way that the movie &lt;em&gt;Primer&lt;/em&gt;
is - intense, absolute, ruthless, narrative exploration of logical
implications, while continually, dizzyingly, escalating to the next level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: left"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>comic</category><category>fiction</category><category>free-to-read</category><category>media</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/demon/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 31 May 2021 16:08:52 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Fine Structure</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/fine-structure/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Fine Structure cover" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2021/fine-structure-cover.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another fabulously enjoyable science fiction adventure from qntm. Like their
other novels, it does a tremendous job of exploring the implications and
consequences of big science fiction concepts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this case, it's a story of human superheroes, whose powers derive from
beings-beyond-comprehension, from the high-dimensional multiverse, the
Structure, within which our paltry three-plus-one space-time is naught but an
embedded decal. Their struggles rewrite the fundamental physics of our
universe, to fashion it into an inescapable trap, denying humanity access to
advanced sciences, and to communion with the higher levels of the Structure.
Loved it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those like me with an epub fetish, you can buy &lt;em&gt;Fine Structure&lt;/em&gt; in many
formats, including Amazon links, EPUBs, or free-to-read online, &lt;a href="https://qntm.org/structure"&gt;at the
author's site&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: left"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>epub</category><category>free-to-read</category><category>media</category><category>novel</category><category>qntm</category><category>science-fiction</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/fine-structure/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 24 May 2021 16:55:26 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Ed</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/ed/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Ed cover" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2021/ed-by-qntm-cover.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by qntm, 2021&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It took me a few pages to shift gears to match the provocatively casual style,
but once I did, it quickly became an engrossing and endearing read.
The book collects a series of tiny but grand adventures, each riffing on one
of the titular Ed's fabulous new inventions or discoveries. Together these
form an arc which burns through combinations of high-concept SF ideas at an
unseemly rate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It reminded me of what I've fondly said about 200AD (the galaxy's greatest
comic), that somehow the superficiality of the medium allows
writers to experiment more wildly with form and content, throwing up a torrent
of creativity which, while sometimes uneven, generates moments of sheer
brilliance. I thought being a comic was an essential part of that formula. But
&lt;em&gt;Ed&lt;/em&gt; proves me wrong by achieving the same velocity of verve and vigor,
rendered in prose. A delight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Epilogue reminds me gleefully of
&lt;a href="https://worldbuilding.stackexchange.com/a/151964/13496"&gt;this Stack Overflow World-building answer&lt;/a&gt;
I gave a few months ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those like me with an epub fetish, you can buy &lt;em&gt;Ed&lt;/em&gt; in many formats,
including Amazon links, EPUBs, or free-to-read online,
&lt;a href="https://qntm.org/ed"&gt;at the author's site&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: left"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>epub</category><category>fiction</category><category>free-to-read</category><category>media</category><category>novella</category><category>qntm</category><category>science-fiction</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/ed/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 17 May 2021 15:48:53 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Ra</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/ra/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Ra cover" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2021/ra-by-qntm-cover.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I bought all four of &lt;a href="https://qntm.org/fiction"&gt;qntm's books&lt;/a&gt;
when I discovered the fantastic
&lt;a href="https://www.tartley.com/posts/there-is-no-antimemetics-division/"&gt;There is no Antimemetics Division&lt;/a&gt;.
I didn't really expect to like all of them, sight unseen, but was delighted to
support an emerging author who had contributed to the genius of SCP. But then
the books that arrived turned out to be bloody brilliant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This one tells a tale in which magic was discovered to be real in the 1970s,
becoming a new, arcane branch of physics. From there, it piles on the twists
and raises the stakes at an enthralling and dizzying rate, demanding the
reader to keep up through many exciting layered reveals and escalating changes
of perspective. Absolutely smashing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like &lt;em&gt;Antimemetics&lt;/em&gt;, it scores points with me for including some female heroes,
who surmount challenges through some striking strengths of character &amp;amp;
expertise, rather than simply being the best at applied violence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those like me with an epub fetish, you can buy &lt;em&gt;Ra&lt;/em&gt; in many formats,
including Amazon links, EPUBs, or free-to-read online,
&lt;a href="https://qntm.org/ra"&gt;at the author's site&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: left"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>epub</category><category>fiction</category><category>free-to-read</category><category>media</category><category>novel</category><category>qntm</category><category>science-fiction</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/ra/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 15 May 2021 17:22:32 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>There is no Antimemetics Division</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/there-is-no-antimemetics-division/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left; padding-bottom: 1em"&gt;
&lt;img alt="There is No Antimemetics Division cover" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2021/there-is-no-antimemetics-division-cover.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by qntm, 2020&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;img alt="spoilers" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/spoilers.svg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I first became aware of this book when I noticed that the good folks over
at &lt;a href="http://www.scpwiki.com/"&gt;The SCP Foundation&lt;/a&gt; have kept themselves busy in
the years since I last looked over their peerless and endlessly enthralling
wiki of dry and tantalizing protocols with which to "Secure, Contain, and
Protect" a catalog of creepy anomalous artifacts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the arcs to break the churning surface of that crowd-sourced
fictional milieu is that of the
&lt;a href="http://scp-wiki.wikidot.com/antimemetics-division-hub"&gt;Antimemetics Division&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;"An antimeme is an idea which, by its intrinsic nature, discourages people
from spreading it. Think of ideas that you wouldn't share - passwords,
taboos, shameful secrets.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Anomalous antimemes are another matter entirely. How do you contain
something you can't record, or remember? How do you fight an enemy when you
can never even know you're at war?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Welcome to the Antimemetics Division.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;No, this is not your first day."&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Intrigued, I started clicking around, and as is the way of SCP, discovered
many hours had passed. Shortly afterwards, I realized the arc has been
collected into this book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Occasional SCP entries, in the format we know and love, intertwine a short but
intense tale of memetic hazards, populated by a few of the Division's
finest - those rare individuals who can go from the standing start of a hint
that their memories can't be trusted, to a well-executed plan based upon
a stack of assumptions about what might be needed, and what might already have
been done that they can count upon, even though they no longer remember any of
it, without ever retaining any knowledge of their situation, or what they're up
against. I don't think I've ever been so impressed by the sheer depth of a
character's resourcefulness and initiative.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The journey does contain world-ending hellscapes, with some gore, which might
not be everyone's cup of tea. But it's short and somehow manages to stay light
in tone, so isn't emotionally arduous on that front.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Probably my favorite fiction of the year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those like me with an epub fetish,
you can buy &lt;em&gt;There is No Antimememtics Division&lt;/em&gt; in many formats,
including Amazon links, EPUBs, or free-to-read online,
&lt;a href="https://qntm.org/scp"&gt;at the author's site&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: left"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>epub</category><category>fiction</category><category>free-to-read</category><category>media</category><category>novel</category><category>qntm</category><category>science-fiction</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/there-is-no-antimemetics-division/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 10 May 2021 18:50:52 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Lena</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/lena/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Lena" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2021/lena.webp"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fabulous short story, &lt;a href="https://qntm.org/mmacevedo"&gt;Lena&lt;/a&gt; by qntm, riffs on
&lt;a href="http://www.scpwiki.com/"&gt;SCP&lt;/a&gt;'s idea of a work of fiction as a wiki entry.
But this is entirely standalone, not part of the SCP universe, and more
resembles a Wikipedia entry. Seems both genuinely scary and almost inevitable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The title stems from the image above, head-and-shoulders hurriedly torn from
the centerfold of a colleague's issue of Playboy in 1972, while searching for
an image to use in an image processing conference paper. From this, we can
infer the proper pronunciation is &lt;em&gt;Lenna&lt;/em&gt;, as in the name of the model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This image has been widely re-used in scientific journals for decades. It has
some objectively useful properties - good dynamic range, details and flat
regions, shading and texture. However, its viral popularity most probably stems
overwhelmingly from its racy nature, featuring an attractive woman, used in
male-dominated fields. This was in contrast to other common test images of
the time, derived from dull 1960s television standards work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The common long term use of the image was done without the knowledge or
permission of Playboy magazine - the copyright holder - or Lena herself. Over
the years they each became aware of it, and made their peace with it. By 2019,
though, Lena stated that the image, like her, ought to be retired.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: left"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>fiction</category><category>free-to-read</category><category>media</category><category>qntm</category><category>science-fiction</category><category>short</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/lena/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 09 May 2021 21:25:51 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>