<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Made out of meat (Posts about gig)</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://www.tartley.com/categories/gig.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2024 &lt;a href="mailto:tartley @ tartley dot com"&gt;Jonathan Hartley&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 04 Oct 2024 14:52:18 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Musicians : wake up!</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/musicians-wake-up/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;I left this as a comment &lt;a href="http://www.tbray.org/ongoing/When/201x/2010/01/21/On-Books"&gt;somewhere
else&lt;/a&gt;, in
response to someone complaining about how:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"...musicians are asked to just get over the fact that no one pays for
music... [it is] my hope that someday more people make the same
realization that unless people to help finance records, you'll never
get that fantastic song you can't stop listening to all summer."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hey there. I really disagree that the onus is on the rest of society to
solve all musicians' problems. People have been copying my work on the
internet for decades now. I'm a computer programmer. We're in exactly
the same boat as musicians - probably more so, and have been there for
longer. But we manage to get by.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some programmers attempt to stop copying of their work, but this is
rarely successful. Others take a different tack. We've had to adapt. We
acknowledge that our work will be routinely pirated on the internet, and
we adopt our business model accordingly. We have to make and sell
different sizes and types of tools than we were accustomed to making,
and sell them through different channels. We have had to find other ways
of charging for our work. My own company gives away our software for
free. We embrace piracy as inevitable, and use it as a promotional tool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is difficult. It is counter-intuitive, grounded as we all are in
the scarcity economy of the physical world. It requires us to change our
attitudes and outlook and behaviour. Sometimes we fail. We are still
figuring out the realities of our markets in a post-internet world.
But &lt;em&gt;goddammit&lt;/em&gt; we are trying and sometimes we try things and they work.
The software business is more diverse and thriving than it ever has been
- despite all our work being just as freely copyable (and freely copied)
as music.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The financial hardship that musicians are feeling has always been felt
by musicians. Copying music on the internet has not made this any worse
than it always was. This is simply the cost of choosing to be a
musician.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Musicians must adapt, just like programmers have. It saddens me to see
so few musicians even try. Is it really true that computer programmers
are more flexible and adaptable and imaginative than musicians. Who
would have thunk it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Embracing piracy as a promotional tool can allow bands to make more
money on live shows than they have ever made selling records, but still,
the majority of musicians sit around, complacent, thinking that the
responsibility lies on the rest of society, to put things back the way
they were before the internet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No. I for one refuse. Adapt or die - if you can't make it, someone else
will take your place. By definition, that someone will be more
adaptable, imaginative, risk-taking and dynamic. Isn't that supposed to
be what our creatives are good at?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People will doubtless think I'm being harsh - imposing my tyranny on
struggling musicians. But I'm not. When I say "adapt or die", I'm not
imposing my will. I'm merely reminding you of reality. If we were
talking about a guitarist who couldn't play the guitar, we would all
agree that they have put themselves in a bit of a paradoxical situation,
and that they must either adapt (learn to play) or die (stop being a
guitarist.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is how competition works. Competition might seem harsh, but it's
best for everyone in the long run. The poor guitarists are eventually
persuaded by market realities to stop being guitarists and try being
something else. The good guitarists get rewarded, and the standard of
music available to the world is increased as a result.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead of untalented guitarists, today we are talking about musicians
who would like to get paid, but who don't want to expend any energy on
figuring out how they will get paid. Can you see the paradoxical
situation they have put themselves in? This attitude is entirely
understandable and human - I also would enjoy locking myself in my room
and making beautiful computer programs which nobody else need ever see.
But if I expect to get paid for making computer programs, then I must
interface with the reality of the world around me. It's no use me simply
wishing that High St stores will start selling my software in
shrinkwrapped boxes again - those days are long gone. Instead, I must
figure out what programs people want, and produce them in a timely
manner at high quality, promote them somehow, and figure out my angle on
how I'm going to get people to pay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is not too much for us to ask musicians to also have to conform to
reality like this. If they want to make money, and the means of making
money from music are changing, then they will have to expend a little
energy figuring out how they are going to get people to pay. If they
don't want to think about that at all, then fine, they won't get paid.
Adapt or die, we'll all be better off for it.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>geek</category><category>gig</category><category>imho</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/musicians-wake-up/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 22 Jan 2010 15:43:24 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Adventures of Prince Achmed (1926) at Latitude</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/latitude/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.latitudefestival.co.uk" title="Latitude Festival"&gt;&lt;img alt="Latitude Festival" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2007/07/latitude.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's summertime again, even in sodden old England, and that means it's
festival season. True to its image as one of the newer and smaller
festivals in the UK, Latitude had a good-natured crowd, diverse music -
albeit without many big-name bands, was laid-back and eclectic, and not
too muddy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.tartley.com/files/2007/07/prince-achmed.jpg" title="Prince Achmed"&gt;&lt;img alt="Prince Achmed" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2007/07/prince-achmed.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The defining highlight for me was a showing of &lt;em&gt;The Adventures of
Prince Achmed&lt;/em&gt; (1926) (&lt;a href="http://imdb.com/title/tt0015532/"&gt;IMDB&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Adventures_of_Prince_Achmed"&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;),
a beautiful rendition of tales from Arabian Nights, using stop-motion
shadow-puppetry, accompanied by a haunting live musical soundtrack by &lt;a href="http://www.myspace.com/littlesparta"&gt;Little
Sparta&lt;/a&gt;. I've wanted to see the movie for
ages - it is the oldest surviving feature-length animation, and was brought
about by the dedication of one woman, &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lotte_Reiniger,"&gt;Lotte
Reiniger&lt;/a&gt; who single-handedly
constructed all the cutouts in the movie using nothing more than scissors, and
then animated them all by hand.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>animation</category><category>gig</category><category>media</category><category>movie</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/latitude/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 16 Jul 2007 15:48:46 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>