<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Made out of meat (Posts about history)</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://www.tartley.com/categories/history.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2023 &lt;a href="mailto:tartley @ the domain tartley dot com"&gt;Jonathan Hartley&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 23 Aug 2023 18:34:55 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Self-Calm</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/self-calm/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Self Calm cover" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2021/self-calm-cover.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Chris DeLeon (2018)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Roman Emperor Marcus Auralias' notes, traditionally titled &lt;em&gt;Meditations&lt;/em&gt;,
are a foundational text for practical Stoicism. They comprise a multitude of
observations and recommendations, grouped into sections such as "Keeping
thoughts tranquil", and "Cooperation, collaboration and contribution". They
offer advice for living a contented life, with less regret, sorrow, anger and
fear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several translations exist, themselves dated from through the ages. This book
combines them, to synthesize a text which doesn't hew as precisely to the
original as a straight translation might, but is instead intended to have the
most relevance to modern ears.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Confession: It's taken me &lt;em&gt;months&lt;/em&gt; to get through it. Partly this is because
I've allowed myself to be distracted by more gaudy and immediate books along
the way. Partly it's because I found the best way to read this was &lt;em&gt;slowly&lt;/em&gt;.
Practically every paragraph is worth reflecting upon, to consider how it
applies to my own life, and ponder what practical, specific next steps are
implied.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I had to criticize, it would only be the superficial wrinkle that there's
a lot of repetition, such as hundreds of suggestions to not fear death.
Apparently the original documents were accumulated over decades of Auralias'
life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Genuinely life changing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can get the epub for free from
&lt;a href="https://gumroad.com/l/self-calm"&gt;the author's gumroad page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: left"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>history</category><category>media</category><category>non-fiction</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/self-calm/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 03 Jun 2021 12:38:57 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>12 Books That Changed The World</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/12-books-that-changed-the-world/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="12 Books That Changed The World" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2007/06/12books-that-changed-the-world.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Melvyn Bragg (2006)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A brilliant assembly of potted snippets of history, ideal for someone
like myself with scarcely a glimmer of an education. By cunning omission
of the definite article, Bragg gets to talk not just about 12 important
books, but is able to manipulate the list such that it is all about 12
&lt;em&gt;British&lt;/em&gt; books, a move I heartily approve of. Apparently written to
accompany some television series, I neither knew nor cared. For the
record, his selection is below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: both"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Principia Mathematica&lt;/em&gt; by Isaac Newton, 1687. "Will always have a
    pre-eminance above all the other works of human genius."&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Married Love&lt;/em&gt; by Marie Stopes, 1918. Transformed the married lives
    of a whole generation, furthering the rights of women, and making it
    possible to broach subjects that had been entirely taboo.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Magna Carta&lt;/em&gt; by Members of the English ruling classes, 1215. The
    fundamental origins of the English constitution, setting up a
    balance of powers which forms the basis and language for many others
    since, including America and India.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Rule Book of Association Football&lt;/em&gt; by a group of former English
    public school men. Codifying the most popular game on the planet.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;On the Origin of Species&lt;/em&gt; by Charles Darwin, 1859. The greatest and
    most far-reaching scientific theory yet produced.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;On the Abolition of the Slave Trade&lt;/em&gt; an oration by William
    Wilberforce in Parliament, 1789. This was published immediately
    after his oration in parliament, forming a cornerstone of the
    anti-slave trade movement, and eventually leading to the abolition
    of the slave trade just days before Wilberforce's death, a move
    that, in subsequent decades, was emulated by nations all over the
    world.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;A Vindication of the Rights of Women&lt;/em&gt; by Mary
    Wollsenstonecraft, 1792. The first great feminine thesis, coming at
    a time when the world sorely needed it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Experimental Researches in Electricity&lt;/em&gt; by Michael Faraday,
    1839-55. A study in dedication and impartial perseverance, resulting
    in an astonishing number of discoveries which now affect the
    everyday lives of billions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Patent Specification for Arkwright's Spinning Machine&lt;/em&gt; by Richard
    Arkwright, 1769. Trailblazer for a commerce-fuelled industrial
    revolution that shows no signs of slowing down in its transformation
    of the world.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;The King James Bible&lt;/em&gt; by fifty-four scholars appointed by the
    King, 1611. A beautiful construction that has contributed more
    phrases and expressions to the English language than any other
    source.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;An Inquiry into the Nature and Causes of the Wealth of Nations&lt;/em&gt; by
    Adam Smith, 1776. Transformed views of how wealth was to be measured
    and generated, practically inventing capitalism along the way.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;The First Folio&lt;/em&gt; by William Shakespeare, 1623. No other work of
    fiction, religious texts aside, can match the cultural influence and
    endearing effect on our language that this body of work has had.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rating:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;9/10 if you know nothing, like what I do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;5/10 if you've already read all the entries in his list, like I haven't.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>culture</category><category>history</category><category>media</category><category>non-fiction</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/12-books-that-changed-the-world/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 12 Jun 2007 13:14:17 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>A Short History Of Nearly Everything</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/a-short-history-of-nearly-everything/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2007/02/short-history-of-nearly-everything.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Bill Bryson (2003)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bryson's unassuming style make this a joy to read - welcoming,
continually interesting, and with warm and often laugh-out-loud humour
firmly woven through almost every paragraph.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book's only failing is perhaps in attempting to do too much - in
less capable hands, its ambitious remit would cause it to sprawl far
beyond the extent of this middling-sized tome. But Bryson deftly manages
to give an overview of not just the most prominent fields in science,
but their history, and most delightfully, the eccentricities of their
practitioners to boot. In performing such a feat he is obliged to omit a
great deal, and is only able to skim nuggets of trivia from the surface
of each topic. However, his sure, deliberate style, like an educational
Sunday afternoon sightseeing stroll, guides us deftly to appreciate each
notable landmark upon the way, and then he unobtrusively ushers us
onward, to the next worthy vista.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Heartily recommended, for its perspective on the human background to how
we know what we know, and the sheer jolliness with which it is
presented.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rating: 8/10&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: both"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>history</category><category>media</category><category>non-fiction</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/a-short-history-of-nearly-everything/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Feb 2007 06:12:36 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>