<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>tartley.com (Posts about imho)</title><link>https://tartley.com/</link><description>In my humble opinion.</description><atom:link href="https://www.tartley.com/categories/imho.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2022 &lt;a href="mailto:tartley @ the domain tartley dot com"&gt;Jonathan Hartley&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 14 Jan 2022 21:16:37 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>I am such a child</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/i-am-such-a-child/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dear Julio,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many thanks for considering me for this opportunity. I feel as though my
skills are a good match for the position, and would like you to consider
my application.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I feel as though this is the start of a new phase in life for me, as
though I have really rounded a corner. I have not used a computer, but
my nephew says he will meet me tomorrow afternoon to teach me how to do
it. Also, my therapist says that my bouts of incoherent rage will
continue to diminish, so that will be good in my new job. My probation
for stealing from my previous employer is almost up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am high, but I can absolutely have this under control and be
completely sober by Monday, when I trust you will call me at your
earliest convenience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Best regards,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jonathan Hartley&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;-------- Original Message --------&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Subject:   offer number 078
  Date:      Fri, 9 Jul 2010 17:28:46 -0500
  From:      &lt;a href="mailto:tartley@tartley.com"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  To:        &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My name is Julio YEPES, I am a hiring manager with ...&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>imho</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/i-am-such-a-child/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 10 Jul 2010 18:36:20 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Great Resolver IDE Anecdote</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/the-great-resolver-ide-anecdote/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Found myself telling this story yet again, so I figured I should just
post it here and start linking to it, rather than remembering, retyping
and re-embellishing it every time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ever since we started at &lt;a href="http://www.resolversystems.com/"&gt;Resolver&lt;/a&gt;,
developers have been free to choose their own IDE (Integrated
Development Environment, although some of the ones I'm going to talk
about aren't so integrated, so I guess you should just read 'IDE' herein
to mean 'development environment').&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like herding cats, this of course resulted in everyone choosing a
different IDE. At one peak, we had fourteen people, and about ten
different IDEs. Sigh. To our incredulity though, this worked fine, and
everyone was happy. So far, so good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We pair program, so we see a lot of each other's IDEs. In fact, we end
up learning them all pretty thoroughly. Spending eight hours a day,
every day, using someone else's IDE, with a bona-fide expert in that IDE
sitting in your lap, guiding you through it, will tend to do that. After
a few months, we all knew every IDE out there back-to-front. An example
of how pairing spreads knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every so often, someone would change their mind about their chosen IDE.
Having been educated about the alternatives, they would decide to
switch. This was also fine, and everyone continued to be happy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, after a few months of this, an interesting thing happened.
Gradually, one by one, twelve of our fourteen people each decided, of
their own accord, to switch to using either Vi or Emacs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I regard this of an example of pairing not just spreading knowledge, but
spreading &lt;em&gt;enlightenment&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They each had realised that although these hallowed text editors didn't
have some of the more advanced features they'd come to expect from an
IDE, such as auto-completion or 'go to definition', they were flexible
and powerful enough that one could add such features yourself. To do so
is a rite of passage for an experienced programmer, akin to Luke
building his own lightsaber - so that it's customized to his precise
needs, and he understands each nuance of its behaviour.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More than that, all the conveniences of a traditional IDE made it very
convenient to do only what the authors of the IDE had envisaged. To do
anything else was made very difficult. If you wished to use a different
compiler, or write in a different language than those prescribed by your
IDE vendor, you were out of luck, and would have to learn an entirely
different IDE to do that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;"We shape our tools and afterwards our tools shape us."&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Marshall McLuhan ('The media is the message' guy)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On one project, or two, this might seem a trivial restriction. Extended
over the course of a lifetime, the conveniences shields a developer from
learning anything other than how to drive an IDE, and the restrictions
become blinkers, crippling their scope and abilities. The IDE is a
cage... for your &lt;em&gt;mind&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2010/05/matrix_morpheus_red_blue_pill.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The outliers are worth noting: We still use Visual Studio on rare
occasions, for the lovely built-in GUI designer. The irrepressible
Michael Foord loves Wing, and stuck with that. Will Reade, our tame
brainiac, stuck with transparent simplicity of the lightweight but
surprisingly useful TextPad. Go figure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update&lt;/strong&gt;: The coda to the outliers is also interesting. Nowadays we're
embedded in a huge mission to free our codebase from embedded win32
controls, so that we might have a chance of running under Mono, and
hence on other platforms. It would be nice if we could escape Windows
Forms altogether - I understand WPF would let us display our GUI on the
web. Writing this post makes me wonder - if we hadn't been using Visual
Studio's convenient GUI designer all along, is it remotely possible that
we might have considered our choice of GUI layer more thoroughly? If we
hadn't been entranced by the "obviously right" convenience of the Visual
Studio GUI designer, might our minds have been free enough to have made
this decision right the first time around?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>imho</category><category>software</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/the-great-resolver-ide-anecdote/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 04 May 2010 17:56:47 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Musicians : wake up!</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/musicians-wake-up/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;I left this as a comment &lt;a href="http://www.tbray.org/ongoing/When/201x/2010/01/21/On-Books"&gt;somewhere
else&lt;/a&gt;, in
response to someone complaining about how:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"...musicians are asked to just get over the fact that no one pays for
music... [it is] my hope that someday more people make the same
realization that unless people to help finance records, you'll never
get that fantastic song you can't stop listening to all summer."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hey there. I really disagree that the onus is on the rest of society to
solve all musicians' problems. People have been copying my work on the
internet for decades now. I'm a computer programmer. We're in exactly
the same boat as musicians - probably more so, and have been there for
longer. But we manage to get by.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some programmers attempt to stop copying of their work, but this is
rarely successful. Others take a different tack. We've had to adapt. We
acknowledge that our work will be routinely pirated on the internet, and
we adopt our business model accordingly. We have to make and sell
different sizes and types of tools than we were accustomed to making,
and sell them through different channels. We have had to find other ways
of charging for our work. My own company gives away our software for
free. We embrace piracy as inevitable, and use it as a promotional tool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is difficult. It is counter-intuitive, grounded as we all are in
the scarcity economy of the physical world. It requires us to change our
attitudes and outlook and behaviour. Sometimes we fail. We are still
figuring out the realities of our markets in a post-internet world.
But &lt;em&gt;goddammit&lt;/em&gt; we are trying and sometimes we try things and they work.
The software business is more diverse and thriving than it ever has been
- despite all our work being just as freely copyable (and freely copied)
as music.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The financial hardship that musicians are feeling has always been felt
by musicians. Copying music on the internet has not made this any worse
than it always was. This is simply the cost of choosing to be a
musician.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Musicians must adapt, just like programmers have. It saddens me to see
so few musicians even try. Is it really true that computer programmers
are more flexible and adaptable and imaginative than musicians. Who
would have thunk it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Embracing piracy as a promotional tool can allow bands to make more
money on live shows than they have ever made selling records, but still,
the majority of musicians sit around, complacent, thinking that the
responsibility lies on the rest of society, to put things back the way
they were before the internet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No. I for one refuse. Adapt or die - if you can't make it, someone else
will take your place. By definition, that someone will be more
adaptable, imaginative, risk-taking and dynamic. Isn't that supposed to
be what our creatives are good at?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People will doubtless think I'm being harsh - imposing my tyranny on
struggling musicians. But I'm not. When I say "adapt or die", I'm not
imposing my will. I'm merely reminding you of reality. If we were
talking about a guitarist who couldn't play the guitar, we would all
agree that they have put themselves in a bit of a paradoxical situation,
and that they must either adapt (learn to play) or die (stop being a
guitarist.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is how competition works. Competition might seem harsh, but it's
best for everyone in the long run. The poor guitarists are eventually
persuaded by market realities to stop being guitarists and try being
something else. The good guitarists get rewarded, and the standard of
music available to the world is increased as a result.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead of untalented guitarists, today we are talking about musicians
who would like to get paid, but who don't want to expend any energy on
figuring out how they will get paid. Can you see the paradoxical
situation they have put themselves in? This attitude is entirely
understandable and human - I also would enjoy locking myself in my room
and making beautiful computer programs which nobody else need ever see.
But if I expect to get paid for making computer programs, then I must
interface with the reality of the world around me. It's no use me simply
wishing that High St stores will start selling my software in
shrinkwrapped boxes again - those days are long gone. Instead, I must
figure out what programs people want, and produce them in a timely
manner at high quality, promote them somehow, and figure out my angle on
how I'm going to get people to pay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is not too much for us to ask musicians to also have to conform to
reality like this. If they want to make money, and the means of making
money from music are changing, then they will have to expend a little
energy figuring out how they are going to get people to pay. If they
don't want to think about that at all, then fine, they won't get paid.
Adapt or die, we'll all be better off for it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>geek</category><category>gig</category><category>imho</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/musicians-wake-up/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 22 Jan 2010 15:43:24 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The ACM is pissing in the well</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/the-acm-is-pissing-in-the-well/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;An open letter I have sent to the ACM.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have recently been considering joining the ACM, as the most eminent
international professional body of software engineers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On reflection I have decided not to join, because of two actions by the
Association in recent weeks that appear strongly contrary to the best
interests of its members, and indeed contrary to the interests of all
software engineers and scholars of every discipline.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am referring, firstly, to the shameful take-down requests issued to
Ke-Sen Huang, and subsequent conditions imposed over his meticulously
assembled pages of links to SIGGRAPH and other academic computer
graphics papers.
&lt;a href="http://kesen.huang.googlepages.com"&gt;http://kesen.huang.googlepages.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second act is the recent official comment from the ACM on the White
House's public feedback to expanding open access to scientific papers.
This comment is to the effect that the ACM resists the move towards
making scientific papers available to all.
&lt;a href="http://blog.ostp.gov/2009/12/10/policy-forum-on-public-access-to-federally-funded-research-implementation/comment-page-3/#comments"&gt;http://blog.ostp.gov/2009/12/10/policy-forum-on-public-access-to-federally-funded-research-implementation/comment-page-3/#comments&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both these actions bore the signature of the ACM's Bernard Rous, who has
the unbelievable gall to suggest he opposes the creation of a repository
of academic papers, because it would undermine the ACM's revenue from
keeping such papers behind a paywall, and that this is a legitimate
interest which must be 'balanced with' the interest of the ACM members
desiring access to those papers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr Rous perhaps needs reminding that the ACM's has *no such*
legitimate interest here. The Association's entire existence is soley
contingent upon the benefit that it provides to its members. These
actions seem to me to be in flagrant violation of the ACM's own Code of
Ethics (&lt;a href="http://www.acm.org/about/code-of-ethics"&gt;http://www.acm.org/about/code-of-ethics&lt;/a&gt;) and worse, it seems to
be contrary to the ACM's entire charter and purpose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have no doubt the ACM performs many valuable services which incur
substantial costs, and these costs need to be offset by exploring
methods of generating revenue. But this is not an acceptable method. It
costs nothing to make these papers available online - and the ACM has no
business opposing the establishment of free learning resources that
would compete with its own offerings. On the contrary, the ACM is not a
profit-making organisation. Its charter to promote learning and
education amongst its members, and this can only be best served by
promoting and facilitating the free and open access to academic papers
such as these.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It seems clear to me that if the ACM does not effect an immediate and
total reversal of its policy on these matters, then the Association has
changed from the illustrious body it once was, into a force for ill,
pissing in the well of knowledge, to be actively opposed by
professional, moral software engineers everywhere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The background to this issue is most clearly expressed here:
&lt;a href="http://www.realtimerendering.com/blog/us-gov-requests-feedback-on-open-access-acm-gets-it-wrong-again/"&gt;http://www.realtimerendering.com/blog/us-gov-requests-feedback-on-open-access-acm-gets-it-wrong-again/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would urge others to boycott any further membership payments to the
ACM until this is satisfactorily resolved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sincerely,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jonathan Hartley&lt;br&gt;
Software Engineer&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>geek</category><category>imho</category><category>software</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/the-acm-is-pissing-in-the-well/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 18 Dec 2009 21:45:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Result of MP visit - I suck</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/result-of-mp-visit-i-suck/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;So earlier tonight I turned up at the monthly 'surgery' of my MP, Frank
Dobson (Labour), to present my objections to the Digital Economy Bill.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the benefit of others also going to tackle Mr Dobson on this issue,
(and anyone going to see some other MP) here's a quick write up of my
experiences:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I arrived up half an hour before it started, and there were about eight
parties ahead of me in line. My turn came half an hour after they kicked
off. I had hoped to present my argument pretty much as I laid it out in
my previous blog post. However, sadly I pretty much comprehensively
failed to get my point across.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The 'I am not a spittle-flecked loon' introduction&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As planned, I started out by saying that I fully support copyright law,
and of the importance of finding ways to ensure that artists get
renumerated for their work. The portions of the bill which describe the
pursuit of illegal downloaders therefore have laudable and important
goals, however I think that the costs and problems associated with
preventing illegal downloads like this are substantial, and actually
make this section of the bill counter-productive. Mr Dobson was an
affable gent, and listened attentively to what I had to say.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Disconnection needlessly punishes more innocent people than guilty
ones&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first objection I wanted to raise, because it seems to me to be the
most clear-cut, is that the bill suggests disconnection from the
internet for persistent downloaders. I pointed out that since most
internet connections are shared between several people (families and
housemates) disconnecting a single illegal downloader would also
unfairly affect all the people who share their connection. Mr Dobson's
opinion was that it would rarely come to actual disconnection - the
intention of the Bill is very much that disconnection would be a
rarely-used last resort. The earlier provisions in the bill (warning
offenders for their first 'two strikes') are intended to stop almost
everyone from illegally downloading, without any need for actual
disconnections to take place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obviously I regard that as a grave misjudgement. But I had a lot of
ground to cover, so I left this issue at that. I still feel that even if
disconnection were only applied to a small number of people (which seems
unlikely, from my perspective), it is still true that this would affect
more innocents than guilty parties. There is no reason not to prefer
more conventional punitive measures over disconnection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Impossibility of distinguishing guilt from innocence&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I moved onto my second point: When monitoring downloads, it is
impossible to distinguish between guilt and innocence. If I download a
song I own, from my home to my office, this behaviour may currently be
legally murky, but it is clearly morally justifiable. To any external
observer, this looks indistinguishable from illegal download. An
observer cannot tell whether a particular download is illegal or not
just by looking at the bits going down the wire - it requires more
context than that. It requires the observer to know which CDs I have
bought, and to what use I intend to put the proceeds (is it subject to
fair use exemptions, etc?) Therefore, along with many illegal
downloaders, the system proposed in the bill will also catch many
innocent people in its net.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These innocents can appeal - there is a procedure in the bill for this -
however they will find it impossible to demonstrate their innocence. If
I have bought a CD and ripped it to my computer (which I have done with
all my CDs, many years ago) then when I am accused of illegally
downloading it, how am I supposed to demonstrate that I once bought that
CD?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr Dobson listened with patience and good humour to this. However, it
was clear from his responses that while he is a capable man who is
working hard and with the best of intentions, the scenario I outlined
was fairly foreign to his experience. He suggested that the bill is not
aimed at catching people like me who are doing nothing wrong. It is
aimed at people who are making a dishonest living by massive downloads
which they are somehow making money from. I don't believe that any such
people actually exist, never mind that the bill is aimed at them: The
wording of the bill clearly encompasses individuals downloading music
for their own listening pleasure, and deliberately so, but I did not go
into this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr Dobson felt that the appeals process would be sufficient for anyone
such as my self to protest their innocence. I totally failed to
communicate that demonstrating my innocence during such an appeals
process would be very difficult. When I reiterated that I could not, for
example, produce the receipts to all the music and movies I have ever
bought in my entire lifetime, Mr Dobson reiterated that the bill was not
aimed at innocent people like me, it would only be applied to illegal
downloaders. I again said I don't see how the ISPs can distinguish
between the two - for example I cannot produce the receipts nor the CDs
that my music came from - I ripped them in 1998, and have since
discarded them all. Mr Dobson said that perhaps &lt;em&gt;when&lt;/em&gt; the bill become
law (my emphasis), people will be obliged to keep their CDs "in a
plastic bag in the garage", in preparation for just such a scenario. I
pointed out that all of my music for the last few years has been
purchased online - so never came on any CDs to begin with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr Dobson didn't seem receptive to this argument. He was still in good
spirits at this point, however, I totally failed to persuade him that
difficulty in distinguishing between guilty and innocent downloaders was
even a realistic possibility, never mind that it would actually be a
serious problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had hoped to move on from this point to demonstrate that this
presumption of guilt that the bill contains will have a severe chilling
effect on people's legitimate and morally justifiable uses of the
internet, and this will hamper the development of business models, which
will be presumptively quashed before ever getting a chance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, Mr Dobson suggested that I should send him the remainder of my
points to him in a letter. I asked him if I could just spend 30 seconds
skipping through the executive summary of the remainder of my argument,
since I felt there was a logical chain of inferences to follow, which
demonstrated some real problems with the bill. He suggested that I write
it to him in a letter instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Probable ten or fifteen minutes had elapsed. We exchanged cordial
pleasantries and headed out for a lovely curry down the street with my
awesome wife.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>geek</category><category>imho</category><category>journal</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/result-of-mp-visit-i-suck/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 05 Dec 2009 05:23:09 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>My objections to the Digital Economy Bill</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/my-objections-to-the-digital-economy-bill/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is pretty much a riff on what I posted yesterday, only this is my
draft for how I intend to present it to my MP tomorrow. I have no idea
how much time I'll have, nor how receptive he'll be. This may all be a
big waste of time, but just in case, this is my plan, such as it is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you think any part of this is idiotic, or that I've misunderstood how
the relevant bits of the Bill work, or that I'm belabouring some points
at the expense of other, more important ones, then I'd really love to
hear about it. The last thing I want is for some stupid part of my
argument to undermine the other parts of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Digital Economy Bill&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200910/ldbills/001/10001.i-ii.html"&gt;http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/ld200910/ldbills/001/10001.i-ii.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want to clarify at the outset that I absolutely support the importance
of copyright law, its enforcement, and give my full support to the
expectation of artists to be remunerated in a market-driven manner. I do
not want the following arguments to be confused with those which suggest
that copyright should be abolished, or everything online should be
free.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(This bit is my attempt to establish some credibility and rapport. In
reality, I think copyright, although sound in principle, is sorely in
need of substantial revision, namely it should be much shorter in
duration, should have larger and more explicit exceptions, and should
require pro-active registering and renewal by the rights holder. But
those concerns are orthogonal to the Digital Economy Bill in its current
form, and raising them here would only confuse the issue.)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a computer programmer, I am directly affected by illegal downloads.
Almost everything I have created professionally has subsequently been
available online for illegal download - affecting my own income and the
financial viability of my employers, such as my current small technology
start-up. &lt;em&gt;(This is not entirely true - some military projects I have
worked on have not suffered any piracy, due to having, shall we say,
extravagant hardware requirements)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, even with that background, I still have strong objections to
the sections of the bill 4 through 17, which attempt to redress the harm
done to the creative industries by the elimination of illegal
downloading.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I believe this pursuit of illegal downloaders comes with problems that
are so profound as to make this portion of the bill counter-productive -
and I believe that a superior alternative course of action does exist,
that would be of substantially more benefit to artists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problems as I perceive them are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. Disconnection affects many innocents.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regarding the Obligations to Limit Access described in section 11.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Almost every internet connection is used by more than one person. For
example family members, or independent parties in a shared house.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Disconnection of persistent illegal downloaders will therefore impact
all these other users of the shared connection. The innocent users
disconnected by this legislation will greatly outnumber the illegal
downloaders being targeted!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This similarly also applies to the other, lesser remedies described by
section 11, of affecting service speed or access to particular
materials.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is flagrantly unfair - a whole household of innocent people are
being punished because of the actions of one guilty person.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Infringing downloads may not even have originated from a resident of the
house. They could easily have been made a dinner guest - very possibly
without the resident's knowledge, and yet they are to be collectively
punished for it. Are hosts expected to prevent this by searching every
guest to their house, demanding guests hand over their phones and other
devices?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This idea is equally problematic when considering publicly available
internet connections, such as at libraries, airports, coffee-shops, etc.
Are they to be disconnected when one of their customers infringes?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My conclusion: Disconnection and the other remedies described in section
11 are not, under any circumstances, appropriate courses of action, even
for the most egregious offenders, and more conventional remedies should
be considered instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. Impossibility of distinguishing guilt from innocence&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several times a week, I routinely download many dozens of online media
from my home collection, to wherever I happen to be at the time - the
office, at a conference, travelling overseas. These are on the whole
media I have previously bought - music or movies or computer programs or
games. I have ripped these legally purchased items to my computer
precisely so that I would have the freedom to move them geographically,
and to format-shift them from one device to another.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To any external observer, these downloads are indistinguishable from an
illegal download. Copying of the exact same songs is involved in each
case. The external observer cannot know that I have already bought the
music or movie or whatever in question.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I were accused of illegal downloading under this law, which I
apparently would be on a very regular basis, then would have no way of
defending myself against these false accusations. I cannot produce proof
of purchase for all of the media I have purchased over my whole
lifetime.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If it came down to producing the physical media as evidence, such as CDs
my songs came on, then of course many of my songs were purchased online,
and the CDs I bought years ago were discarded as soon as I had ripped
them, in celebration of my freedom from the constraints of physical
media.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Similarly, my accuser, upon whom I believe the onus of proof should lie,
cannot prove the negative (that I never bought the media in question.)
So it is impossible to distinguish the guilty from the innocent, and&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. Chilling effect&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The presumption of guilt inherent in the Bill will clearly have a
chilling effect on my personal use of the internet as described above.
The &lt;em&gt;raison d'Ãªtre&lt;/em&gt; of the internet is to facilitate the copying of
information from one place to another, and yet my perfectly innocuous
desire to use it for exactly that is, in this instance, prevented for
fear of me being tarred with the same brush as illegal downloaders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If this were the full extent of the chilling effect that the bill will
have, then it is arguable that this is a regrettable but acceptable
collateral damage in the struggle to recompense artists. However, this
is not the only action that is chilled by the Bill's presumption of
guilt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;TODO, this section is weak, and represents what I think is the most
important problem. At the very least, more compelling examples are
needed here&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Artists exchanging material while collaborating on a project, or or
someone downloading music that they themselves wrote, or business model
that involves copying media from one place to another, all would be
under risk from invoking the penalty of 'illegal downloads', and will be
prevented from occurring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Personal freedoms and business models of both the present and the future
will be inhibited by the presumption of guilt that the pursuit of
file-sharers requires.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is, to my mind, the most serious of all the problems with the
Bill's pursuit of illegal downloaders. Instead of stimulating the
digital economy, these measures seem to me to stifle it, by pandering to
the wishes of existing special interests, at the expense of personal
freedoms and the emerging business models of the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4. No provision to clarify the legality of innocent use&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is disappointing that the bill does not take the opportunity to make
actions which are both common and morally justifiable clearly and
explicitly legal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am thinking here of actions such as my space-shifting of the files I
own, as described above, and of format-shifting between different
devices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These actions do not in any way represent a valid 'lost sale', and have
absolutely no negative effect on the content industry's business, other
than countering unreasonable attempts to force consumers to purchase the
same media several times over.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Removing the uncertainty about these actions would free individuals from
the lurking threat of frivolous prosecution over harmless activities,
and would foster innovation by giving business some guidelines about
exactly what is allowed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5. Intrusive state monitoring of everyone's online actions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I strongly object to the notion of the ISPs, acting as representatives
of the State, monitoring every single action that I and my family and my
friends carry out online. It is ripe for abuse, for the information
falling into the wrong hands, and for leaving me under suspicion due to
clerical or other errors during the collection or storage of the data.
It is absolutely unacceptable to me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;6. Lack of substantive evidence that artists income has really
dropped&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As stated initially, the goal of ensuring artists are suitably
remunerated for their creations is a laudable one, that I fully support.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Crucially though, the purported losses incurred by the music and movie
industries are commonly derived from flawed studies, directly funded by
the industries in question, and frequently make fundamental mistakes
such as equating every download made with a lost sale. More substantive
information than this is required about the size of the problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Indeed, some figures show that the music industry has in fact grown very
healthily in the last few years. For example, these figures compiled and
published by The Times on 12th November 2009, based on the BPI's own
data:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://labs.timesonline.co.uk/blog/2009/11/12/do-music-artists-do-better-in-a-world-with-illegal-file-sharing/"&gt;http://labs.timesonline.co.uk/blog/2009/11/12/do-music-artists-do-better-in-a-world-with-illegal-file-sharing/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This suggests that since 2004, recorded music incomes in the UK have
fallen by some £326M. Whether this is due to illegal downloading is not
known - presumably it is partly due to that, and partly due to other
factors, such as the music industry putting out fewer records in recent
years. However, the same figures also show that over the same period,
income from live music and merchandising have risen by the larger amount
of £373M. The industry as a whole is around £47M better off, and as a
bonus, the proportion of this income which is paid directly to artists
has risen dramatically, since artists make more money from live shows
than from recorded music sales.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This fits with my own personal experience - free downloads act as a
tremendous promotional boost for bands. I have many friends who are able
to try out far more music as a result of its availability online, and as
a result are far more active in attending live music events, often of
bands they would not otherwise have heard of, had they not discovered
them online.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If this is true, then free downloads cause artists to lose money via
recorded music, but also to gain more in recompense through other
channels. In this case, do we really need heavy-handed legislation to
protect their interests, if the legislation in question comes with all
the other costs described here? If artists really are earning more than
they were five years ago, do we need to introduce the chilling effects
this bill will cause on the rest of the economy in order to try and help
them out? What if the pursuit of illegal downloaders means that revenues
in live music then drops back to their previous lower levels? Artists
will have actually been financially hurt by this bill. This needs to be
understood before taking such drastic actions as the bill proposes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;7. One alternative&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TODO: Lay out the "central pool to remunerate artists in proportion to
their number of downloads" idea, merely to make it clear that there are
alternatives courses of action which could be used to tackle this
situation, which seem to come with real incentives to stimulate the
digital and creative economies, and with smaller, more soluble problems
than Digital Economy Bill in its current form.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>geek</category><category>imho</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/my-objections-to-the-digital-economy-bill/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 04 Dec 2009 06:32:58 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>[SOLVED]UK Digital Economy Bill</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/solveduk-digital-economy-bill/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;So my splendid talented intelligent handsome friend Robert (who is also
my boss, of sorts) today shared this smashing post:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://gizmodo.com/5417318/my-6247-royalty-statement-how-major-labels-cook-the-books-with-digital-downloads"&gt;My \$62.47 Royalty Statement: How Major Labels Cook the Books with
Digital
Downloads&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;About one aspect of how artists get ripped off by the labels. It's not
required reading, but you can if you like. I'll wait.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hey. So it made me realise that a very possible fix to the dreadful
abuse of artists by the labels is possible. Even better, the solution to
this appalling situation is also the solution to the dire problems with
the UK's Digital Economy Bill.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So the UK govt. are debating a new bill, part of which introduces
measures to ruthlessly pursue illegal downloaders. There are some
problems with this, namely that:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;someone (probably the ISPs) will have to monitor what everyone
    downloads, and report people downloading anything that trips their
    filters for 'copyrighted work'. Understandably, they don't want to
    do this.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It will cost lots to implement - currently estimated at 100
    million, but of course the ensuing arms race with encrypted
    downloads will inflate that. Has anyone compared this with the
    &lt;em&gt;actual&lt;/em&gt; economic losses that it is aiming to fix? (not just the
    inflated ones self-reported by those with most to gain.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is literally impossible to automatically detect breach of
    copyright accurately - it can't be done just by looking at the bits.
    There will be lots of false positives and false negatives.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It will be easy to get around, using encryption or similar
    technologies to evade detection. It will not fix the problem it aims
    to fix.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It requires representatives of the state to intrusively monitor
    every single thing we do online.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The false positives will target and punish many innocent people,
    who have no way to demonstrate their innocence.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Perhaps worst of all, its presumption of guilt will have a chilling
    effect on many legal and morally justifiable uses of the internet,
    including business models of the present and the future.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They are talking about disconnection from the internet as a
    potential punitive measure for persistent downloaders. Most internet
    connections are shared by several people, and many of us use each
    other's connections all the time. Disconnecting one person for
    something that someone else downloaded is flagrantly wrong, and
    without wishing to be melodramatic, collective punishment like this
    is, strictly speaking, in breach of article 33 of the Geneva
    Convention. Plus it makes free wi-fi impossible to provide. Are we
    meant to be &lt;em&gt;destroying&lt;/em&gt; the digital economy?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If your country doesn't have a Bill like this, rest assured, it soon
will have.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyhow, it's clear to me that there's no use in railing against the Bill
unless one has an alternative to offer. The debate in the House of Lords
yesterday made it clear that the mood there is that millions are
flouting the law with illegal downloads to rip off artists and Something
Must Be Done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what's the alternative? The solution is the final chapter from
Stanford Law Prof. Lawrence Lessig's book '&lt;a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/Free-Culture-Nature-Future-Creativity/dp/0143034650"&gt;Free
Culture&lt;/a&gt;',
that describes how to fix the whole copyright mess in such a way that
will make everybody happy. Artists will get paid in abundance, very
fairly, in a market-driven way, and the payment will be direct to them.
The labels will be eliminated from the loop. No state monitoring of what
people download will be required. Everybody will be able to continue to
download whatever they like from wherever they like, for free (at point
of use), legally and with clear conscience. Best of all, the creation of
new business models and grass-roots creativity such as songs and other
content will be stimulated through the roof. Whichever country first
introduced this would lead the world in a creative tidal wave that
embraces the powers of the internet, rather than fighting against them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm not going to write what the copyright fix is here. I have to go to
work and I'm still in my pajamas. Oh alright, here's the quick quick
version. We add a tax to every high bandwidth internet connection. The
money goes in a pot. Then a central agency samples how many of each
creative work is being downloaded. This is just a sample - it needn't be
tied to any individual downloader, so it is cheap to do and unintrusive.
Then we distribute the money in the pot to artists, in proportion to the
number of downloads they had.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This quick version has some holes in it. Prof. Lessig ties it all up in
his book. Yes it has some problems - taxes are never popular, and more
expensive internet connections are not what we want. But these problems
are small and soluble, compared to what is currently being discussed
instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know this is so starry-eyed idealistic that it has no chance of being
seriously discussed. But I decided last night that I have to at least
give it a try.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Readers from the UK - Do YOU have even the slightest inkling of
interest in suggesting this to your own MP? Or at least pointing out the
downsides of the current Bill? It would just be one evening out of your
life. I'm visiting mine this weekend. Email me if you have any interest
at all. I can lead you through the process, it's simple.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>geek</category><category>imho</category><category>lessig</category><category>python</category><category>software</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/solveduk-digital-economy-bill/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 03 Dec 2009 16:04:59 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>A Layman's Philosophical Musings</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/a-laymans-philosophical-musings/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;A quick response to to polymath Chris DeLeon's thoughtful post
&lt;a href="http://cdgdl.com/lessons/philosophy.html"&gt;exhorting the virtues of
Philosophy&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A position of ignorance&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Right off the bat I should qualify all this by saying that I don't know
anything about Philosophy. I've never studied it. It seems at times to
be an alien mismatch to the sensibilities of my left-brained mind, and
worse, one that claims to be about logic and reasoning, topics that
ostensibly should be right up my alley. I read Bertrand Russell's
&lt;em&gt;History of Western Philosophy&lt;/em&gt; last year, and although that was a
fabulous, educational romp through the field, &lt;a href="https://www.tartley.com/posts/history-of-western-philisophy"&gt;my complaints about
it&lt;/a&gt; still stand. Now I'm reading a second
book, &lt;em&gt;Think : A Compelling Introduction to Philosophy&lt;/em&gt; by Simon Blackburn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Process&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The process of &lt;em&gt;thinking about things&lt;/em&gt; is a valuable and worthwhile
endeavour. Some people enjoy it, some people don't. Amongst those who
enjoy it, it becomes an end unto itself, and thought and discussions
typically stray towards the more abstract, the more meta, the more
foundational. Anyone who has gleefully participated in a pub discussion
about religion, death, reality, consciousness, government, or any of a
million other topics has participated in this process. It is joyful,
sometimes enlightening, entertaining, and refines the individual's
ability to meaningfully reason on all kinds of topics, from the abstract
to the prosaic. In this sense, and especially from the perspective of
the individual's active participation in the activity, I'm all in favour
of philosophy. Presumably this is why I have been drawn back to read
this second book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Content&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If anything, I have had more objections to &lt;em&gt;Think&lt;/em&gt; than I had to
Russell's book. At first, I thought that my issue was simply that the
discussed historical philosophers produced curiously shoddy work. Their
premises seem shaky. Their arguments full of holes at best. Their
conclusions entirely suspect. While there are some genuinely insightful
ideas and arguments, they are often mutually contradictory, and the
signal to noise is terrible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chris points out the importance of reading a decent translation of the
original sources to gain enough insight to benefit from the arguments,
and in this I defer to his experience. There certainly are some
historical philosophers who seem to make a lot more sense to me than the
others. I had not expected to have to pick and choose based so much upon
my own personal preferences, so in some way my frustration here is
perhaps indicative of an expectation mismatch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As for &lt;em&gt;Think&lt;/em&gt;, as I continue to read, it has slowly dawned on me that
perhaps this impression is actually because the author himself is an
appalling philosopher (sorry Simon!) Every few pages he makes what seems
to me like a terrible logical blunder. If this were correct, that would
presumably make his interpretation of historical philosophers equally
suspect, and perhaps this is why they so often seem simply ludicrous to
me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I realise it is arrogant and bonkers for me to assume I can outclass the
author, a man apparently of considerable knowledge and experience, at
his own game. But this is how it seems to me, so what am I to make of
that?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It seems to me that there are only three possibilities:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Professor Blackburn's thinking is entirely defective. I am sure this
    cannot be the case. He is a professor of his subject, his book,
    while quite understandably not comparable to Russell, has garnered
    great reviews on Amazon and in the press, for whatever that's worth.
    As a layman I shall accord him the deference that is entirely his
    due.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;My own thinking is entirely defective. This is, of course, entirely
    possible, however distasteful it may be to me. How would I know? In
    defence of my sanity, I note that I seem to get by, more or less, in
    everyday life. Or at least, I don't seem to be any more confounded
    by the state of the world than the people around me.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Perhaps, then, the problem lies not solely with myself, but is
    shared by us all. Perhaps human reasoning as expressed in the
    English language is generally not sufficiently precise, well-defined
    or powerful to support consistent philosophical arguments of the
    type that are being put forward. More generally, we aren't remotely
    as good at thinking as we think we are. Pretty much I'm saying
    that (1) and (2) are both true, but that both the professor and I
    can derive some comfort from the idea that the same applies to
    pretty much everybody else.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Method&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is, of course, a method for dealing with the unreliability of our
thoughts and perceptions - the scientific method, in its many forms and
manifestations. I have friends who claim that the scientific method came
out of philosophy, and while I have some reservations about the truth of
this in the day-to-day reality of individual practitioners, of course in
an abstract sense I can see that this lineage is real.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Application of the scientific method would be the normal way out of the
morass of imprecise thoughts that, to date, characterise the majority of
philosophy for me. Some aspects of ancient philosophy have proven
tractable in this regard. These are the subjects that have subsequently
calved off from philosophy to form whole new fields and sciences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, this has the curious effect of diluting the perceived value
of philosophy. As soon as the application of the scientific method lets
thinkers actually gain any traction and start to make real progress on
their topic, we immediately snip that subject off from the realm of
philosophy and give it a different name. Astronomy and cosmology,
biology and psychology, chemistry, physics, and many more. Philosophy
proper, then, consists of the left over bits - the topics upon which the
scientific method has not proven applicable, and hence upon which no
meaningful progress can be made.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chris, and discussion with friends, has helped me see that in this
dismissal, I was overlooking the value of philosophy as an incubator for
other fields. This is of course critical to the development of human
civilisation, and of interest to historians of the respective fields.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What it isn't&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I'm left with is the impression that my minor experiences of
philosophy would have been much improved if my expectations had been
very different at the outset.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My layman's impression of philosophy from the outside was that it
claimed to be the study of tremendously insightful reasoning done by
some of the most powerful minds in history. This expectation was
naturally bound to lead me to be disappointed when my initial foray led
me to discover that many philosophers, particularly ancient ones,
distorted as they are by translation and interpretation, cultural
mismatch, and lack of my modern knowledge of the world, appear to my
sensibilities to be pretty poor. I hope to improve on this situation by
taking on board Chris' advice about choosing particular philosophers who
resonate for me personally, together with the idea of studying
particular translations of original works, rather than quick summaries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition, I had an expectation that all this intense thought might
lead to some more definitive and objective conclusions. However ancient
philosophers acted without the benefit of the scientific method, and
modern philosophy is pruned of topics to which the scientific method is
applicable. As a result, there is much bad mixed in with the good. Even
the good parts cannot be trusted as a guide to any sorts of truth, since
choosing 'the good parts' seems to be a subjective process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This seems inevitable, since without the benefit of the scientific
method, there is no utility function to be used as feedback, by which
ideas could be judged and one school of thought meaningfully compared
against another. There can be no definitive winners or losers, and
without competition, ideas cannot improve by evolution. Instead, each
contributor adds their own voice to the mutually contradictory babble,
and it is left to the reader to sift through for the parts of value.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The lack of an objective means to prune the discussion of its less
worthy branches mean that many philosophers are deified, their writings
sacrosanct and studied for generations, even in cases where they were
clearly absolutely wrong. (Plato's thoughts about the shapes of atoms,
for example.) I accept that study of historical and ancient philosophers
is valid for the perspective it gives on the &lt;em&gt;process&lt;/em&gt; of philosophy,
and as a study of the &lt;em&gt;history&lt;/em&gt; of philosophy itself. However, I am
appalled that so much of their actual, specific writings are studied and
discussed in so much detail, in the same way I would be mortified by the
prospect of scholars spending centuries reviewing the specifics of what
me and my friends said in our philosophical discussions in the pub.
There may be some value in there, but I came to this expecting a précis
of the best minds in the world, not a mishmash of sometimes incoherent
ideas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Upshot&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've done a lot of bitching, but don't take it as a wholesale rejection.
In addition to the things I complain about, there are also a bunch of
really great, stimulating ideas. I just didn't expect to have to do so
much searching and interpretation to find them. Rather, interpret the
above as the painful transitions in my understanding of what philosophy
&lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt;, which parts of it are likely to be of value to me, and what I
should expect from it. Thanks to Chris for his significant contributions
towards my continuing education on this.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>imho</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/a-laymans-philosophical-musings/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 10 Oct 2009 20:09:20 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Copyright and the crowdsourcing of promotional materials</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/copyright-and-the-crowdsourcing-of-promotional-materials/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;There was &lt;a href="http://blog.facebook.com/blog.php?post=110636457130"&gt;a
rumour&lt;/a&gt; that
Facebook was allowing third-party advertisers to use user's photos in
promotional materials. I imagine a photo of me and my friends enjoying
Bacardi responsibly being scraped for use in an advert.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It turns out that rumour is false. But it's not totally groundless -
it's based on the fact that some third-party Facebook applications were
behaving in this way. Facebook put a stop to it, and are to be commended
for that. In the general case, though, it's entirely believable that
this sort of thing may still happen, on Facebook or elsewhere, and it's
fascinating for me to think about why I personally have an objection to
it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I mean, if some company does use your photo in their promotions, then of
course some people would feel this is a privacy issue simply because
they are shy about having their personal photos widely disseminated
outside their immediate social circle - pasted up on billboards or
whatever - and they have a negative emotional reaction to that, and
that's understandable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many people, however, would instead have a &lt;em&gt;positive&lt;/em&gt; emotional
reaction. If my photo of me and friends enjoying Bacardi was chosen to
be used in an ad, it would actually be kinda cool and funny. However, I
*still* would object to them doing it. Even though I'm not losing
anything on this deal, and in fact I'm gaining an amount of amusement
and notoriety, I still don't want Bacardi to reap the benefit. Why is
that?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For me, it's this: Bacardi, who incidentally, have done nothing wrong -
they are my hypothetical example. In fact, let's just call them BigCorp
instead. BigCorp expect to be able to use my photo, without
reciprocating in kind. If I had tried to use BigCorp's images or music
or logo, for my own purposes, and it had come to their attention, then
they would have sued me into the ground.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It may be that they had little choice in the matter. That they were
merely acting in a way that they perceived the prevailing legal and
commercial environment obliged them to do. Regardless, the upshot from
my perspective is that they would have sued me into the ground.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that isn't cool. There is a groundswell of resentment in me for the
way our cultural heritage - all the music and t.v. and movies and images
and adverts and logos that surround us, the things that have come to
form our whole cultural milieu, have been prised from our fingers, by
gradually increasing legal boundaries, such that none of us as
individuals, owns it any more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Copyright used to be of limited scope. It was designed to prevent the
wholesale appropriation of creative works such as books, which were
being copied and republished and sold by third parties unconnected with
the author. This is a fairly obnoxious behaviour, and one I'm prepared
to condemn, and I accept that introducing copyright to prevent it seems
like a good idea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, since the 1970's the scope of what copyright is applicable to
has expanded and expanded, way beyond its original remit. Instead of
being triggered by the commercial activity of a large book
(re)publishing entity, it is now triggered and invoked by the tiniest of
non-commercial personal behaviours, not just publishing books, but
giving a song to a friend, or drawing a comic for your blog in your
bedroom that incorporates the distinctive likeness of a character you
like.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Things that used to be common and socially acceptable (eg. giving an
album you like to a friend) are now clearly illegal and can get you sued
for your life savings plus draconian life-changing conditions. We can no
longer give the songs we like to our friends. We can't post parts of our
culture on YouTube. We can't put it on our blogs, or use it in any way
we feel like. We have been unwillingly converted into pure consumers of
culture, instead of participants. We have been robbed of something we
used to have.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I strongly agree with Banksy, who feels that if any corporate image or
logo or advert is shoved into my face in a public space (e.g.
billboards, but also tv or on the web), then it is, from that moment on,
mine to do with as I wish. If I wish to appropriate the image, or
augment it with daubings of my own, then why should anyone have the
right to stop me? (*huge separate discussion reqd here to justify this,
obviously. Maybe later.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But this, obviously, has been utterly repudiated by the copyright
industry, acting in concert with BigCorp lobbyists, has used legal
strong-arm tactics to deny me the ability to so much as sing happy
birthday in my own restaurant without paying royalties, never mind
ripping off BigCorp advertising materials to form my own pastiche. I
resent that. I've been putting up with it for years, and in return
BigCorp has earned my ill-will on this topic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So in answer to the question "Can Facebook's partners use your photos
for promotional purposes? It'll be funny and cool!" I have to reply "No
you can't. I agree that it would be kinda funny and cool, but on this
topic you have seriously annoyed me. We are not friends. You cannot use
my photos. Now piss off."&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>imho</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/copyright-and-the-crowdsourcing-of-promotional-materials/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 29 Aug 2009 18:08:59 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Letter to my Member of European Parliament : Proposed Copyright Extension</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/letter-to-my-member-of-european-parliament-proposed-copyright-extension/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thursday 19 March 2009&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dear Baroness Ludford, (&lt;strong&gt;Update&lt;/strong&gt;: This was sent to all eleven of my
MEPs)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am writing with reference to the European Parliament's vote on
copyright extension for sound recordings, due to take place on March
23rd.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you know, this is a complex issue, but I shall try my best to keep
this short, I know you must be busy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Amongst the justification for this particular extension to the term of
copyrights, is the idea that artists need more protection, particularly
towards the end of their lives when their income from royalties might
dry up as their copyrights expire.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is misleading in the extreme. Under the current 50 year term, an
artist recording at age 25 will be protected until age 75, and any
artist who records throughout their lifetime will be protected until
many decades beyond their death.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is no need whatsoever to extend the term in order to benefit or
incentivise artists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, as everyone knows, artists in practice almost never end up
owning the copyrights to their own works - the labels do. While artists
and labels are aligned in the desire to sell as many records as
possible, they are in direct opposition when it comes to dividing up the
proceeds. The majority of the income from sales goes to the labels,
because they have such an overwhelmingly dominant position of power in
the relationship. No label is reliant upon any individual artist, while
every artist is very much dependant on their label, to whom they are
tied by contract for many years. Strengthening copyright only
strengthens the position of the copyright owner, ie. the labels, at the
expense of what little leverage the artist may have. Extending the term
of copyright only enhances the labels' income, not the artists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is not the role of copyright to be a protectionist measure to support
labels who are having to adjust their business models in these times of
great change. The last thing we need to do is to construct laws which
chain Europe's creative industries to last-century modes of operation,
at precisely a time when the current tumult will reveal as yet undreamed
of exciting new ways of doing business.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you know, copyright is intended to stimulate the creation of new
creative works, by enabling the artist to earn an income from their own
creations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There exists significant evidence to suggest that stronger copyright may
actually inhibit the production of creative work, by allowing
monopoly-level profits to be reaped from ever smaller amounts of
creative output. The composer Verdi is notable for suddenly decreasing
his creative output when copyright laws over music were introduced in
18th century Italy - his personal correspondence indicates that he
simply had to work less because he was earning more from his earlier
compositions. (note that he retained copyright over his own work.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Similarly, there is the very vital and oft-overlooked influence of the
creative environment which our society fosters. It could well be that
freedom to borrow and build upon inspiration from other artists is a
vital input to the engines of creativity, and to encourage fledgling
artists. By way of anecdotal evidence I say it would not be very
controversial to suggest that the last great English composer of the
Baroque period was Handel, who coincidentally died around the same year
copyright over music was introduced in England. After that, there is a
dearth of truly top-class composers from England, right up until the
20th century. Meanwhile Germany, too preocupied with invasions and
reforging of the nation to introduce copyright laws over music, went on
to produced greats like Bach, Mozart and Beethoven, in a succession of
creative gear-shifts which formed the romance and classical eras, all
done with no copyright over music. *1&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I apologise if I have been unable to express my points very succinctly,
but I hope I have made given you some reasons to consider rejecting this
extension of the copyright term, or at least to consider assessing it in
the light of evidence over its theorised effects, rather than the
deliberately misleading suppositions put forward by those representing
the special interests who stand to directly benefit from the proposal at
the expense of artists and of the rest of society.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With all my gratitude and respect for the work you and your fellow MEPs
have done and will continue to do to resolve these issues,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yours sincerely,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jonathan Hartley&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;*1 See this February 2009 Harvard paper which notes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"An attempt to determine the impact of legal changes on entry into
composing is inconclusive. The paper shows, however, that a golden age
of musical composition nevertheless occurred in nations that
lackedcopyright protection for musical works."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=1336802"&gt;http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=1336802&lt;/a&gt;
The paper is summarised persuasively in an online news article here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.techdirt.com/articles/20090308/1022324034.shtml"&gt;http://www.techdirt.com/articles/20090308/1022324034.shtml&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>imho</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/letter-to-my-member-of-european-parliament-proposed-copyright-extension/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 19 Mar 2009 19:32:20 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>