<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Made out of meat (Posts about ishiguro)</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://www.tartley.com/categories/ishiguro.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2024 &lt;a href="mailto:tartley @ tartley dot com"&gt;Jonathan Hartley&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 04 Oct 2024 14:52:17 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Klara and the Sun</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/klara-and-the-sun/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Klara and the Sun cover" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2022/klara-and-the-sun-cover.webp"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Kazuo Ishiguro, 2021&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was just wonderful to read.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="background:#bb2200; color:white; border-radius: 1em; padding-left: 0.5em; padding-right: 0.5em; padding-top: 2px;"&gt;spoilers&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The near-future scenario is revealed in a compellingly minimal way, teased
in minor details. Eventually we piece together an epidemic of children without
siblings, born into a competitive, authoritarian society. Higher-rank parents
are able to purchase artificial friends, to help with the rigors of
socialization. Klara, a newly activated artificial friend, demonstrates a lack
of experience in dealing with human situations, but her efforts are
unstinting, to understand what is going on within the family to whom she is
sold, and do her best for them. Her earnest naivety as a narrator only
serves to magnify the emotional impacts of the story, as her keen but
inexperienced observation conveys everything we need to know about the
dysfunctions of her tragic new family. She describes
herself as feeling emotions, so the story is partly a discussion of what it
means to be concious, to feel, as the humans around her are forced by
circumstance into desperate schemes that expose the self-protective
aspects of their love.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For all that, though, I'm not sure what to take away from it. Clearly the
author is very skilled. It seems likely that metaphors are at work here. But,
lunk that I am, I'm unable to discern what they are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm fairly sure that the "boxes" Klara sometimes relates her perceptions being
divided into are just stylish flair - a reference to the ways in which her
brain works differently from ours, calving off processing into separate
processors, or some-such, which comes to the fore when she is under stress,
or deciphering complex emotions. I don't &lt;em&gt;think&lt;/em&gt; this strikingly non-literal
aspect is indicative of any deeper symbolism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes, when I fail to pick up on metaphor, it's because religious
allegory is involved. Beyond tales of mere personal transcendence, my brain
just isn't wired that way. I can see that Klara is in many ways an innocent.
Free not only of wrongdoing, but also of wishing harm, and - being made, not
born - of original sin. On the literal level, this is emotionally
resonant, especially when Klara's heroic contribution to the family is
rewarded by being uncomplainingly discarded, like an appliance, at the end of
the book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But is this related to the other big clue about things I'm not picking up on -
the title? I'm at a loss of what to make about Klara's relationship with the
sun, which is a central plot point. Was Klara's bargain with her Sun god
literally answered by a special burst of healing light, that saved her family's
child from terminal illness? Certainly that is how Klara relates it. Could she
perhaps have been imagining this? Might the recovery have been fated to happen
anyway, and Klara's association with the burst of sunlight was all in her head?
But the text tells us that the rest of the household are awestruck by the
brilliance and beauty of that particular sunbeam, not just Klara. Later on, the
questions Rick asks of Klara show that, although he does not understand, he has
guessed the significance of the moment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So. Klara the innocent's anthropomorphized Sun god's healing powers are real,
and He answers her prayers to save the life of a child. And I don't know what
to make of that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, I'm in good company. A quick search does yield intelligent writing
about the book, but I don't see anyone coming up with aspects or metaphors
that I've entirely overlooked - although that is usually quite fruitful when I
search about other books that puzzle me. So I venture that I'm not the only one
who doesn't get it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: left"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>fiction</category><category>ishiguro</category><category>media</category><category>novel</category><category>science-fiction</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/klara-and-the-sun/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 04 Jan 2022 22:06:39 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Buried Giant</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/the-buried-giant/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="The Buried Giant cover" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2021/the-buried-giant-cover.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Kazuo Ishiguro, 2015&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A mythical tale, set in post-Arthurian England. Author Kazuo Ishiguro, Nobel
prize winner for literature, is also famous for Klara and the Sun, Never Let
Me Go, and The Remains of the Day (yes, that one about butlers.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ishiguro moved from Japan to England as a young child, and his insightful
observation of English and Western culture and myth benefits from that
transplant's perspective - at once deeply at home in England, and also
an outsider to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="background:#bb2200; color:white; border-radius: 1em; padding-left: 0.5em; padding-right: 0.5em; padding-top: 2px;"&gt;spoilers&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The tale is populated by ragged peoples, affected by a pervasive amnesia.
Elderly couple Axl and Beatrice abruptly decide to leave their village of damp,
hobbit-like underground burrows to visit a son they'd forgotten they had.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Simlarly, other characters are inspired by a variety of classical sources, from
Beowulf to Arthur's knight and nephew Sir Gawain, now old and prone to quixotic
rants - hinting at the subconscious conflict his code of honor has with the
dark means by which he and other knights formerly helped Arthur achieve the
current uneasy peace between native Britons and invading Saxons, now occupying
villages across the land.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The journey is perilous, encountering roaming ogres and deadly pixies, not
to mention soldiers of the local lords, and deadly conflicts within the party
itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But any action is relayed with cool distance. Either through the pervasive
mental fog, or using expert fighters' clinical analysis of the minutia of
stance or grip, or by foretelling the ebb and flow of a battle by analysing the
terrain, then allowing the battle itself to take place off stage, only assumed
to have happened, by characters who weren't there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This muted indirectness is entirely in keeping with the ambiguous, dreamlike
style of the book, which is heightened by the sing-song formalism of the
characters' medieval speech, and the narrator's occasional surreal hint of
relating this tale to contemporaries who live in some other, unidentifiable,
historic time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The journey eventually comes to revolve around the dispatch - or defence - of a
dragon that is said to be the source of everyone's forgetfulness, and as this
goal approaches, vague fears surface of what might be remembered when the
mist lifts. Will Axl and Beatrice's treasured relationship survive the
revelations of their pasts? Will the longstanding truce in the land survive
the remembering of wartime battles and atrocities? Will Saxon resentment at
Arthur's desperate misdeeds be stoked into resumption of the violent war of
invasion? This is left unresolved by the novel's end, but as reader, we know
that the Saxons did ultimately conquer all of England, displacing the Britons
culturally and politically, and probably murdering a good number of them along
the way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Personally, I'm minded to think of ancient England here as being a root of
modern Western culture, and the mist as an allegory for the bland ignorance of
our own culture's atrocities. The deliberate forgetting, like the mist, clouds
all our conciousnesses, making it hard for us to remember who we are. Why we're
here. The silent resentment of crushed minorities and genocide survivors forms
a pressure, struggling against the placating narrative that everything's OK
now. But, contained, the pressure builds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Truly a buried giant, indeed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: left"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>fantasy</category><category>fiction</category><category>ishiguro</category><category>media</category><category>myth</category><category>novel</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/the-buried-giant/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 25 Oct 2021 15:16:53 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>