<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>tartley.com (Posts about journal)</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/</link><description>Events of my life.</description><atom:link href="https://www.tartley.com/categories/journal.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2021 &lt;a href="mailto:tartley @ the domain tartley dot com"&gt;Jonathan Hartley&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 18 May 2021 21:17:53 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Result of MP visit - I suck</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/result-of-mp-visit-i-suck/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;So earlier tonight I turned up at the monthly 'surgery' of my MP, Frank
Dobson (Labour), to present my objections to the Digital Economy Bill.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the benefit of others also going to tackle Mr Dobson on this issue,
(and anyone going to see some other MP) here's a quick write up of my
experiences:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I arrived up half an hour before it started, and there were about eight
parties ahead of me in line. My turn came half an hour after they kicked
off. I had hoped to present my argument pretty much as I laid it out in
my previous blog post. However, sadly I pretty much comprehensively
failed to get my point across.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The 'I am not a spittle-flecked loon' introduction&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As planned, I started out by saying that I fully support copyright law,
and of the importance of finding ways to ensure that artists get
renumerated for their work. The portions of the bill which describe the
pursuit of illegal downloaders therefore have laudable and important
goals, however I think that the costs and problems associated with
preventing illegal downloads like this are substantial, and actually
make this section of the bill counter-productive. Mr Dobson was an
affable gent, and listened attentively to what I had to say.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Disconnection needlessly punishes more innocent people than guilty
ones&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first objection I wanted to raise, because it seems to me to be the
most clear-cut, is that the bill suggests disconnection from the
internet for persistent downloaders. I pointed out that since most
internet connections are shared between several people (families and
housemates) disconnecting a single illegal downloader would also
unfairly affect all the people who share their connection. Mr Dobson's
opinion was that it would rarely come to actual disconnection - the
intention of the Bill is very much that disconnection would be a
rarely-used last resort. The earlier provisions in the bill (warning
offenders for their first 'two strikes') are intended to stop almost
everyone from illegally downloading, without any need for actual
disconnections to take place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obviously I regard that as a grave misjudgement. But I had a lot of
ground to cover, so I left this issue at that. I still feel that even if
disconnection were only applied to a small number of people (which seems
unlikely, from my perspective), it is still true that this would affect
more innocents than guilty parties. There is no reason not to prefer
more conventional punitive measures over disconnection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Impossibility of distinguishing guilt from innocence&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I moved onto my second point: When monitoring downloads, it is
impossible to distinguish between guilt and innocence. If I download a
song I own, from my home to my office, this behaviour may currently be
legally murky, but it is clearly morally justifiable. To any external
observer, this looks indistinguishable from illegal download. An
observer cannot tell whether a particular download is illegal or not
just by looking at the bits going down the wire - it requires more
context than that. It requires the observer to know which CDs I have
bought, and to what use I intend to put the proceeds (is it subject to
fair use exemptions, etc?) Therefore, along with many illegal
downloaders, the system proposed in the bill will also catch many
innocent people in its net.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These innocents can appeal - there is a procedure in the bill for this -
however they will find it impossible to demonstrate their innocence. If
I have bought a CD and ripped it to my computer (which I have done with
all my CDs, many years ago) then when I am accused of illegally
downloading it, how am I supposed to demonstrate that I once bought that
CD?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr Dobson listened with patience and good humour to this. However, it
was clear from his responses that while he is a capable man who is
working hard and with the best of intentions, the scenario I outlined
was fairly foreign to his experience. He suggested that the bill is not
aimed at catching people like me who are doing nothing wrong. It is
aimed at people who are making a dishonest living by massive downloads
which they are somehow making money from. I don't believe that any such
people actually exist, never mind that the bill is aimed at them: The
wording of the bill clearly encompasses individuals downloading music
for their own listening pleasure, and deliberately so, but I did not go
into this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr Dobson felt that the appeals process would be sufficient for anyone
such as my self to protest their innocence. I totally failed to
communicate that demonstrating my innocence during such an appeals
process would be very difficult. When I reiterated that I could not, for
example, produce the receipts to all the music and movies I have ever
bought in my entire lifetime, Mr Dobson reiterated that the bill was not
aimed at innocent people like me, it would only be applied to illegal
downloaders. I again said I don't see how the ISPs can distinguish
between the two - for example I cannot produce the receipts nor the CDs
that my music came from - I ripped them in 1998, and have since
discarded them all. Mr Dobson said that perhaps &lt;em&gt;when&lt;/em&gt; the bill become
law (my emphasis), people will be obliged to keep their CDs "in a
plastic bag in the garage", in preparation for just such a scenario. I
pointed out that all of my music for the last few years has been
purchased online - so never came on any CDs to begin with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr Dobson didn't seem receptive to this argument. He was still in good
spirits at this point, however, I totally failed to persuade him that
difficulty in distinguishing between guilty and innocent downloaders was
even a realistic possibility, never mind that it would actually be a
serious problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had hoped to move on from this point to demonstrate that this
presumption of guilt that the bill contains will have a severe chilling
effect on people's legitimate and morally justifiable uses of the
internet, and this will hamper the development of business models, which
will be presumptively quashed before ever getting a chance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, Mr Dobson suggested that I should send him the remainder of my
points to him in a letter. I asked him if I could just spend 30 seconds
skipping through the executive summary of the remainder of my argument,
since I felt there was a logical chain of inferences to follow, which
demonstrated some real problems with the bill. He suggested that I write
it to him in a letter instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Probable ten or fifteen minutes had elapsed. We exchanged cordial
pleasantries and headed out for a lovely curry down the street with my
awesome wife.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>geek</category><category>imho</category><category>journal</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/result-of-mp-visit-i-suck/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 05 Dec 2009 05:23:09 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Difference Engine</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/the-difference-engine/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="differenceengine" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2008/12/differenceengine.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by William Gibson and Bruce Sterling, 1990&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A quick re-read, inspired by a recent visit to &lt;a href="http://www.sciencemuseum.org.uk/"&gt;the Science
Museum&lt;/a&gt;, where we were enthralled by
our meanderings around various astonishing artifacts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rickety-looking &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Apollo_10"&gt;Apollo
  10&lt;/a&gt; capsule, charred from
  re-entry, having journeyed to within 9 miles of the moon and back
  again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stephenson%27s_Rocket"&gt;Stevenson's
  Rocket&lt;/a&gt;, not, as
  I had previously understood, the first steam-powered railway
  locomotive, just a revolutionary improvement in design, capable of
  the unheard-of speed of 29 miles an hour.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Watson and Crick's original 6-foot mechano model of the double-helix
  structure of a &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/DNA"&gt;DNA molecule&lt;/a&gt; (or
  at least the original bits of it, re-assembled at Kings around
  1990), constructed between LSD fuelled revelry and Sunday
  afternoons' quiet boozing pondering the meaning of life. Not a bad
  lifestyle, it has to be said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Charles Babbage's Difference Engine number 1, or at least remnants
  of it. This is the arithmetic precursor to his subsequent, and more
  ambitious, analytical engine, the conception of which was a precient
  stroke of genius, the world's first programmable computer. Lacking
  electronics, it was implemented in a purely mechanical manner, a 40
  year labour of which he pursued until his death.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was surprised to learn that the failing of the device was not, as I
had previously heard, due to the inadequate manufacturing tolerances of
the time. Recent examinations have demonstrated these to be more than
adequate. Instead, the lengthy and costly extensions to the project,
leading to its eventual failure in an ocean of debts and soured
relationships is nowadays blamed on the project suffering from
'inappropriate management'. Interesting to see the nascent software
industry starting out as it was destined to continue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was, of course, this last item at the museum which inspired me to
pick up &lt;em&gt;The Difference Engine&lt;/em&gt; paperback again, an alternate history
novel in which the authors indulge the fantasy that Babbage's project
had been a success, and the British Empire, in the upheaval of a
steam-powered information processing era, underwent a series of
meritocratous social revolutions, and as a result was better equipped to
continue its expansion across the globe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rating 7.5/10 - a splendid ripping yarn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: both"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>books</category><category>exhibits</category><category>fiction</category><category>geek</category><category>journal</category><category>media</category><category>novel</category><category>science-fiction</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/the-difference-engine/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2008 15:19:16 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Suze...</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/the-suze/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Launches a new blog, at &lt;a href="http://thesuze.com"&gt;a shiny new permenant URL&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>journal</category><category>write</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/the-suze/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2008 17:52:19 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>OpenID works!</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/openid-works/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2008/09/openid.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've always been
intrigued by &lt;a href="http://openid.net"&gt;OpenID&lt;/a&gt;, while simultaneously being
repulsed by the identifiers that I thought users were forced to adopt.
Seeing one too many strings like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;https://me.yahoo.com/a/.DuSz_IEq5Vw5NZLAHUFHWEKLSfQnRFuebro-&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;tossed around made me think I'd have to adopt a username like that,
which obviously is never going to wash, for aesthetic and typability
reasons alone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fortunately &lt;a href="http://nedbatchelder.com/blog/200809/openid_is_too_hard.html"&gt;Ned Batchelder's
rant&lt;/a&gt;,
leading me to &lt;a href="http://simonwillison.net/2006/Dec/19/openid/"&gt;Simon 'Zeppelin' Willison's demystifying blog
post&lt;/a&gt;, taught me all about
how to use your own URL as your OpenID equivalent of a username, by
inserting some HTML onto your web page. So now I've managed to jump
through the sign-up hoops required to get me one of those
globally-unique OpenID username identifiers for myself:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;tartley.com&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There. That isn't too painful, is it? Since I got set up, it has proven
lovely to use. Get on board!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>geek</category><category>journal</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/openid-works/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2008 00:06:48 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Freefall</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/freefall/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Bjnje6-8vCM" title="Sound of screaming"&gt;&lt;img alt="Sound of screaming" src="https://img.youtube.com/vi/Bjnje6-8vCM/0.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Me and the missus slung 200 feet in the air in a spherical 10 foot roll
cage, on board the 'Slingshot' on the opening night of the Steel County
Fair, Minnesota.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>journal</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/freefall/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2008 12:40:08 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Neogeography</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/neogeography/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2008/08/co-to-ca-road-trip-map.png" title="co-to-ca-road-trip-map"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the summer I've been keeping a geographic journal of some of our
recent adventures:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;dl&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;&lt;a href="http://maps.google.com/maps/ms?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;msa=0&amp;amp;msid=114555587615190768594.00044fcb05ec0c0be2012&amp;amp;ll=45.540084,-93.44283&amp;amp;spn=5.809675,14.282227&amp;amp;z=7"&gt;The Minnesota project&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;our summer in Blooming Prairie&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;dl&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;&lt;a href="http://maps.google.com/maps/ms?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;msa=0&amp;amp;msid=114555587615190768594.000453372a3a9329df229&amp;amp;ll=37.431251,-110.786133&amp;amp;spn=13.158173,28.564453&amp;amp;t=h&amp;amp;z=6"&gt;CO to CA&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;our summer roadtrip&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's an amusing journalling project for me, but as an exercise in
neogeography (the distainful term Geographic Information System pros use
to describe such upstart tools, popular with the great unwashed) I have
to say it's pretty forlorn. The editing tool is thoroughly annoying to
use, and the data model is none existant - you're simply crayoning
one-off symbols on top of the map, with no ability to relate any symbol
to any other, except by manually assigning them the same symbology. The
ability to import KMZ is little consolation if all the resultant data is
so unstructured. No doubt things will get better as GIS and neogeography
borrow each other's best ideas, but for the time being this exercise
left me disappointed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I seem to recall that the editing tools in Google Earth are a smidgeon
better, but still profoundly lacking. Anyone got any ideas what I should
be using instead for personal 'for amusement' projects like this?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>gis</category><category>journal</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/neogeography/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 11 Aug 2008 21:31:25 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Just Married!</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/just-married/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.tartley.com/files/2008/05/wed.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="Just Married!" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2008/05/wed.jpg" title="Just Married!"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At
the end of March, Susan and I exchanged rings, vows, signatures and
thumbprints on a beach near to Tulum, Mexico, with eighty-five of our
families and friends, plus 'TriPawd', the beach's resident three-legged
dog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks to everyone for coming all the way to join the party and making
it so special. It all worked out better than we could have hoped - We
never imagined that our own wedding would be so spectacularly brilliant.
The honeymoon in Guatemala was also astonishingly good, from watching
the sun rise over Mayan ruins in the jungle, to hiking volcanoes
overlooking lake Atitlan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We've taken photos from a few people, and put a selection of the best of
these online, listed below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://photos.google.com/album/AF1QipOOwy2ywMiILnYGBxh3UGImNgtiKi4QCyr04WmG"&gt;Arrival in Tulum&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://photos.google.com/album/AF1QipNAqeKG0tcJkfPGSDthl-Ms_phvFVqeOthOdPdV"&gt;Thursday night party&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://photos.google.com/share/AF1QipPcz63xwl28uezPMUa40psZmkOEpGzL0LWdm3_q0eHMeCNJDXmjuHHB4BD-bbxqsQ?key=VktPczAwcmE0VEFLY2RHbEpCWVM1X084bmNFOERR"&gt;Wedding day breakfast and preparation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://photos.google.com/album/AF1QipMJbxudvhu-eKxwxxUhOA_GlYzrsnu9rOMviKi3"&gt;Wedding ceremony&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://vimeo.com/840598"&gt;Awesome little vid of the petal-throwing&lt;/a&gt;, courtesy Lindsay &amp;amp; Aaron&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://photos.google.com/album/AF1QipOYwojvKwjo9Xf-XYhe9Iscks84LVMTVuSOvNI3"&gt;Wedding reception&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://photos.google.com/album/AF1QipNRP6Z6WhM9uKyLnLE-BbWUVuazzMG1juHe-Jg3"&gt;More of Tulum&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://photos.google.com/album/AF1QipM816PgXq11ACuayazsraR6BIjRw6uUiLWrA9Oi"&gt;Boat trip&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are also a metric zillion other photos elsewhere too:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/aaronindenver/sets/72157604336077174/"&gt;Aaron's&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.brownsolutions.biz/administrator/components/gallery/JBs-Wedding"&gt;Al Brown's&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.facebook.com/album.php?page=1&amp;amp;aid=20525&amp;amp;id=509123606"&gt;Alia's&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Amanda's&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.facebook.com/album.php?aid=19098&amp;amp;id=501388030&amp;amp;op=80"&gt;one&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.facebook.com/album.php?aid=19099&amp;amp;id=501388030&amp;amp;op=80"&gt;two&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://photos.walmart.com/shareephotolib/p=120121210651609191/l=10368438/g=17690942/cobrandOid=1011/otsc=SYE/otsi=SALB/pns/share/p=120121210651609191/l=10368438/g=17690942/cobrandOid=1011/otsc=SYE/otsi=SALB"&gt;Anita's&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Batty's:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/ebatty/sets/72157604321078488/"&gt;ceremony&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/ebatty/sets/72157604370499812/"&gt;Tulum&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.facebook.com/album.php?aid=104393&amp;amp;id=806225359&amp;amp;op=60"&gt;Harry's&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.facebook.com/album.php?aid=44698&amp;amp;id=626416349&amp;amp;op=80"&gt;Jules'&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://picasaweb.google.com/marci.pierce/Tulum"&gt;Marci's&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://flickr.com/photos/neil_stone/sets/72157604415231580/"&gt;Neil's&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nixta's&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/flixta/sets/72157604378814124/"&gt;wedding&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/flixta/sets/72157604374702326/"&gt;environs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/ebatty/collections/72157600828965024/"&gt;Peter's&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Phil's&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://frosties.com/index.php?option=com_gallery2&amp;amp;Itemid=28&amp;amp;g2_itemId=33451"&gt;one&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://frosties.com/index.php?option=com_gallery2&amp;amp;Itemid=28&amp;amp;g2_itemId=33552"&gt;two&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://frosties.com/index.php?option=com_gallery2&amp;amp;Itemid=28&amp;amp;g2_itemId=33653"&gt;three&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.facebook.com/album.php?aid=33845&amp;amp;id=513030422&amp;amp;op=60"&gt;Steve's&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://picasaweb.google.com/tiva.montalbano/SusanAndJBTulumMarch2008?authkey=5bI2u0vkCWo"&gt;Tiva's&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/atonks/sets/72157604418837612/"&gt;Tonk's&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.kodakgallery.com/I.jsp?c=37w0p9r.3r4uaqjj&amp;amp;x=0&amp;amp;y=tbhnex&amp;amp;localeid=en_US"&gt;Will's&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If there are more that we haven't yet seen, please
&lt;a href="mailto:tartley@tartley.com"&gt;let us know&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>journal</category><category>refried</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/just-married/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 23 Apr 2008 18:16:36 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>History meme</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/history-meme/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class="err"&gt;$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;history&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;|&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;awk&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;'{a[$2]++ } END{for(i in a){print a[i] " " i}}'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;|&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;sort&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;rn&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;|&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;head&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="mi"&gt;107&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;ll&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="err"&gt;#&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;an&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;alias&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;for&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;ls&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;l&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="mi"&gt;92&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;cd&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="mi"&gt;50&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;next&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;sh&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="err"&gt;#&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;a&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;script&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;I&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;use&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;during&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;a&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;presentation&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;I&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;'ve given a lot recently&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s1"&gt;35 vi&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s1"&gt;19 imageresize # a script I wrote to shrink photos before uploading them&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s1"&gt;17 sudo&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s1"&gt;17 rm&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s1"&gt;17 gvim&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s1"&gt;17 ctags # Does '&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;history&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="err"&gt;'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;include&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;shell&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;commands&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;executed&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;by&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;mappings&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;within&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;vi&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="vm"&gt;?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="mi"&gt;13&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;ls&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;</description><category>geek</category><category>journal</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/history-meme/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 23 Apr 2008 11:50:01 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Denver stagathon</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/denver-stagathon/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2008/03/nun-of-your-business.jpg"&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Nun of your business&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://photos.google.com/album/AF1QipM04-dGG9h_wCxE57Ut2zg9k7VsxEf-O2hAzWvr"&gt;Some blurry photos are up&lt;/a&gt;
of an
absolutely brilliant stag event in Denver, starting with an afternoon of
UK vs rest-of-the-world tomfoolery, which included the most laughing
I've done in ages. After a brilliant curry and singstar-style action at
Pete's ultimate downtown loft, I was presented with my outfit for the
evening (pictured.) We made a beeline for The Bank to reprise the
stalwart Colfax crawl route, where we were intercepted by &lt;em&gt;the ladies&lt;/em&gt;,
and where we then, in turn, intercepted Dana Sisti's engagement party.
Finished the night roasting gently in Phil's hot-tub until the dawn.
Brilliant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So brilliant to see everyone. Luv ya! Mean it!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some much better photos by people with steadier hands and real cameras:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://talia73.multiply.com/photos/album/64/JBs_Colfax_Crawl_-_He_tried_but_didnt_escape..."&gt;Natalie&lt;/a&gt;
  (registration needed)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/aaronindenver/sets/72157604216510883/"&gt;Aaron&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update:&lt;/strong&gt; Oh god, there's a &lt;a href="http://www.aaronsdayoff.com/2008/03/jbs-bachelor-partypub-crawl.html"&gt;video of the
cowbell&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update:&lt;/strong&gt; The scores are in. It was difficult to discern in the heat
of battle, but a rigourous statistical analysis reveals that team UK
absolutely dominated the laser quest:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.tartley.com/files/2008/03/lqods.zip" title="LQ"&gt;&lt;img alt="LQ" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2008/03/lq.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>journal</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/denver-stagathon/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2008 03:59:38 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Where you gonna be?</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/where-you-gonna-be/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;[&lt;a href="http://www.vimeo.com/796747/l:embed_796747"&gt;Google Earth and
whereyougonnabe&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href="http://www.vimeo.com/user365144/l:embed_796747"&gt;Peter
Batty&lt;/a&gt; on
&lt;a href="http://vimeo.com/l:embed_796747"&gt;Vimeo&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Peter Batty has a funky screencast of his incipient social networking
slash geolocation application, &lt;a href="http://whereyougonnabe.com/"&gt;Where You Gonna
Be?&lt;/a&gt; which allows you to see when your
future itinerary crosses paths with other people you know. Initially
implemented as a &lt;a href="http://apps.facebook.com/whereyougonnabe/"&gt;Facebook
app&lt;/a&gt;, it now features Google
Earth integration. It's currently restricted to beta testers, but should
be opening up to all comers soon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One day, functionality like this will be part of the ubiquitous and
unobtrusive infrastructure of society. For now, there's WYGB.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>gis</category><category>journal</category><category>web</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/where-you-gonna-be/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 20 Mar 2008 06:26:41 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>