<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>tartley.com (Posts about law)</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://www.tartley.com/categories/law.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2021 &lt;a href="mailto:tartley @ the domain tartley dot com"&gt;Jonathan Hartley&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 18 May 2021 19:11:54 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Remix</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/remix/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left; padding: 1em"&gt;
&lt;img alt="remix" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2009/04/remix.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Lawrence Lessig&lt;/em&gt;, 2008.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is creating a mix CD for a friend an act of creativity, or a criminal
offence? When you shoot a home video of your child which has a TV on in
the background, is there really any need for lawsuits? What business do
federal laws have in trying to regulate this sort of activity anyway?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those, like me, who view modern copyright law as a morass of
intractable problems, irreconcilable interests, overreaching government
intervention and profoundly unfair restrictions on personal freedoms,
Professor Lessig's words are a welcome infusion of clarity, pragmatism
and respect for all interested parties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With an engaging and accessible style, he describes exactly what is
wrong with modern copyright, with clarity and impartiality, and why this
is a deep and pervasive problem that cuts to the heart of all that we
value in human culture. He describes how fixing this would benefit each
of us, from individual consumers and amateur producers, through
professional writers, musicians and copyright holders. Then, in a
surprisingly constructive final section, he outlines five simple changes
to copyright law that would, at a stroke, fix all the major problems,
vastly simplify the situation, eliminate the ambiguity over the legality
of our everyday actions, and all without apparently causing any harm or
loss to any interested party.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rating:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;10/10 If you have any interest in the forces that are reshaping our
society and turning industries upside-down within the space of years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;0/10 If you dislike freedom or free markets, or are a big fan of
overbearing government regulation and monopolies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: both"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>books</category><category>culture</category><category>internet</category><category>law</category><category>media</category><category>non-fiction</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/remix/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 08 Apr 2009 04:42:58 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Free Culture</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/free-culture/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Free Culture" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2008/02/free-culture.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Lawrence Lessig (2004)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Accessible, entertaining, rich with historical perspective, and cuts
incisively to the core of modern society's conflict over intellectual
property. To my mind, one of the most important books of the decade. I'd
highly recommend it. And it's available for free from your iPhone's
built-in ebooks installer, or
&lt;a href="http://www.free-culture.cc/freecontent/"&gt;as a pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rating: 10/10. Blimey.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: both"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>books</category><category>culture</category><category>internet</category><category>law</category><category>media</category><category>non-fiction</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/free-culture/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 25 Feb 2008 20:08:18 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Hacker Crackdown : Law and Disorder on the Electronic Frontier</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/the-hacker-crackdown-law-and-disorder-on-the-electronic-frontier/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="The Hacker Crackdown" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2008/01/hacker-crackdown.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Bruce Sterling, &lt;a href="http://www.archive.org/search.php?query=hacker%20crackdown%20AND%20mediatype%3Aaudio%20AND%20collection%3Aopensource_audio"&gt;read aloud by Cory Doctorow&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Only the second audiobook I've bothered to listen to, and it seems to
work very well, especially when commuting, since you can continue
listening without interruption while leaving the tube and walking. (It's
taken me 36 years to figure this out? Genius.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cory does a fine job of reading, and I'm grateful to him for bringing
this important book to my attention. When he describes reading it on
it's publication in 1994 as 'life changing', I can understand why. It
describes the clash of cultures resulting from American law
enforcement's attempts to crack down on the hackers, crackers and
phreaks of the nascent cyberpunk underworld of the early '90s. Many of
the underlying issues have even more relevance today. Can taking a copy
of digital information be equated with stealing, given that the original
owner still retains their original copy? Or is it more analogous to
attempting to overhear a conversation which the speakers would rather
wasn't overheard? While some hackers have real criminal intent, there
are a significant proportion with a very strong ethic to do no harm, who
view their tinkering as merely the exploration of an online frontier,
filled with challenges and puzzles, and rewards of rich hordes of
information - the dispersal of which is not just a god-given right, but
actually a moral responsibility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When law enforcement agencies went after this crowd with a heavy-handed
and indiscriminate approach, teenagers still living with their parents
ended up in court facing years in prison, colossal fines and legal fees,
in some instances simply for simply republishing a document that was
already in widespread circulation. Innocents had tens of thousands of
dollars worth of computers seized and never returned, even though no
charges were ever filed against them. The resulting backlash formed the
beginnings of the Electronic Frontier Foundation, a philanthropic
organization devoted to defending the rights of individuals in the
online realm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This whole tale is laced with many entertaining insights into the quirks
and motives of the colorful individuals involved, and this makes the
whole thing an enjoyable romp through a serious topic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rating: 8/10 - I only wish I'd read it ten years ago&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: both"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>audiobook</category><category>books</category><category>culture</category><category>internet</category><category>law</category><category>media</category><category>non-fiction</category><category>software</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/the-hacker-crackdown-law-and-disorder-on-the-electronic-frontier/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 02 Feb 2008 22:15:49 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>