<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>tartley.com | Jonathan Hartley's personal blog (Posts about law)</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://www.tartley.com/categories/law.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2023 &lt;a href="mailto:tartley @ the domain tartley dot com"&gt;Jonathan Hartley&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 23 Aug 2023 15:22:21 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Permanent Record</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/permanent-record/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Permanent Record" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2021/permanent-record-cover.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Edward Snowden, 2019&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I really enjoyed this memoir. The story is familiar, but intriguing to hear
in the characteristically articulate words of Snowden himself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He recounts growing up as a computer nerd in a family dedicated to military
service, punctuated by startling scenes such as being caught in the pandemonium
outside NSA headquarters as it was evacuated during 9/11, and the subsequent
overreach of surveillance capability that triggered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He describes the interesting parts of his ascent through jobs, and clearance
levels, within the intelligence community, and how he came to slowly suspect —
and later confirm — that the government was collecting all the communications
and transactions, from everyone who touched a phone or computer, in America and
across the world. A vast spying mechanism turned upon the populace, beyond the
wildest dreams of the Stasi, who only surveilled one third of their population.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At "Constitution Day" in the office, a forlorn desk in the cafeteria hands
out copies of the constitution, which his clearance had required that he, and
his colleagues, swear an oath to uphold. He quoted the 4th amendment to
colleagues:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;"The right of the people to be secure in their persons, houses, papers, and
effects, against unreasonable searches and seizures, shall not be violated."&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The responses were dead-eyed shrugs - yeah, sure, but what can you do? What
indeed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He describes the dangers of a government given too much power to spy on
the everyday lives of its citizens, and the crisis of conscience that slowly
lead to his decision to let the American people know that they were being spied
upon, and his planning of how to go about it. How he slowly accumulated the
hundreds of documents needed to reveal the full extent and capabilities of the
spying apparatus. The extraction of those documents, hidden on his person on
micro SD cards, concealed in places such as in a Rubik's cube he routinely
carried through security. The months long process of selecting journalists who
could both communicate the material coherently to the public, and vet the
public releases to eliminate the risk to our undercover personnel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His recounts the preparations for flight, tying up his affairs like a man about
to die. Emptying bank accounts, leaving cash for his girlfriend to find.
Leaving the house tidy and repaired. The necessity of flight, to avoid a show
trial, devoid of any meaningful defense. A whistle-blower is not allowed to
argue that their disclosures were civilly beneficial. Even now, when Snowden's
leaks have caused Congress to change laws regarding surveillance, or caused the
courts to strike down types of mass surveillance programs as illegal, or caused
both the Attorney General and the President of the United States to admit that
the resulting debate over mass surveillance was a crucial one for the public to
have. All these claims would be dismissed by the court as not just irrelevant,
but inadmissible, leading to a sentence of up to ten years per leaked document.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And finally, flight itself. A tense series of airplanes and delays, meeting the
selected journalists in Hong Kong, selected for being sufficiently disjoint
from Chinese rule so as not to taint his revelations with the suspicion of
having sold out to China, but still sufficiently lawful, and under the auspices
of the distant Chinese rule, that that the American government would not snatch
him off the street with impunity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The indulgence of the Hong Kong government fell apart, as the US filed for
extradition. He fled bound for Ecuador, but was pulled aside during a 20-hour
layover in a Moscow airport, for a conversation with Russian intelligence,
during which Snowden insists he will not work with them, he only wants to catch
his flight out. They reveal to him that he cannot leave, since the US State
department has cancelled his passport. He is stranded in Moscow airport for 40
days, and eventually granted temporary asylum in Russia. Eventually, his
girlfriend — who knew nothing about his plans — recovered from the shock of his
unannounced departure, moved out to Moscow to be with him, and then a year
later, they were married.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: both"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>law</category><category>media</category><category>memoir</category><category>non-fiction</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/permanent-record/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 10 Oct 2021 16:18:16 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Remix</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/remix/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left; padding: 1em"&gt;
&lt;img alt="remix" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2009/04/remix.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Lawrence Lessig&lt;/em&gt;, 2008.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is creating a mix CD for a friend an act of creativity, or a criminal
offence? When you shoot a home video of your child which has a TV on in
the background, is there really any need for lawsuits? What business do
federal laws have in trying to regulate this sort of activity anyway?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those, like me, who view modern copyright law as a morass of
intractable problems, irreconcilable interests, overreaching government
intervention and profoundly unfair restrictions on personal freedoms,
Professor Lessig's words are a welcome infusion of clarity, pragmatism
and respect for all interested parties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With an engaging and accessible style, he describes exactly what is
wrong with modern copyright, with clarity and impartiality, and why this
is a deep and pervasive problem that cuts to the heart of all that we
value in human culture. He describes how fixing this would benefit each
of us, from individual consumers and amateur producers, through
professional writers, musicians and copyright holders. Then, in a
surprisingly constructive final section, he outlines five simple changes
to copyright law that would, at a stroke, fix all the major problems,
vastly simplify the situation, eliminate the ambiguity over the legality
of our everyday actions, and all without apparently causing any harm or
loss to any interested party.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rating:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;10/10 If you have any interest in the forces that are reshaping our
society and turning industries upside-down within the space of years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;0/10 If you dislike freedom or free markets, or are a big fan of
overbearing government regulation and monopolies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: both"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>culture</category><category>internet</category><category>law</category><category>lessig</category><category>media</category><category>non-fiction</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/remix/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 08 Apr 2009 04:42:58 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Free Culture</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/free-culture/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Free Culture" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2008/02/free-culture.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Lawrence Lessig (2004)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Accessible, entertaining, rich with historical perspective, and cuts
incisively to the core of modern society's conflict over intellectual
property. To my mind, one of the most important books of the decade. I'd
highly recommend it. And it's available for free from your iPhone's
built-in ebooks installer, or
&lt;a href="http://www.free-culture.cc/freecontent/"&gt;as a pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rating: 10/10. Blimey.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: both"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>culture</category><category>internet</category><category>law</category><category>lessig</category><category>media</category><category>non-fiction</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/free-culture/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 25 Feb 2008 20:08:18 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Hacker Crackdown : Law and Disorder on the Electronic Frontier</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/the-hacker-crackdown-law-and-disorder-on-the-electronic-frontier/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="The Hacker Crackdown" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2008/01/hacker-crackdown.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Bruce Sterling, &lt;a href="http://www.archive.org/search.php?query=hacker%20crackdown%20AND%20mediatype%3Aaudio%20AND%20collection%3Aopensource_audio"&gt;read aloud by Cory Doctorow&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Only the second audiobook I've bothered to listen to, and it seems to
work very well, especially when commuting, since you can continue
listening without interruption while leaving the tube and walking. (It's
taken me 36 years to figure this out? Genius.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cory does a fine job of reading, and I'm grateful to him for bringing
this important book to my attention. When he describes reading it on
it's publication in 1994 as 'life changing', I can understand why. It
describes the clash of cultures resulting from American law
enforcement's attempts to crack down on the hackers, crackers and
phreaks of the nascent cyberpunk underworld of the early '90s. Many of
the underlying issues have even more relevance today. Can taking a copy
of digital information be equated with stealing, given that the original
owner still retains their original copy? Or is it more analogous to
attempting to overhear a conversation which the speakers would rather
wasn't overheard? While some hackers have real criminal intent, there
are a significant proportion with a very strong ethic to do no harm, who
view their tinkering as merely the exploration of an online frontier,
filled with challenges and puzzles, and rewards of rich hordes of
information - the dispersal of which is not just a god-given right, but
actually a moral responsibility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When law enforcement agencies went after this crowd with a heavy-handed
and indiscriminate approach, teenagers still living with their parents
ended up in court facing years in prison, colossal fines and legal fees,
in some instances simply for simply republishing a document that was
already in widespread circulation. Innocents had tens of thousands of
dollars worth of computers seized and never returned, even though no
charges were ever filed against them. The resulting backlash formed the
beginnings of the Electronic Frontier Foundation, a philanthropic
organization devoted to defending the rights of individuals in the
online realm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This whole tale is laced with many entertaining insights into the quirks
and motives of the colorful individuals involved, and this makes the
whole thing an enjoyable romp through a serious topic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rating: 8/10 - I only wish I'd read it ten years ago&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: both"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>audiobook</category><category>book</category><category>culture</category><category>doctorow</category><category>geek</category><category>internet</category><category>law</category><category>media</category><category>non-fiction</category><category>software</category><category>stirling</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/the-hacker-crackdown-law-and-disorder-on-the-electronic-frontier/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 02 Feb 2008 22:15:49 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Tide Turning on Copyright Abuses?</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/tide-turning-on-copyright-abuses/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="movie copyright warning" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2007/09/movie-copyright-warning.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As reported on &lt;a href="http://www.groklaw.net/article.php?story=20070831145639691"&gt;Groklaw - Complaint Filed by CCIA with FTC Re
Fair Use&lt;/a&gt;, a
conglomerate of computer, technology and communication companies are
filing suit against major copyright holders such as movie studios,
sports leagues and publishers, to prevent them from continuing the
practice of misleading the public with their threatening copyright
notices. The nitty-gritty of the filing is that notices such as&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"WARNING: For private use only. Federal law provides severe civil and
criminal penalties for the unauthorized reproduction, distribution or
exhibition of copyrighted motion pictures and video formats."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;at the start of movies serves to intimidate the public from attempting
the many operations to which they are legally entitled, and even
encouraged, by US Federal laws and equivalents globally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Time to get on the bandwagon? Anyone else interested in conspicuously
taking photos of the copyright notice on the opening day of some
blockbuster movie, and when they come to eject us from the cinema, find
that we're handcuffed to our front row seats?&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>geek</category><category>imho</category><category>law</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/tide-turning-on-copyright-abuses/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 03 Sep 2007 03:03:59 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>