<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>tartley.com (Posts about lessig)</title><link>https://tartley.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://www.tartley.com/categories/lessig.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2022 &lt;a href="mailto:tartley @ the domain tartley dot com"&gt;Jonathan Hartley&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 14 Jan 2022 21:16:37 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>[SOLVED]UK Digital Economy Bill</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/solveduk-digital-economy-bill/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;So my splendid talented intelligent handsome friend Robert (who is also
my boss, of sorts) today shared this smashing post:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://gizmodo.com/5417318/my-6247-royalty-statement-how-major-labels-cook-the-books-with-digital-downloads"&gt;My \$62.47 Royalty Statement: How Major Labels Cook the Books with
Digital
Downloads&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;About one aspect of how artists get ripped off by the labels. It's not
required reading, but you can if you like. I'll wait.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hey. So it made me realise that a very possible fix to the dreadful
abuse of artists by the labels is possible. Even better, the solution to
this appalling situation is also the solution to the dire problems with
the UK's Digital Economy Bill.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So the UK govt. are debating a new bill, part of which introduces
measures to ruthlessly pursue illegal downloaders. There are some
problems with this, namely that:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;someone (probably the ISPs) will have to monitor what everyone
    downloads, and report people downloading anything that trips their
    filters for 'copyrighted work'. Understandably, they don't want to
    do this.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It will cost lots to implement - currently estimated at 100
    million, but of course the ensuing arms race with encrypted
    downloads will inflate that. Has anyone compared this with the
    &lt;em&gt;actual&lt;/em&gt; economic losses that it is aiming to fix? (not just the
    inflated ones self-reported by those with most to gain.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is literally impossible to automatically detect breach of
    copyright accurately - it can't be done just by looking at the bits.
    There will be lots of false positives and false negatives.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It will be easy to get around, using encryption or similar
    technologies to evade detection. It will not fix the problem it aims
    to fix.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It requires representatives of the state to intrusively monitor
    every single thing we do online.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The false positives will target and punish many innocent people,
    who have no way to demonstrate their innocence.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Perhaps worst of all, its presumption of guilt will have a chilling
    effect on many legal and morally justifiable uses of the internet,
    including business models of the present and the future.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They are talking about disconnection from the internet as a
    potential punitive measure for persistent downloaders. Most internet
    connections are shared by several people, and many of us use each
    other's connections all the time. Disconnecting one person for
    something that someone else downloaded is flagrantly wrong, and
    without wishing to be melodramatic, collective punishment like this
    is, strictly speaking, in breach of article 33 of the Geneva
    Convention. Plus it makes free wi-fi impossible to provide. Are we
    meant to be &lt;em&gt;destroying&lt;/em&gt; the digital economy?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If your country doesn't have a Bill like this, rest assured, it soon
will have.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyhow, it's clear to me that there's no use in railing against the Bill
unless one has an alternative to offer. The debate in the House of Lords
yesterday made it clear that the mood there is that millions are
flouting the law with illegal downloads to rip off artists and Something
Must Be Done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what's the alternative? The solution is the final chapter from
Stanford Law Prof. Lawrence Lessig's book '&lt;a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/Free-Culture-Nature-Future-Creativity/dp/0143034650"&gt;Free
Culture&lt;/a&gt;',
that describes how to fix the whole copyright mess in such a way that
will make everybody happy. Artists will get paid in abundance, very
fairly, in a market-driven way, and the payment will be direct to them.
The labels will be eliminated from the loop. No state monitoring of what
people download will be required. Everybody will be able to continue to
download whatever they like from wherever they like, for free (at point
of use), legally and with clear conscience. Best of all, the creation of
new business models and grass-roots creativity such as songs and other
content will be stimulated through the roof. Whichever country first
introduced this would lead the world in a creative tidal wave that
embraces the powers of the internet, rather than fighting against them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm not going to write what the copyright fix is here. I have to go to
work and I'm still in my pajamas. Oh alright, here's the quick quick
version. We add a tax to every high bandwidth internet connection. The
money goes in a pot. Then a central agency samples how many of each
creative work is being downloaded. This is just a sample - it needn't be
tied to any individual downloader, so it is cheap to do and unintrusive.
Then we distribute the money in the pot to artists, in proportion to the
number of downloads they had.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This quick version has some holes in it. Prof. Lessig ties it all up in
his book. Yes it has some problems - taxes are never popular, and more
expensive internet connections are not what we want. But these problems
are small and soluble, compared to what is currently being discussed
instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know this is so starry-eyed idealistic that it has no chance of being
seriously discussed. But I decided last night that I have to at least
give it a try.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Readers from the UK - Do YOU have even the slightest inkling of
interest in suggesting this to your own MP? Or at least pointing out the
downsides of the current Bill? It would just be one evening out of your
life. I'm visiting mine this weekend. Email me if you have any interest
at all. I can lead you through the process, it's simple.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>geek</category><category>imho</category><category>lessig</category><category>python</category><category>software</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/solveduk-digital-economy-bill/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 03 Dec 2009 16:04:59 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Remix</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/remix/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left; padding: 1em"&gt;
&lt;img alt="remix" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2009/04/remix.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Lawrence Lessig&lt;/em&gt;, 2008.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is creating a mix CD for a friend an act of creativity, or a criminal
offence? When you shoot a home video of your child which has a TV on in
the background, is there really any need for lawsuits? What business do
federal laws have in trying to regulate this sort of activity anyway?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those, like me, who view modern copyright law as a morass of
intractable problems, irreconcilable interests, overreaching government
intervention and profoundly unfair restrictions on personal freedoms,
Professor Lessig's words are a welcome infusion of clarity, pragmatism
and respect for all interested parties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With an engaging and accessible style, he describes exactly what is
wrong with modern copyright, with clarity and impartiality, and why this
is a deep and pervasive problem that cuts to the heart of all that we
value in human culture. He describes how fixing this would benefit each
of us, from individual consumers and amateur producers, through
professional writers, musicians and copyright holders. Then, in a
surprisingly constructive final section, he outlines five simple changes
to copyright law that would, at a stroke, fix all the major problems,
vastly simplify the situation, eliminate the ambiguity over the legality
of our everyday actions, and all without apparently causing any harm or
loss to any interested party.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rating:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;10/10 If you have any interest in the forces that are reshaping our
society and turning industries upside-down within the space of years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;0/10 If you dislike freedom or free markets, or are a big fan of
overbearing government regulation and monopolies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: both"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>culture</category><category>internet</category><category>law</category><category>lessig</category><category>media</category><category>non-fiction</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/remix/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 08 Apr 2009 04:42:58 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Free Culture</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/free-culture/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Free Culture" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2008/02/free-culture.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Lawrence Lessig (2004)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Accessible, entertaining, rich with historical perspective, and cuts
incisively to the core of modern society's conflict over intellectual
property. To my mind, one of the most important books of the decade. I'd
highly recommend it. And it's available for free from your iPhone's
built-in ebooks installer, or
&lt;a href="http://www.free-culture.cc/freecontent/"&gt;as a pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rating: 10/10. Blimey.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: both"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>culture</category><category>internet</category><category>law</category><category>lessig</category><category>media</category><category>non-fiction</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/free-culture/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 25 Feb 2008 20:08:18 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>