<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>tartley.com (Posts about mental-health)</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://www.tartley.com/categories/mental-health.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2021 &lt;a href="mailto:tartley @ the domain tartley dot com"&gt;Jonathan Hartley&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 18 May 2021 20:48:51 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Balloon Therapy</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/balloon-therapy/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2008/09/balloon.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Ivan Idso&lt;/em&gt;, 2007.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A disclaimer, to begin - the author is my new-to-me brother in law, so I
got a copy at cost, inscribed 'soft aardvarks' (I think), and a few
weeks later got a once-in-a-lifetime experience of being taken on a
balloon ride by the man himself. So the write-up is going to be a
glowing one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, I don't have to stretch the truth at all in order to do so.
It's a short and lightweight read, which does explain the mechanics and
practicalities of hot-air ballooning. However, the focus of the book is
on the social aspects, and the effect it has had on the life and
disposition of Ivan, his family and friends. As a result, it's a
thoroughly personal and heart-warming read, engrossing and explanatory
and fulfilling throughout, that left me feeling closer to the author,
and with more of an understanding of him and his lifestyle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: both"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>books</category><category>media</category><category>mental-health</category><category>non-fiction</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/balloon-therapy/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2008 02:44:50 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Broken Open: How Difficult Times Can Help Us Grow</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/broken-open-how-difficult-times-can-help-us-grow/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Broken Open" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2007/03/broken-open.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Elizabeth Lesser (2004)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's the sort of nancy self-help psychobabble that would normally earn a
derisive snort from my direction, but the onset of middle-age is
broadening my horizons and dimming my discernment, so here I am, led to
it by the memories of difficult times in my own life, now sufficiently
distant for me to re-examine them, ponder how they changed me, and
wonder how I could have better handled both my contributions and
reactions to them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be sure, the author is at times a good deal more spiritual and
mystical than I have any taste for - her visit to a trailer-park psychic
may have been a revelationary and life-changing experience for her, but
despite the poetic appeal of the events therein, it wasn't for me, and
the specifics of the event would best have been omitted in trying to win
me over.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But having said that, with a little patience, I found a great deal of
value to be teased out of the other chapters. The overarching theme is
undeniable: that we fill our lives with superficial distractions, in our
efforts to keep up appearances, by design, we never have time or energy
left over for the difficult and unpleasant tasks of serious
introspection, of admitting and addressing our own flaws, or of
providing the openness and honesty needed by those close to us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even when jolted out of our habitual routine by a painful external
stimulus, such as personal injury or bereavement, in the hours or years
of soul-searching that follow, it is all too easy to remain wrapped up
in grief, anger or arrogance. But sometimes, in the depths of those dark
times, people learn how to overcome their own ego, and discern what is
truly important in their lives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It sounds like a relentless downer, and it does indeed contain tales of
woe, but each story told within contains a message of hope. Pretences
drop, acceptance begins and honesty prevails. There are powerful lessons
in both self-awareness and humility to be learned here, and I'm glad it
found me when it did.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rating: 6/10&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alright, can I turn the smartalec cynicism back on now?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: both"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>books</category><category>media</category><category>mental-health</category><category>non-fiction</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/broken-open-how-difficult-times-can-help-us-grow/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Mar 2007 18:11:38 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>