<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>tartley.com (Posts about mental-health)</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://www.tartley.com/categories/mental-health.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2022 &lt;a href="mailto:tartley @ the domain tartley dot com"&gt;Jonathan Hartley&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 19 Sep 2022 15:37:50 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Infinite Jest</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/infinite-jest/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Inifinite Jest" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2009/02/infinitejest.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by David Foster Wallace (1996)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've had such a diverse set of reactions to this, and how could I not?
The writing is bold and idiosyncratic throughout. The novel's story is
not presented in chronological order, and the timeline is obfuscated by
the gleeful adoption of 'subsidised time', in which traditional numeric
monikers denoting each calender year are replaced by the sponsored
labels designated by major corporations - 'Year of the Whopper', and so
on - a marvellous concept which nevertheless makes it completely and
artificially impossible to tell what the hell's going on until about 500
pages in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The whole novel unashamedly celebrates the author's literary and formal
grammatical credentials - from the extraordinarily-crafted opening
scene, where a tragically misunderstood literary genius disastrously
fails a university entrance interview, with just a hint of a
semi-autobiographical air about him. Scenes of superlative execution are
interspersed with a narrative that is, on the whole, told in the third
person but in the argot of the currently eminent protagonist, leading to
large swathes of the book which are, like, more than conversational in
their familiarity. The combination gives rise to a relentlessly
inventive stream of neology and malapropism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the book resoundingly makes many insightful points by the conclusion, the
story which serves as a vehicle for their delivery is, a collision of ideas,
introducing entirely new and unexplored premises at the 11th hour, which
peter out, ignored and unresolved, by the final page. The jest continues
on, I suppose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The insidious footnotes for which Wallace's writings are well-known do
not serve to streamline the prose by separating out incidental
annotations, but instead seem specifically employed to elevate the
reader's awareness of the footnotes themselves. Including them in the
main body of the text would allow for the possibility of a busy reader
failing to give each pithy addendum it's full, weighty consideration.
Wallace cunningly obviates this possibility, by discreetly giving pause
to any reader assiduously trying to do their best with a challenging
book, requiring them to invoke the titillating ritual of thumbing
forward a literal thousand pages or so, giving an involuntary moment of
rest in the narrative in which the reader may properly anticipate the
mysterious text to be revealed while they dereference the footnote's
numeric identifier, and then a second pause afterwards to properly
digest and appreciate, while they thumb a literal thousand pages back
again to find where they left off. Three hundred and eighty eight times,
no less. Plus sub-footnotes, obviously. Some of these are pages-long
tomes of critically insightful dialog between major characters. Many
others are completely irrelevant technical specifications. I have to
ask, what the fuck is going on here? Does this really make the novel
somehow better? While I laughed and cried about the content of many of
the footnotes, I remain unconvinced by the mechanism of their delivery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I rant about these aspects of style because these are definitely the
first impressions any reader will have. Getting into the book &lt;a href="http://kottke.org/09/03/growing-sentences-with-david-foster-wallace"&gt;does
require a little
work&lt;/a&gt;.
But fortunately Wallace more than provides the incentive to do so. The
book ranges over many areas, but is mostly about addiction, in its many
forms, and its relationship to freedom of will and to happiness. These
are deep and interesting topics, and are unflinchingly explored with a
very keen eye. For every one of the annoyances mentioned above, the book
provides powerful rewards for those who stick it out. The
heart-wrenching depictions of people going through the utter destruction
of their humanity are as touching and insightful as anything I have
read.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are some problems or tasks in life which are small enough that an
individual can overcome them by force of will, grinding down the problem
until it is flattened and overcome. This approach fails, however, when
the problem is too large or too hard. Some problems cannot be crushed by
any individual. To navigate past them requires that, instead of trying
to demolish the problem, the individual must instead mould themselves to
fit around the problem's existing contours. People emerge on the other
side of these experiences triumphant but sober - having been changed to
their core by the experience. I consider &lt;em&gt;Infinite Jest&lt;/em&gt; to belong to
this latter class of experience. From the base-camp of its 981 pages
(plus 98 of footnotes), it is intimidating and uncompromising. You love
it and hate it in equal measure, and it makes no attempt to pander to
the former. But as I ploughed on, through it, week after week after
week, I grew to enjoy it more and more and more. I began to see
reminders of it everywhere I looked. I spotted echoes of its style in
the speech of friends who are fans of Wallace. It began, very subtly, to
infect my own speech and writing. The topics it covered touched me to
the core, changing my outlook on deep issues such as religion. By the
time I reached the very last page I emerged, bruised and weary, but also
tremendously excited - I actually flipped it right back and re-read the
first few chapters all over again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now for perhaps the greatest test to date of my supposedly
subjectivity-proof rating system. Here goes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rating:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;10/10: If you are ready for a challenge, that entertains and wrenches in
equal measure, stretching you, changing your definitions, taking you on
a tour of regions you never knew existed. It will make you laugh and it
will make you cry. It will leave you a different person than when you
began.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;0/10: If you can't be bothered.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>drugs</category><category>fiction</category><category>media</category><category>mental-health</category><category>novel</category><category>wallace</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/infinite-jest/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 28 Mar 2009 21:26:49 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Balloon Therapy</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/balloon-therapy/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2008/09/balloon.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Ivan Idso&lt;/em&gt;, 2007.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A disclaimer, to begin - the author is my new-to-me brother in law, so I
got a copy at cost, inscribed 'soft aardvarks' (I think), and a few
weeks later got a once-in-a-lifetime experience of being taken on a
balloon ride by the man himself. So the write-up is going to be a
glowing one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, I don't have to stretch the truth at all in order to do so.
It's a short and lightweight read, which does explain the mechanics and
practicalities of hot-air ballooning. However, the focus of the book is
on the social aspects, and the effect it has had on the life and
disposition of Ivan, his family and friends. As a result, it's a
thoroughly personal and heart-warming read, engrossing and explanatory
and fulfilling throughout, that left me feeling closer to the author,
and with more of an understanding of him and his lifestyle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: both"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>media</category><category>mental-health</category><category>non-fiction</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/balloon-therapy/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2008 02:44:50 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Breakfast of Champions</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/breakfast-of-champions/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2008/08/breakfast-of-champions.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Kurt Vonnegut (1973)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;po
I've always loved Vonnegut (who doesn't?) but I'd avoided this since
seeing the &lt;a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0120618/"&gt;painful 1999 movie&lt;/a&gt;
made of it, proof if ever it were needed that some books are simply
unfilmable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The novel, however, is everything we love about Vonnegut. His clarity,
wit, grumpiness and simplicity. The story of ordinary people in a small
midwestern town reads like a playful Hemmingway, but forms a therapeutic
rumination on the nature of sanity, and the author's own relationship
with it, in the insane world we find ourselves in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rating: 7/10 - and so on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: both"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>fiction</category><category>media</category><category>mental-health</category><category>novel</category><category>vonnegut</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/breakfast-of-champions/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 27 Aug 2008 20:45:56 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>From Hell</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/from-hell/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="From Hell" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2007/07/fromhellsm.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Alan Moore (author), Eddie Campbell (artist) (1989)&lt;/em&gt; &lt;img alt="spoilers" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/spoilers.svg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moore has almost single-handedly transformed the definition of the comic
industry in the last 20 years, and this fetishistically researched
comic-book dramatisation of the dark and macabre Jack the Ripper murders
is no exception to his visionary high standards. Moore plunges headlong
into the sensational conspiracy theory that Royal Physician, Dr. William
Gull, killed East End prostitutes to silence the story of an
illegitimate royal baby, under the direct orders of the implacable Queen
Victoria herself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr Gull regards his mission as the great work of his life, which will
not only quash the threat to the crown, but also fulfil ancient pagan
destinies, reasserting the male dominance over matriarchy that began
when the Romans reclaimed London and slew Queen Boadicea. Gull knows
this because he has knelt before his God, who told him just what needed
to be done. As a doctor, Gull knows that these visions are madness,
brought about by his stroke of the previous year. As a man, however, he
responds that "If this is madness, who'd be sane?", and, embracing the
subjective reality of his hallucinations, he goes about his work with
gusto, confiding along the way in his witless coachman and reluctant
accomplice, Nettley.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Dr Gull and coachman Nettley" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2007/07/boadicea-died-sm.jpg" title="Dr. Gull &amp;amp; coachman Nettley"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The story is a tapestry, woven on many levels. The iniquities of wealth
and power are richly depicted as the poverty-stricken residents of the
East End are contrasted with the powers-that-be, who move swiftly and
decisively to ensure that Gull is never caught nor found out, for fear
of scandal, even while he goes on killing with impunity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The appalling violence of the murders and dismemberment of the victims
is shown in unflinching detail, one pivotal 34-page chapter "The Best of
all Tailors", consisting solely of the actions of Gull, a renowned
surgeon, with his victim in a tiny, squalid room, which made me
profoundly grateful that the sketches are only in black-and-white.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Such graphic nastiness is not for no reason. Gull is convinced that the
act of violence is a pivotal part of the ancient and grisly prophesies
he is enacting. Under the psychological strain of each successive
murder, Gull experiences increasingly vivid hallucinations, symptoms of
his condition. But then, something altogether strange starts to happen.
As his visions become more vivid, Gull begins to experience glimpses of
the future. Visions of our time. At times and places where people have
historically claimed to have seen the ghost of Jack the Ripper, Moore
cunningly reverses the perspective, allowing Gull to see them also. By
the end, Gull's visions have him stalking the sterile hallways of the
modern world in blood-soaked shirtsleeves, roaring at oblivious office
workers, exhorting them to look up and remember the history from which
our century was birthed in blood. The ancient magic that Gull raved
about was real, while we have lost our connection to our violent and
animal past, and with it, our very humanity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Nettley's coach - harbinger of doom." src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2007/07/coach-sm.png" title="Nettley's coach - harbinger of doom."&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rating: 10/10.
Cor blimey it's a classic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: both"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>comic</category><category>fiction</category><category>media</category><category>mental-health</category><category>moore</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/from-hell/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 22 Jul 2007 03:34:22 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Broken Open: How Difficult Times Can Help Us Grow</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/broken-open-how-difficult-times-can-help-us-grow/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Broken Open" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2007/03/broken-open.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Elizabeth Lesser (2004)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's the sort of nancy self-help psychobabble that would normally earn a
derisive snort from my direction, but the onset of middle-age is
broadening my horizons and dimming my discernment, so here I am, led to
it by the memories of difficult times in my own life, now sufficiently
distant for me to re-examine them, ponder how they changed me, and
wonder how I could have better handled both my contributions and
reactions to them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be sure, the author is at times a good deal more spiritual and
mystical than I have any taste for - her visit to a trailer-park psychic
may have been a revelationary and life-changing experience for her, but
despite the poetic appeal of the events therein, it wasn't for me, and
the specifics of the event would best have been omitted in trying to win
me over.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But having said that, with a little patience, I found a great deal of
value to be teased out of the other chapters. The overarching theme is
undeniable: that we fill our lives with superficial distractions, in our
efforts to keep up appearances, by design, we never have time or energy
left over for the difficult and unpleasant tasks of serious
introspection, of admitting and addressing our own flaws, or of
providing the openness and honesty needed by those close to us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even when jolted out of our habitual routine by a painful external
stimulus, such as personal injury or bereavement, in the hours or years
of soul-searching that follow, it is all too easy to remain wrapped up
in grief, anger or arrogance. But sometimes, in the depths of those dark
times, people learn how to overcome their own ego, and discern what is
truly important in their lives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It sounds like a relentless downer, and it does indeed contain tales of
woe, but each story told within contains a message of hope. Pretences
drop, acceptance begins and honesty prevails. There are powerful lessons
in both self-awareness and humility to be learned here, and I'm glad it
found me when it did.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rating: 6/10&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alright, can I turn the smartalec cynicism back on now?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: both"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>media</category><category>mental-health</category><category>non-fiction</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/broken-open-how-difficult-times-can-help-us-grow/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Mar 2007 18:11:38 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>