<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>tartley.com (Posts about movie)</title><link>https://tartley.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://www.tartley.com/categories/movie.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2022 &lt;a href="mailto:tartley @ the domain tartley dot com"&gt;Jonathan Hartley&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 06 Jan 2022 18:13:10 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Cloverfield (2008)</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/cloverfield-2008/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Cloverfield cover" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2009/04/cloverfield.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Against my better
judgement I couldn't help but snag a torrent of this. Sure enough, as
the opening credits kicked in, my housemates assured us it was rubbish.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But then what happened is that I proceeded to love it. Clearly it
polarises. The whole thing is shot in a shaky handicam held by one of
the characters - imagine Blair Witch meets 9/11, only it isn't
terrorists, it's a giant, evil &lt;em&gt;whatthefuckisthat&lt;/em&gt; stalking the streets
of NYC. It reminds me of
&lt;a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0390384/"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Primer&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, in which the script is
so realistic and lacking in over-ripe gravitas that, unusually, the
actors don't even look like they are acting! What a concept. Well this
is similar - albeit a lot dumber - but the strength is not in the
script, which isn't especially strong, but is in the novel method of
presentation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's clearly a limited number of movies that could be made like this,
but for me, it was a welcome respite from the staged set-pieces of
Hollywood's more conventional output. The sense of panic and confusion
was beautifully heightened by the total lack of exposition - viewers
only get to see what this small group of characters get to see, and even
that is in blurry and imperfect fragmetary snatches. The monster, when
it is even visible, is only glimpsed from afar. It was the closest a
movie has ever come to creating the kind of tense, terrifying immersion
that really great computer games can create.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was amused to note that a bridge they take shelter under at the end
looks exactly like the bridge they took shelter under at the end of The
Day The Earth Stood Still (2008) - do all the bridges in Central Park
look the same, or does this one have some special meaning? Anyhow, the
final scene is saddening and telegraphed quite plainly from the opening
shot (&lt;em&gt;Camera retrieved at incident site US 447. Area formerly known as
"Central Park"&lt;/em&gt;) and it makes me weep with relief that a movie could so
willing try and break the mold.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rating:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;0/10 if you're not into monster flicks, or if handycam footage makes you
vomit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;10/10 If you fancy being scared silly by a giant alien monster.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: both;"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>fiction</category><category>media</category><category>movie</category><category>science-fiction</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/cloverfield-2008/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 30 Apr 2009 13:15:58 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Day The Earth Stood Still</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/the-day-the-earth-stood-still/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="2008" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2009/04/day-the-earth-stood-still-2008.jpg"&gt; &lt;img alt="1951" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2009/04/day-the-earth-stood-still-1951.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Earth obligingly stood still for us twice this week, on back-to-back
nights. In each, a lone alien man arrives in a spaceship with his giant
robot buddy Gort, to tell humans that they must mend their destructive
ways or be destroyed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 1951 version was very Fifties - intrusively hopeless special
effects, and seems to my eyes to be riddled with outlandish social
etiquette and hopelessly naive politics. I suppose in the years
following World War II any platform for preaching pacifism seemed worth
a shot. If only more people considered it worth preaching today. I
completely missed the Christian allegory that permeates the movie until
it was pointed out to me: The alien comes from the heavens, and lives
amongst common people, taking the name 'Carpenter' to blend in. He
preaches peace to humankind, or else warns we will suffer a fiery
apocalypse. He is our intermediary to 'Gort' (in fact the servant of
Gort, in the original script) who later resurrects him from the dead, so
that he may deliver his final message before being taken back up into
the skies. Cute if you're into that, I guess.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Equally predictably, the 2008 version was very Naughties. Intrusively
overblown production values string together a mediochre script. The
pacifism and Christian message of the original has been replaced with a
more timely environmental message - the writers perhaps intuiting that
modern Americans are not so receptive to anti-war talk. Otherwise the
scope and potential of the ideas at play are completely wasted - lost
amidst the creative wasteland of a budget that could no doubt have fed
countries. Once provoked, Gort unleashes self-replicating insectile
microbots, which swarm and consume Philly, spreading fast. At the last
moment, Keanu / Klaatu sees some humans hugging and crying, and has a
big change of heart - the Earth deserves to be spared, after all. What a
crock.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So there you have it. Watch this space for more reviews from me -
wasting nights of my life, so that you don't have to. Final ratings:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;10/10 if you are a stump-sucking mealy-mouthed pig-dog with googly eyes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;0/10 if you have any vestigial glimmers of taste or discernment.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>fiction</category><category>media</category><category>movie</category><category>science-fiction</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/the-day-the-earth-stood-still/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 30 Apr 2009 03:17:24 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Fargo</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/fargo/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Directed: The Coen Brothers, 1996.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some brilliant performances, some lovely moments. Emminently watchable.
Interesting point, I don't know about Fargo itself, or The Dakotas, but
the fine residents of Minnesota will insist that they neither sound or
act like the depicted characters, which is of course absolutely
charming. (love you guys! :-)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>fiction</category><category>media</category><category>movie</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/fargo/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2009 23:09:56 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Wall-E</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/wall-e/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="wall-e" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2009/01/wall-e.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Director: Andrew Stanton&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I resisted for quite a while, expecting cloying superficiality. I was
wrong. Or at least I &lt;em&gt;like&lt;/em&gt; this kind of cloying superficiality. Clearly
made with love by a truly dedicated army of master artisans. Featuring
sound effects from the same guru sound guy who worked on the original
Star Wars, along with an animation team who watched every single Buster
Keaton and Charlie Chaplin movie over their lunchtimes, to inspire them
in the ways of visual story telling. With a hardcore &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/General_Products_(Larry_Niven)#General_Products_Hull"&gt;Larry
Niven&lt;/a&gt;
reference and a serious environmental message in the background to boot.
Huge fun. I watched it twice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rating: 8/10 - Thoroughly engaging, emotive and humorous.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>animation</category><category>fiction</category><category>media</category><category>movie</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/wall-e/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2009 05:39:38 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Scarface</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/scarface/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2008/10/scarfacepacino.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Director: Brian de Palma (1983)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oh, I don't know, my expectations were too high or something. I expected
an intense study of greed, corruption and criminal will. Maybe I'm
desensitized. All I found was that it frequently descends into simply
camp 1970s gunfight scenes. Amusing to note the influences it has had on
other media, particularly the mansion in &lt;em&gt;Grand Theft Auto: Vice City&lt;/em&gt;.
I couldn't find much else to commend it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: both"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>fiction</category><category>media</category><category>movie</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/scarface/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 02 Oct 2008 03:11:01 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Simpsons Movie / Goodbye Forever</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/the-simpsons-movie-goodbye-forever/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="The Simpsons Movie" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2008/05/simpsonsmovie.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is, of course,
no point whatsoever in me posting a belated review of the Simpsons
Movie, which I and everyone else gleefully watched many months ago now.
To the now long abandoned discussions of its merit I have absolutely
nothing of value to contribute.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, that shall not dissuade me from posting this one anyway, since
such posts as these are not, as you might assume, for the benefit of my
readership, few and benighted as they might be, but instead form an
attempt to chart my media consumption habits for my own retrospective
perusal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was with some dismay, therefore, that I noted that this inverted
system of priorities is mirrored in the Herculean task of my reading of
other people's posts. Simply put, I seem to be reading other people's
blogs in order to make them feel good, upping their stats, making
complimentary comments, showing an interest, etc, etc, rather than for
my own benefit. Once this cold fact had impinged upon my conciousness, I
had only one course of action left open: Cold Turkey. That's right. No
more Google Reader.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abandoning the hampster wheel should free up a considerable amount of my
time for other activities, and I am keen to quantify that process, so I
will be keeping detailed logs of my time usage for a few days prior and
post the switchover, to ascertain exactly how many hours I previously
spent looking at labelled pictures of cats, which I will henceforth
presumably be free to spend looking at &lt;em&gt;actual&lt;/em&gt; labels on cats (or
possibly labels on &lt;em&gt;actual&lt;/em&gt; pictures of cats, let's not get overly
ambitious.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a final layer of delicious irony, I shall of course be blogging
comprehensively about the entire experience, however your collective
reactions to that will remain forever unknown to me. Henceforth you
should consider me to be a purely one-way conduit of information.
Goodbye forever.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: both"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>imho</category><category>media</category><category>movie</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/the-simpsons-movie-goodbye-forever/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 08 May 2008 17:48:12 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Lions for Lambs</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/lions-for-lambs/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Lions for Lambs" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2008/03/lions-for-lambs.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It got a right drubbing critically, and was a box-office failure, but I
found it powerful and compelling. It may not be crafted with the
greatest finesse, but nevertheless it raises interesting and powerful
questions, of the competence of our leaders in war, of the culpability
of the media in towing the line, and of the personal responsibility that
falls to each of us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most Americans seem unaware that their &lt;a href="http://www.moblogic.tv/video/2008/03/10/whos-got-the-guns-2/"&gt;profligate spending on
'defence'&lt;/a&gt;,
coupled with regular invasions of other countries, cause them to be
regarded by much of the rest of the world as the single biggest threat
to world peace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In such an environment, this movie asks us to have the bravery to let
our point of view be known, and to take action when our beliefs
contradict our Goverments' decision to go to war. For anyone with
questions about the justification for the recent wars that America has
started (and my own country England has supported) this movie raises
many issues, and spoke powerfully to my conscience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rating 8/10.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>fiction</category><category>media</category><category>movie</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/lions-for-lambs/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 20 Mar 2008 04:15:18 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>I am Legend</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/i-am-legend/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="I am Legend" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2008/02/i-am-legend.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Directed by Francis Lawrence.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Summary&lt;/strong&gt;
This is going to be one of those reviews where someone reads the book
and then sees the movie and doesn't like it very much.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Details&lt;/strong&gt;
I read &lt;em&gt;Robinson Crusoe&lt;/em&gt; for the first time when I was about 30. It
forms such a prominent thread within our cultural milieu that I expected
it to be a pinnacle of literature, well-written and evocative. For me,
however, it was nothing of the sort. It seemed to have been lazily
dashed off by a nitwit aristocrat who'd never faced a single day of
hardship in his life, with no thought at all given to the physical and
psychological trials someone in Crusoe's predicament would suffer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Only weeks later, I read Richard Matheson's novel &lt;em&gt;I am Legend&lt;/em&gt;, and
unexpectedly found it to be nigh on exactly the study of loneliness and
despair that I had expected &lt;em&gt;Crusoe&lt;/em&gt; would be. The portrayal of frantic
days spent repairing the fortifications, alternating with horrific
sleepless nights spent indoors, listening to &lt;em&gt;them&lt;/em&gt; trying to get in, is
as dense an atmosphere of desperation as I think I've ever been party
to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So it was with conflicting pangs of emotion that I first heard about the
movie. In many ways the movie's strength is simply the inevitable
reaction one has to the depiction of a desolate New York City. Will
Smith's character is now a world-class scientist, bent on reversing the
ravages of the zombie/vampire plague single-handed, working from his
Hollywood-style basement laboratory. The novel's pivotal ending - from
which the title is derived - is utterly transformed into something
rather jolly and upbeat. Even the signs of him fraying around the edges
under the strain have been sanitised - he talks to mannequins, rather
than drinking himself into oblivion. It's &lt;em&gt;Robinson Crusoe&lt;/em&gt; all over
again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rating: 5/10 - not great.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: both"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>media</category><category>movie</category><category>science-fiction</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/i-am-legend/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 08 Feb 2008 06:45:21 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Straight Story</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/the-straight-story/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="The Straight Story" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2007/07/thestraightstory.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by David Lynch (1999)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aw, heck, I dunno. It's kinda down to Earth and charming, but also plain
and slow-moving. And sure, that was deliberate, it wanted to tell a
simple, powerful story in the terms of its protagonists, within the
context of rural life. But I couldn't really get into it, despite really
wanting to. Some of the acting was a bit lacking. IMDB informs me that
it's a true story. Fair enough. It's still 4/10.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: both"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>dramatization</category><category>media</category><category>movie</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/the-straight-story/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 22 Jul 2007 05:40:15 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Ocean's 13</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/oceans13/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Don Cheadle in Ocean's 13" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2007/07/oceans13.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Directed by Steven Soderbergh&lt;/em&gt; (2007)
&lt;a href="http://imdb.com/title/tt0496806/"&gt;imdb&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I really, really loved 12, despite the Mockney accent. I thought the
script was just immaculate. I think I'm in a minority on that. Anyhow, I
really hated this one, with its witless Godfather references. Rubbish
all over. 3/10.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: both"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>fiction</category><category>media</category><category>movie</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/oceans13/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 22 Jul 2007 05:33:56 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>