<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>tartley.com (Posts about music)</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://www.tartley.com/categories/music.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2021 &lt;a href="mailto:tartley @ the domain tartley dot com"&gt;Jonathan Hartley&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 13 May 2021 16:29:19 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>TIL: Create mp3 from YouTube video</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/til-create-mp3-from-youtube-video/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Install &lt;code&gt;youtube-dl&lt;/code&gt;, a tool to download YouTube videos. Using &lt;code&gt;apt&lt;/code&gt; installs a
version that's too old to work, so:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;pipsi install youtube-dl
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Download the video from YouTube:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;youtube-dl https://www.youtube.com/watch?v&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;nyU1Pt2IXyE
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This results in a webm file. I have no idea what that is, and am relieved
to discover that converting it into an mp3 requires just:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;ffmpeg -I MyVideoFile.webm -vn MyAudioFile.mp3
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where &lt;code&gt;-vn&lt;/code&gt; disables video in the output.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>music</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/til-create-mp3-from-youtube-video/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 13 May 2021 16:18:33 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>My Cacophony</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/my-cacaphony/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Google Calendar tells me that I've now had 8 piano lessons with the
esteemed Marios. It's been heaps of fun, and it's long past time I
shared my progress to date, in the form of some ghastly midi files.
Download at your peril, they are truly awful - only of interest as a
record of my progress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Beautiful Brown Eyes&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, a tune labelled as 'Beautiful Brown Eyes'. This is from a couple
of weeks ago, the first time I managed to record a midi file. The
timing's very sloppy - I haven't been learning any pieces by heart, so
I'm struggling to read the music fast enough to play the tune. I'm
trying to play as many different pieces as I can by reading the sheet
music, rather than learning a few by heart, since that will hopefully
exercise my ability to read music, albeit at the cost of sounding much
less polished for the time being. That's my excuse and I'm sticking to
it!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.tartley.com/files/2007/07/07-06-28-beautiful-brown-eyes.mid" title="Beautiful Brown Eyes, 2007-06-28"&gt;&lt;img alt="MIDI icon" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2007/07/midifile.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
28 Jun&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Alpine Melody&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next up, an even simpler tune, which means I have less difficulty
reading the music and so the timing's a bit better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.tartley.com/files/2007/07/07-07-16-alpine-melody.mid" title="Alpine Melody, 2007-07-16"&gt;&lt;img alt="MIDI icon" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2007/07/midifile.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
16 Jul&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Tetris&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, the music from the computer game Tetris. This is a fairly new
tune to me, and it's obvious that it's a real struggle. I'm not used to
reading such large melodic intervals, and the notes extends over a
broader pitch range than anything I've done before, so I can scarcely
place my fingers on the right keys, never mind in time. Hopefully this
will get better with practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.tartley.com/files/2007/07/07-07-16-tetris-terrible-struggle.mid" title="Tetris, 2007-07-16"&gt;&lt;img alt="MIDI icon" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2007/07/midifile.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
16 Jul&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.tartley.com/files/2007/07/tetris-07-07-21-better.mid" title="Tetris, 2007-07-21"&gt;&lt;img alt="MIDI icon" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2007/07/midifile.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
21 Jul&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>music</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/my-cacaphony/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 17 Jul 2007 03:01:18 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Music 101¾</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/music-101c2be/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Writing music out by hand is incredibly laborious. Or at least, it is
for me. This is my first attempt to pen some notes by plonking around on
the keyboard until it sounds right. Doubtless errors of all kinds
abound, which I'd be much obliged if anyone pointed out to me, tar very
much.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2007/06/score-largo.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>music</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/music-101c2be/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 19 Jun 2007 03:23:47 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Music 101½</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/music-101c2bd/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;It's been said before by others, but I hadn't realised how insidious it
is: When musicians talk about 'theory', they actually mean 'notation'.
With reference to my &lt;a href="http://tartley.com/?p=100"&gt;previous whinging&lt;/a&gt;
about music notation, I notice that the &lt;a href="http://www.mnma.org/"&gt;Music Notation Modernization
Association&lt;/a&gt; are suggesting a number of revisions
to make notation more useful and consistent. One of the more prominent
suggestions is a change to the use of staves to make them compatible
with the octave-offset principle I mentioned earlier, thus making the
appearance of notes consistent across all staves, and making the use of
clefs of any kind redundant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The above idea especially comes into its own when combined with their
other proposals:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Chromatic staves&lt;/em&gt; to indicate intervals in a proportional manner
(rather than the current bonkers '♯' and '♭' notation)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="chromatic-intervals.gif" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2007/06/chromatic-intervals.gif"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Twinline&lt;/em&gt; staves, which only require two horizontal lines, rather
than the conventional five, provides a significant increase in
readability, in keeping with Tufte's principle of
&lt;a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/Visual-Display-Quantitative-Information/dp/0961392142/"&gt;maximising data-ink ratio&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="twinline.gif" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2007/06/twinline.gif"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note color&lt;/em&gt; or shape used to discriminate pitch, rather than the
current quirky use of partially indicating note length. This is
perhaps my favourite, as it massively increases the ease of rapidly
identifying notes on sight. Since note colour is currently used to
distinguish between a minim and a crotchet, then some other way of
making them distinct would have to be found. A unique flag on the
note stem would seem to suffice, and would be more in keeping with
the other note duration symbology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="note-color.gif" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2007/06/note-color.gif"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After what looks like years of painstaking brainstorming, research,
focus testing and refinement, the only thing left for the MNMA to do is
to decide on one single notation that unambiguously combines all the
above ideas, and promote its use with the aim of gradually supplanting
conventional notation. Unfortunately, this seems to be something they
have singularly failed to do. By failing to adopt and recommend a single
notation, they seem to be ensuring that none of their ideas will ever
gain any traction.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>music</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/music-101c2bd/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 11 Jun 2007 15:37:44 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Music 101</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/music-101/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Treble clef" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2007/05/treble-clef.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've been riding high on the sheer joy that is Guitar Hero II (PS2) recently.
Now that &lt;em&gt;Psychobilly Freakout&lt;/em&gt; is the only remaining song for which a
five-star review performance is still eluding me, before unleashing the
masochistically feverish &lt;em&gt;hard&lt;/em&gt; difficulty setting at least, it's time
for me to get my ass into gear and learn to play a &lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt; musical
instrument.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dithering
between piano / keyboard and acoustic / electric guitar, I've decided to
take a few week's lessons in each, to see which initially suits me best.
Accordingly (Speaking of which, I also find the accordion strangely
compelling), I had my first ever piano lesson this weekend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.mariostakoushis.com/html/about.php" title="Mr Marios Takoushis"&gt;&lt;img alt="Mr Marios Takoushis" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2007/05/marious.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My tutor,
&lt;a href="http://www.mariostakoushis.com/html/about.php"&gt;Marios&lt;/a&gt;, an amiable
Greek professional musician with appropriately mad hair, seems like a
brilliant choice thus far: I'm sure we'll get along famously, with only
the minimum amount of absolutely necessary knuckle-rapping.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update 14:35:&lt;/strong&gt; Just remembered: One of the first puzzling things I
discovered is that notes on the bass clef stave are offset from the
notes on the treble clef stave by a non-integer number of octaves.
Hence, a note which would represent 'C' on a treble clef stave is
actually an 'E' when drawn on a bass clef stave. Presumably there's a
reason for this, but I've yet to hear an explanation that sounds like
anything other than a wart on the notation. Can any of my multitudinous
readers enlighten me?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>journal</category><category>music</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/music-101/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 14 May 2007 15:37:21 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>