<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>tartley.com (Posts about novel)</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://www.tartley.com/categories/novel.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2021 &lt;a href="mailto:tartley @ the domain tartley dot com"&gt;Jonathan Hartley&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 17 May 2021 23:21:57 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Ra, by qntm</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/ra-by-qntm/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2021/ra-by-qntm-cover.jpg" style="float: left; padding-right: 1em"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I bought all four of &lt;a href="https://qntm.org/fiction"&gt;qntm's books&lt;/a&gt;
when I discovered the fantastic
&lt;a href="https://www.tartley.com/posts/there-is-no-antimemetics-division/"&gt;There is no Antimemetics Division&lt;/a&gt;.
I didn't really expect to like all of them, but was delighted to support an
emerging author who had contributed to the genius of SCP. But then the books
that arrived turned out to be bloody brilliant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This one tells a tale in which magic was discovered to be real in the 1970s,
becoming a new, arcane branch of physics. From there, it piles on the twists
and raises the stakes at an enthralling and dizzying rate, demanding the
reader to keep up through many exciting layered reveals and escalating changes
of perspective. Absolutely smashing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like &lt;em&gt;Antimemetics&lt;/em&gt;, it scores points with me for including some female heroes,
who surmount challenges through some striking strengths of character &amp;amp;
expertise, rather than simply being the best at applied violence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those like me with an epub fetish, you can buy &lt;em&gt;Ra&lt;/em&gt; in many formats,
including Amazon links, EPUBs, or free-to-read online,
&lt;a href="https://qntm.org/ra"&gt;at the author's site&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="clear: left"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>books</category><category>epub</category><category>fiction</category><category>free-to-read</category><category>media</category><category>novel</category><category>science-fiction</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/ra-by-qntm/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 15 May 2021 17:22:32 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>There is no Antimemetics Division, by qntm</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/there-is-no-antimemetics-division/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2021/there-is-no-antimemetics-division-cover.jpg" style="float: left; padding-right: 1em; padding-bottom: 1em"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I first became aware of &lt;em&gt;Antimemetics&lt;/em&gt; when I noticed that the good folks over
at &lt;a href="http://www.scpwiki.com/"&gt;The SCP Foundation&lt;/a&gt; have kept themselves busy in
the years since I last looked over their peerless wiki of dry and tantalizing
protocols with which to "Secure, Contain, and Protect" a catalog of creepy
anomalous artifacts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the arcs to break the churning surface of that crowdsourced
fictional millieu is that of the
&lt;a href="http://scp-wiki.wikidot.com/antimemetics-division-hub"&gt;Antimemetics Division&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"An antimeme is an idea which, by its intrinsic nature, discourages people
from spreading it. Think of ideas that you wouldn't share - passwords,
taboos, shameful secrets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Anomalous&lt;/em&gt; antimemes are another matter entirely. How do you contain
something you can't record, or remember? How do you fight an enemy when you
can never even know you're at war?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Welcome to the Antimemetics Division.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No, this is not your first day."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Intruiged, I started clicking around, and as is the way of SCP, discovered
many hours had passed. Shortly afterwards, I realized the arc has been
collected into this book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Occasional SCP entries, in the format we know and love, intertwine a short but
intense tale of memetic hazards, and populated by a few of the Division's
finest - those rare individuals who can go from the standing start of a hint
that their memories have been tampered with, to a well-executed plan based upon
a stack of assumptions about what might be needed, and what might already have
been done that they can count upon, even though they no longer remember any of
it, without ever retaining any knowledge of their situation, or what they're up
against. I don't think I've ever been so impressed by the sheer depth of a
character's resourcefulness and initiative.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The journey does contain world-ending hellscapes, with some gore, which might
not be everyone's cup of tea. But it's short and somehow manages to stay light
in tone, so isn't emotionally arduous on that front.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Probably my favorite fiction of the year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those like me with an epub fetish,
you can buy &lt;em&gt;There is No Antimememtics Division&lt;/em&gt; in many formats,
including Amazon links, EPUBs, or free-to-read online,
&lt;a href="https://qntm.org/scp"&gt;at the author's site&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="clear: left"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>books</category><category>epub</category><category>fiction</category><category>free-to-read</category><category>media</category><category>novel</category><category>science-fiction</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/there-is-no-antimemetics-division/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 10 May 2021 18:50:52 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Recent Books</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/june-books/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Notes about some books I read, for me to reminisce over.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2019/06/miracleman.jpg" style="float: left; padding: 1em"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Miracleman, books 1, 2 &amp;amp; 3&lt;/em&gt; by Alan Moore, Alan Davies, &amp;amp; John Totleben.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I spent a little time digging out earlier works of Alan Moore. These
inter-library loans didn't disappoint.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Originally published as &lt;em&gt;Marvelman&lt;/em&gt; by Mick Anglo, from
1954-59. Legal battles rebranded the character as &lt;em&gt;Miracleman&lt;/em&gt; in 1985.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The opening pages reprint one of those campy early stories, involving
primary-colored moralizing while flying around to punch time-travelling Nazi
super-scientists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They then continue with Alan Moore's postmodern 1980s reboot. This recasts the
simplistic tales of the original period as a placating dream, fed to a captured
Miracleman by his nemesis. His hokey origins story is similarly re-ploughed. The
ensuing tales are dark and introspective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One thread follows the emotional stresses placed on Miracleman when incarnated
as his human alter-ego, the frail and fallible half of a godlike being. He's
unable to conceive a child with his wife, although &lt;em&gt;Miracleman&lt;/em&gt; can, and
succumbs to self-loathing and jealousy, culminating in a touching scene in
which he climbs a mountain, leaves a forlorn monument, and changes into
Miracleman one last time, never to change back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, this is more uneven than Moore's later works. Yes, it's unashamedly an
underwear-on-the-outside superhero story. But nonetheless I loved it, and
scenes like the above have stayed with me for months.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: both"&gt;
&lt;img src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2019/06/swamp-thing-vol-1.jpg" style="float: left; padding: 1em"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Swamp Thing, Vol 1: Saga of the Swamp Thing&lt;/em&gt; by Alan Moore, John Totleben, &amp;amp; Steve Bissette.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moore's deconstruction of existing characters continues. Originally Swamp
Thing was Alec Holland, miraculously transformed by in infusion of
artificially stimulated plant matter. When Alan Moore takes over the writing,
Swamp Thing's ostracization and existential dread is compounded by the
discovery that this origins story has been a delusion all along. Alec Holland
was killed outright in the accident, and an accumulation of plant matter grew
around his decaying form, integrating the physical remains of his memories
into a creature that yearned to recapture its human form, but was never human
in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: both"&gt;
&lt;img src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2019/06/hull-zero-three.jpg" style="float: left; padding: 1em"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Hull Zero Three&lt;/em&gt; by Greg Bear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A smashing hard SF tale, about the existential mystery of life aboard a
generation starship that has lost its way. Following in the footsteps of
classic variations, such as &lt;em&gt;Non-Stop&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Methusalah's Children&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Tau
Zero&lt;/em&gt;, it centers around the character's revelations as they uncover their
situation and origins, being decanted to order by warring factions amongst
high technology ruins.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: both"&gt;
&lt;img src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2019/06/station-eleven.jpg" style="float: left; padding: 1em"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Station Eleven&lt;/em&gt; by Emily St. John Mendel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An evocative tale of intertwined lives, before and after the sudden fall of
contemporary civilisation due to a global pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: both"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Atrocity Archive&lt;/em&gt; by Charles Stross. The conceit of Lovecraftian horror
rationalized to a mathematical or computable topic is appealing to me, and
kept the pages turning, but I didn't ultimately find it life-changing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nightwings&lt;/em&gt; by Robert Silverberg. A fantastical far-future tale of humanity
split into occupational castes, guarding the world against prophesied
invasion. Not my thing.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>books</category><category>comics</category><category>fiction</category><category>media</category><category>novel</category><category>science-fiction</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/june-books/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 20 Jun 2019 15:17:46 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Altered Carbon</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/altered-carbon/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="richard-morgan-altered-carbon" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2014/02/richard-morgan-altered-carbon.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Richard Morgan&lt;/em&gt; (2001)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A romp through a hyperviolent cyberpunk future through the eyes of a
character reluctantly press-ganged into the role of detective in a story
woven around personality uploads, swaps, and backups. I did enjoy it,
but was put off by the main character winning their victories
by consecutive applications of remorseless violence. There's no cleverness
or examinations of morality here, just that the character cast as the "goodie"
triumphs by being better at beating people up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;10/10 if you're looking to kick back on the couch with tea, cake, and
some exciting SF.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;0/10 if you're not.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>books</category><category>fiction</category><category>media</category><category>novel</category><category>science-fiction</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/altered-carbon/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 02 Feb 2014 18:59:43 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Makers</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/makers/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Cory Doctorow&lt;/em&gt; (not yet published.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://craphound.com/"&gt;Cory&lt;/a&gt; very kindly brought an early manuscript of
this as a gift to &lt;a href="http://www.voidspace.org.uk/"&gt;Michael&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href="http://www.gilesthomas.com/"&gt;Giles&lt;/a&gt; and I when we met him a while ago,
and I've been wracked with guilt ever since because I apparently lost it
soon after. Thankfully, it recently turned up (on
&lt;a href="http://babbageclunk.com/"&gt;Christian&lt;/a&gt;'s desk - my fault!) last week, so
I happily finished it pronto.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's his best fiction yet! He must be honing his abilities with
practice. \o/ Michael do you want it next?.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Christian doesn't like my subjectivity-proof rating system, so this one
is specially for him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rating:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;10/10 if you want a lightly styled but deeply speculative and engrossing
story that winds a like a sightseeing tour around the social and
personal ramifications of the ways in which modern technology is
changing the way people interact, organise and get things done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;0/10: If you aren't interested in the ways society is changing under our
feet.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>books</category><category>culture</category><category>fiction</category><category>internet</category><category>media</category><category>novel</category><category>science-fiction</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/makers/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 18 Apr 2009 22:10:31 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Infinite Jest</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/infinite-jest/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Inifinite Jest" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2009/02/infinitejest.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by David Foster Wallace&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've had such a diverse set of reactions to this, and how could I not?
The writing is bold and idiosyncratic throughout. The novel's story is
not presented in chronological order, and the timeline is obfuscated by
the gleeful adoption of 'subsidised time', in which traditional numeric
monikers denoting each calender year are replaced by the sponsored
labels designated by major corporations - 'Year of the Whopper', and so
on - a marvellous concept which nevertheless makes it completely and
artificially impossible to tell what the hell's going on until about 500
pages in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The whole novel unashamedly celebrates the author's literary and formal
grammatical credentials - from the extraordinarily-crafted opening
scene, where a tragically misunderstood literary genius disastrously
fails a university entrance interview, with just a hint of a
semi-autobiographical air about him. Scenes of superlative execution are
interspersed with a narrative that is, on the whole, told in the third
person but in the argot of the currently eminent protagonist, leading to
large swathes of the book which are, like, more than conversational in
their familiarity. The combination gives rise to a relentlessly
inventive stream of neology and malapropism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the book resoundingly makes many insightful points by the
conclusion, the story which serves as a vehicle for their delivery is,
at best, a ramshackle collision of ideas, introducing entirely new and
unexplored premises at the 11th hour, and then petering out, ignored and
unresolved, by the final page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The insidious footnotes for which Wallace's writings are well-known do
not serve to streamline the prose by separating out incidental
annotations, but instead seem specifically employed to elevate the
reader's awareness of the footnotes themselves. Including them in the
main body of the text would allow for the possibility of a busy reader
failing to give each pithy addendum it's full, weighty consideration.
Wallace cunningly obviates this possibility, by discreetly giving pause
to any reader assiduously trying to do their best with a challenging
book, requiring them to invoke the titillating ritual of thumbing
forward a literal thousand pages or so, giving an involuntary moment of
rest in the narrative in which the reader may properly anticipate the
mysterious text to be revealed while they dereference the footnote's
numeric identifier, and then a second pause afterwards to properly
digest and appreciate, while they thumb a literal thousand pages back
again to find where they left off. Three hundred and eighty eight times,
no less. Plus sub-footnotes, obviously. Some of these are pages-long
tomes of critically insightful dialog between major characters. Many
others are completely irrelevant technical specifications. I have to
ask, what the fuck is going on here? Does this really make the novel
somehow better? While I laughed and cried about the content of many of
the footnotes, I remain unconvinced by the mechanism of their delivery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I rant about these aspects of style because these are definitely the
first impressions any reader will have. Getting into the book &lt;a href="http://kottke.org/09/03/growing-sentences-with-david-foster-wallace"&gt;does
require a little
work&lt;/a&gt;.
But fortunately Wallace more than provides the incentive to do so. The
book ranges over many areas, but is mostly about addiction, in its many
forms, and its relationship to freedom of will and to happiness. These
are deep and interesting topics, and are unflinchingly explored with a
very keen eye. For every one of the annoyances mentioned above, the book
provides powerful rewards for those who stick it out. The
heart-wrenching depictions of people going through the utter destruction
of their humanity are as touching and insightful as anything I have
read.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are some problems or tasks in life which are small enough that an
individual can overcome them by force of will, grinding down the problem
until it is flattened and overcome. This approach fails, however, when
the problem is too large or too hard. Some problems cannot be crushed by
any individual. To navigate past them requires that, instead of trying
to demolish the problem, the individual must instead mould themselves to
fit around the problem's existing contours. People emerge on the other
side of these experiences triumphant but sober - having been changed to
their core by the experience. I consider &lt;em&gt;Infinite Jest&lt;/em&gt; to belong to
this latter class of experience. From the base-camp of its 981 pages
(plus 98 of footnotes), it is intimidating and uncompromising. You love
it and hate it in equal measure, and it makes no attempt to pander to
the former. But as I ploughed on, through it, week after week after
week, I grew to enjoy it more and more and more. I began to see
reminders of it everywhere I looked. I spotted echoes of its style in
the speech of friends who are fans of Wallace. It began, very subtly, to
infect my own speech and writing. The topics it covered touched me to
the core, changing my outlook on deep issues such as religion. By the
time I reached the very last page I emerged, bruised and weary, but also
tremendously excited - I actually flipped it right back and re-read the
first few chapters all over again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now for perhaps the greatest test to date of my supposedly
subjectivity-proof rating system. Here goes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rating:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;10/10: If you are ready for a challenge, that entertains and wrenches in
equal measure, stretching you, changing your definitions, taking you on
a tour of regions you never knew existed. It will make you laugh and it
will make you cry. It will leave you a different person than when you
began.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;0/10: If you can't be bothered.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>books</category><category>drugs</category><category>fiction</category><category>media</category><category>novel</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/infinite-jest/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 28 Mar 2009 21:26:49 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Fahrenheit 451</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/fahrenheit-451/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Farneheit 451" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2009/01/farneheit_451.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Ray Bradbury&lt;/em&gt;, 1953.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A tale of future urban America, in which political or critical thought
is suppressed by overwhelming popular entertainment and by burning all
books, told with Bradbury's typical simple and beautiful prose. Rarely
has a tale suffused me with such peace and tranquillity than my making
the transition from the frantic, advertising-saturated dystopia into the
moonlit fields and abandoned railroads of the closing chapters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The novel has a curiously bifurcated message for modern times. We would
seem to be even more overwhelmed by noisy and crass distractions of
types unimaginable in Bradbury's time, often unable to pry ourselves
free from a myriad compelling sources of entertainment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, for all the negative impact this internet may have had on our
peace of mind and our attention spans, it has also provided tremendous
benefits that to a great extent defuse the novel's warnings. Books are
now infinitely reproduceable. Dissenting thought or new ideas can easily
be published and read by millions, free from fear of retribution by
employers or governments, those &lt;a href="http://homes.eff.org/~barlow/Declaration-Final.html"&gt;weary giants of flesh and
steel&lt;/a&gt;. Writing by
any person in the world is routinely disseminated to and from the
furthest corners of the globe in seconds. Instantly findable. Free from
censorship. Archived forever. Unburnable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This ease-of-use provides each of us with exactly what we demand of it.
Just as Bradbury foretells, those of a studious mind, those with
legitimate concerns, those with a desire to change the world or make
something more out of life, these people will always gather to talk and
plan and act. Only now, they can do so globally, instantly and
effectively. For each of us, our salvation requires only that we choose
to save ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rating:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;10/10 if you fancy a bit of charming retro SF with a beautiful turn of
phrase&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;0/10 if you think worrying about fulfilment in life, political affairs,
or meaning in life is a big waste of time, especially if it's done by
way of science-fiction metaphors and hyperthetical future scenarios.
Let's go shopping!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>books</category><category>fiction</category><category>media</category><category>novel</category><category>science-fiction</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/fahrenheit-451/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2009 22:15:47 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>City at the End of Time</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/city-at-the-end-of-time/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="city-at-the-end-of-time" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2008/12/city-at-the-end-of-time.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Greg Bear, 2008&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Smashing, but not life changing. Another great ripping yarn. I find
myself with less and less patience for such a thing of late, and I'm not
sure how to tell if that's due to the quality of the works in question,
or due to a change in my own temprament.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would, in years gone by, have listed Greg Bear as one of my favourite
science-fiction authors, but my rating for this one is slipping
dangerously close to the 'not sure it was worth my time' level. I felt
the same way about &lt;em&gt;The Algebraist&lt;/em&gt;, by Ian Banks, who I previously have
also loved to death.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I guess authors have their good and bad seasons just like anyone else.
But I'm tempted to go back and flick through &lt;em&gt;Eon&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Eternity&lt;/em&gt; again,
to see if they really were as well-crafted as I remember them. Whether I
love or loathe the exercise should decide the issue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rating: 6.5/10 Why all the X-point-five scores recently?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>books</category><category>fiction</category><category>media</category><category>novel</category><category>science-fiction</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/city-at-the-end-of-time/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 14 Dec 2008 22:56:38 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Difference Engine</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/the-difference-engine/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="differenceengine" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2008/12/differenceengine.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by William Gibson and Bruce Sterling, 1990&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A quick re-read, inspired by a recent visit to &lt;a href="http://www.sciencemuseum.org.uk/"&gt;the Science
Museum&lt;/a&gt;, where we were enthralled by
our meanderings around various astonishing artifacts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rickety-looking &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Apollo_10"&gt;Apollo
  10&lt;/a&gt; capsule, charred from
  re-entry, having journeyed to within 9 miles of the moon and back
  again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stephenson%27s_Rocket"&gt;Stevenson's
  Rocket&lt;/a&gt;, not, as
  I had previously understood, the first steam-powered railway
  locomotive, just a revolutionary improvement in design, capable of
  the unheard-of speed of 29 miles an hour.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Watson and Crick's original 6-foot mechano model of the double-helix
  structure of a &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/DNA"&gt;DNA molecule&lt;/a&gt; (or
  at least the original bits of it, re-assembled at Kings around
  1990), constructed between LSD fuelled revelry and Sunday
  afternoons' quiet boozing pondering the meaning of life. Not a bad
  lifestyle, it has to be said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Charles Babbage's Difference Engine number 1, or at least remnants
  of it. This is the arithmetic precursor to his subsequent, and more
  ambitious, analytical engine, the conception of which was a precient
  stroke of genius, the world's first programmable computer. Lacking
  electronics, it was implemented in a purely mechanical manner, a 40
  year labour of which he pursued until his death.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was surprised to learn that the failing of the device was not, as I
had previously heard, due to the inadequate manufacturing tolerances of
the time. Recent examinations have demonstrated these to be more than
adequate. Instead, the lengthy and costly extensions to the project,
leading to its eventual failure in an ocean of debts and soured
relationships is nowadays blamed on the project suffering from
'inappropriate management'. Interesting to see the nascent software
industry starting out as it was destined to continue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was, of course, this last item at the museum which inspired me to
pick up &lt;em&gt;The Difference Engine&lt;/em&gt; paperback again, an alternate history
novel in which the authors indulge the fantasy that Babbage's project
had been a success, and the British Empire, in the upheaval of a
steam-powered information processing era, underwent a series of
meritocratous social revolutions, and as a result was better equipped to
continue its expansion across the globe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rating 7.5/10 - a splendid ripping yarn.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>books</category><category>exhibits</category><category>fiction</category><category>geek</category><category>journal</category><category>media</category><category>novel</category><category>science-fiction</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/the-difference-engine/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2008 15:19:16 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Catcher in the Rye</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/the-catcher-in-the-rye/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2008/09/catcher-in-the-rye.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Jerome D. Salinger&lt;/em&gt;, 1951.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, people make such a fuss over it, they really do. You ask
anyone. It's that Salinger's fault. He never listens to anyone.
Sometimes I think he only writes it because he knows it gets on peoples
goat. Writing about some crazy kid. I mean, I say he's crazy because
that's what everyone says, but he's no crazier than the rest of us if
you want to know the truth. Smoking and swearing getting laid, if he got
half a chance. But it's only what anyone would have done, well, anyone
with any sense, that is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's one thing about it though, it made me remember a time when I was
very young, no joke, and I started reading this very book, I don't know
where I got it, I think my Father gave it to me. But I don't think I got
very far. It must have been beyond me, to tell you the truth. Well,
you've got to give the old Pater his due, for trying to stretch you and
all that. That's just like him, it really is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, the story doesn't really go anywhere, at least not anywhere I
could fathom. Well, things happen, but it's just everyday things over
the few days after being expelled from school. The usual stuff. You
could write a whole essay, I suppose, about whether or not Caulfield
changes or learns anything by the novel's end, or simply remains an
adolescent. But I don't think that would amount to very much. So it's a
stylistic experience, at any rate. Very '&lt;em&gt;A Portrait of the Artist as a
Young Man&lt;/em&gt;' I'm sure, and you've got to give him his due.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rating: 7/10 - Bloody Salinger, he never listens to anyone, him.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>books</category><category>fiction</category><category>media</category><category>novel</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/the-catcher-in-the-rye/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2008 22:41:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>