<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>tartley.com (Posts about personal)</title><link>https://tartley.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://tartley.com/categories/personal.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2023 &lt;a href="mailto:tartley @ the domain tartley dot com"&gt;Jonathan Hartley&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 12 Apr 2023 01:02:48 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>You Invite Them To Yourself</title><link>https://tartley.com/posts/you-invite-them-to-yourself/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.facebook.com/photo.php?pid=2212211&amp;amp;id=589628893"&gt;&lt;img alt="Cover Art" src="https://tartley.com/files/2009/03/cover.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Me and the other Pillai's are very happy to announce that the album is
finally done. This is the culmination of what turned out to be over two
years of hard work for all of us, and despite or perhaps because of all
the barrys and the tears, in the end we're pleased as punch with the way
it has turned out. It's already all over the Internets, but if you want
to indulge us, you can buy a copy
&lt;a href="http://www.facebook.com/photo.php?pid=2212211&amp;amp;id=589628893"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>personal</category><guid>https://tartley.com/posts/you-invite-them-to-yourself/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 02 Mar 2009 05:24:57 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Ah... the strangeness of chance</title><link>https://tartley.com/posts/ah-the-strangeness-of-chance/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Milk and cookies. Browser cookies to be precise. Not nutty or
chocolately, but definitely subject to the vagaries of fate. Take this
blog entry. The more astute may detect a hint of the hirsute in this
entry - and all down to that one strange little cookie...&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>guest-blogger</category><category>personal</category><guid>https://tartley.com/posts/ah-the-strangeness-of-chance/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 25 Jan 2008 22:43:58 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Deluded Ramblings of a Rather Odd Person</title><link>https://tartley.com/posts/the-deluded-ramblings-of-a-rather-odd-person/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Hello everybody - I think you are all lovely. Would you like to come for
tea? Great. See you tonight. I have some gorgeous videos of dog-on-dog
hot action, we could watch them together whilst wearing fluffy jumpers.
I have the worlds finest collection of stripy fluffy jumpers. They are
as hot-as-a-hot-pink-thing-would-be-if-it-was really-hot-and-pink.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hmmm... all this talk of hot and pink things reminds me of a dream I had
last night. Don't you love talking about dreams. The only corollary is
how much I loathe listening to other people talk about their dreams.
Anyhoo, back to the subject. Anyhoo is an odd word. I'm sure I was
watching some obscure TV pre-processed-almost-pre-digested program of
yester-year the other day when I heard people using it. What
degradations we force upon our faithful mistress the English language.
(And the subject of degradation neatly reminds me of the dream which I
am now too distracted to talk about.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Language is a great thing. That of course is obvious, but mere hyperbole
and superlatives are insufficient to express the magnitude of the
underlying awesomeness. That of course is midly ironic, which is utterly
lost on me, but there we go. Written language is almost more stupefying.
Scratchings and scribblings that convey meaning, which propels unbidden
into the mind upon the merest glance, and transcends mundane experience
to transport the imagination. How did this state of affairs ever come
into being ?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To explore this extraordinary situation we need to devolve, literally of
course - but also literarily, to component components. Tangentially I
would say this is a bad idea, but parenthetically I would *love* to
watch you try.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway (is this a sentence?). To those of you who have endured to the
ends, I am deeply sorry.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>guest-blogger</category><category>personal</category><guid>https://tartley.com/posts/the-deluded-ramblings-of-a-rather-odd-person/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Mar 2007 20:01:44 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>