<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>tartley.com (Posts about Politics)</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://www.tartley.com/categories/politics.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2020 &lt;a href="mailto:tartley@domain tartley dot com"&gt;Jonathan Hartley&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 11 Jun 2020 21:33:58 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Revolution: An Instruction Manual</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/2013/8/10/revolution-an-instruction-manual.html</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;When you have a government that operates without limits, who proclaims
the right to arrest, torture and kill anyone, anywhere, with no
warrants, no trial, no due process...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you have a government that militarizes the police and grants the
armed forces the power to operate with impunity within your own borders
and beyond. A government that views you, the people, as the enemy, and
treats you as such...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you have a government that lies to you takes you into wars of
aggression, toppling country after country, killing hundreds of
thousands of innocent civilians, and sending your sons and daughters and
your fathers and your brothers home in flag draped coffins, or
disfigured and broken in mind and body, their lives destroyed in wars
that serve only to line the pockets of a unelected cartel of bankers and
corporations...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you have all of this right in front of you, so blatant, so clear,
you shouldn't have to be convinced that both parties in this political
puppet show are owned and operated by the same interests. You shouldn't
have to be convinced that these overrated corporate popularity contests
that some call elections are distractions that will achieve nothing.
With this understood, you shouldn't have to be convinced that the system
you are living under must be brought to a halt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://stormcloudsgathering.com/revolution-an-instruction-manual"&gt;Read
on...&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>Politics</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/2013/8/10/revolution-an-instruction-manual.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 10 Aug 2013 16:50:36 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Quote from Tim Bray</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/2010/3/15/quote-from-tim-bray.html</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The iPhone vision of the mobile Internet's future omits controversy,
sex, and freedom, but includes strict limits on who can know what and
who can say what. It's a sterile Disney-fied walled garden surrounded
by sharp-toothed lawyers. The people who create the apps serve at the
landlord's pleasure and fear his anger.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hate it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hate it even though the iPhone hardware and software are great,
because freedom's not just another word for anything, nor is it an
optional ingredient.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tim Bray, &lt;a href="http://www.tbray.org/ongoing/When/201x/2010/03/15/Joining-Google"&gt;Now a No-Evil
Zone&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm increasingly aware that many of my lifestyle choices, from my
Android phone and my long-standing affection for Linux, through to my
choices of where I live and who I work for, are driven by my instinctive
dislike for being told what I can and can't do. I value my freedom.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>Geek</category><category>Politics</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/2010/3/15/quote-from-tim-bray.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 15 Mar 2010 14:12:29 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>