<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>tartley.com (Posts about review)</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://www.tartley.com/categories/review.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2020 &lt;a href="mailto:tartley @ the domain tartley dot com"&gt;Jonathan Hartley&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 16 Jun 2020 15:54:16 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Legend of Zelda : The Phantom Hourglass</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/2009/1/16/legend-of-zelda-the-phantom-hourglass/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2008/05/phantom-hourglass.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nintendo, 2008&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nintendo spin off a &lt;em&gt;fourteenth&lt;/em&gt; iteration of the familiar and
oh-so-beloved franchise. I'd only previously played the
preposterously-sub-titled &lt;em&gt;Ocarina of Time&lt;/em&gt; on the N64, of which I
retain fond, sepia-coloured memories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I found &lt;em&gt;Phantom Hourglass&lt;/em&gt; to be engaging, and played it to a
thoroughly jolly completion over the course of a couple of months. The
gameplay and plot are a tad more casual and lightweight than &lt;em&gt;Ocarina&lt;/em&gt;,
as befitting play snatched while on-the-go on the handheld platform.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using the DS stylus to control Link is delightfully transparent and
intuitive. Just as for a mouse, however, expert users will eventually
eschew it for many actions, preferring the speed, precision and
tactility of distinct physical buttons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the down side, some of the puzzles are downright contrived. After
introducing a handy little map, on which you can scrawl notes and
reminders for yourself, the game then promptly takes it away again for
&lt;em&gt;exactly&lt;/em&gt; the levels on which it would be of most use, proclaiming 'you
can't use the map here, some sort of magic prevents it.' Right. Up
yours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Equally intrusive, the dialog is entirely Nintendo-esque cutesy Japanese
schmultz, and it would have improved the game no end for it to have been
entirely absent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Such niggles are few and far between, though. Time for another go of the
newfangled rating system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rating: Place yourself somewhere between...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;10/10 if you're into a deftly executed handheld riff on the Zelda
series, beautifully integrated with the affordances and sensibilities of
the hosting hardware in that way that only Nintendo can do. Lots to love
here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;0/10 if you're done with revisiting timeworn ideas, even ones as
compelling and charming as this, and yearn for a resurgence in
experimental originality to kick the gaming industry out of one or two
ruts (such as having a blind spot for crappy dialog.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>ds</category><category>games</category><category>nintendo</category><category>review</category><category>videogame</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/2009/1/16/legend-of-zelda-the-phantom-hourglass/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2009 20:36:05 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>