<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>tartley.com (Posts about scient-fiction)</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://www.tartley.com/categories/scient-fiction.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2021 &lt;a href="mailto:tartley @ the domain tartley dot com"&gt;Jonathan Hartley&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 18 May 2021 19:10:38 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>I am Legend</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/i-am-legend/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="I am Legend" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2008/02/i-am-legend.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Directed by Francis Lawrence.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Summary&lt;/strong&gt;
This is going to be one of those reviews where someone reads the book
and then sees the movie and doesn't like it very much.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Details&lt;/strong&gt;
I read &lt;em&gt;Robinson Crusoe&lt;/em&gt; for the first time when I was about 30. It
forms such a prominent thread within our cultural milieu that I expected
it to be a pinnacle of literature, well-written and evocative. For me,
however, it was nothing of the sort. It seemed to have been lazily
dashed off by a nitwit aristocrat who'd never faced a single day of
hardship in his life, with no thought at all given to the physical and
psychological trials someone in Crusoe's predicament would suffer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Only weeks later, I read Richard Matheson's novel &lt;em&gt;I am Legend&lt;/em&gt;, and
unexpectedly found it to be nigh on exactly the study of loneliness and
despair that I had expected &lt;em&gt;Crusoe&lt;/em&gt; would be. The portrayal of frantic
days spent repairing the fortifications, alternating with horrific
sleepless nights spent indoors, listening to &lt;em&gt;them&lt;/em&gt; trying to get in, is
as dense an atmosphere of desperation as I think I've ever been party
to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So it was with conflicting pangs of emotion that I first heard about the
movie. In many ways the movie's strength is simply the inevitable
reaction one has to the depiction of a desolate New York City. Will
Smith's character is now a world-class scientist, bent on reversing the
ravages of the zombie/vampire plague single-handed, working from his
Hollywood-style basement laboratory. The novel's pivotal ending - from
which the title is derived - is utterly transformed into something
rather jolly and upbeat. Even the signs of him fraying around the edges
under the strain have been sanitised - he talks to mannequins, rather
than drinking himself into oblivion. It's &lt;em&gt;Robinson Crusoe&lt;/em&gt; all over
again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rating: 5/10 - not great.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: both"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>media</category><category>movies</category><category>scient-fiction</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/i-am-legend/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 08 Feb 2008 06:45:21 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>