<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>tartley.com (Posts about short)</title><link>https://tartley.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://tartley.com/categories/short.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2023 &lt;a href="mailto:tartley @ the domain tartley dot com"&gt;Jonathan Hartley&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 12 Apr 2023 01:02:53 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>The Works of Larry Niven</title><link>https://tartley.com/posts/the-works-of-larry-niven/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://tartley.com/files/2022/niven/view-from-the-surface-of-a-ringworld.webp"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few days ago I mistakenly
&lt;a href="https://tartley.com/posts/termination-shock"&gt;named Neal Stephenson as the author I'd read more of&lt;/a&gt;
than any other. But I was forgetting about being young and inhaling books.
On reflection, that title must surely belong to Larry Niven. As a teenager I
read every last thing he did - or at least everything I could find in my
hometown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At one point my Mom picked up &lt;em&gt;World Out of Time&lt;/em&gt;, to see what craziness her
son was always buried in, and she concluded over the dinner table that I was
reading it for the sex scenes she'd found. I presumably objected inarticulately
that I was so little interested in Larry Niven's brief nerdy depictions of
space sex that I'd barely even noticed they were there, but I have the
impression she wasn't convinced. But it &lt;em&gt;really was&lt;/em&gt; was his brand of hard
science fiction that I was there for (I protest too much!) - revolving around
ideas rather than character arcs, and the ruthless application of consistent
world-views.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In inventing the Ringworld, Niven was inspired by Dyson spheres,
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Star_Maker"&gt;first described by Olaf Stapledon&lt;/a&gt;,
and &lt;a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20140109033551/http://meaningoflife.tv/transcript.php?speaker=dyson"&gt;popularized by Freeman Dyson&lt;/a&gt;.
A full, solid Dyson sphere was, in some regards, inefficient. Dyson postulated
miraculous gravity generators to make the inner surface of the sphere
habitable. But this can be achieved much more feasibly by simply spinning the
structure. However, all the matter inside the sphere, including any atmosphere,
then pools at the equator. Niven observed that the superfluous surface of the
sphere, away from the equator, can then be removed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This vastly reduces the material needed to construct the megastructure.
Given miraculous elemental transmutation, one could easily gather enough
matter by recycling all the planets in a solar system as building material,
even with a 1,000km "wall" along each edge to keep the fringes of the
atmosphere in. Although this yields a much smaller habitable interior surface
area than a full sphere, it's still something like a million times larger than
planet Earth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The aliens themselves weren't quite like any I've read before or since. The
creepy sessile but sentient Grogs. The mysterious Outsiders, information
brokers who are able to answer any question humanity has - if only we could
afford the prices. The warlike, carnivorous Kzinti (picture a species of
vicious, vaguely feline Chewbaccas - surely the inspiration for Wing
Commander's Kilrathi) forever attacking humanity before they were quite ready.
You can't help but almost feel sorry for them. By the times of Ringworld,
representatives such as Speaker to Animals (named for his shameful profession,
interfacing with humans) are sufficiently adapted to working alongside humans
to become formidable allies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps Niven's greatest alien race was The Pierson's Puppeteers - like an
ostrich with two necks, each topped with a single eye and dexterous mouth,
while the brain resides safely in the body (pictured below, on the cover for
Neutron star). The body plan makes so much sense in action. Mobile eyes mean
they routinely view objects from both sides simultaneously, perfect for
close-up detailed work, using the hand-like mouths. Or, spread the necks wide
for amazing stereoscopic vision when distance estimation matters. And that
gestural laugh - eyes turned inward to briefly gaze into one another, observing
the self, no mirror required.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The psychology is also exquisite. Herbivores and herd-beasts, the Puppeteers
are inveterate cowards. No human has ever met a sane one - only their more
unstable individuals would venture out alone to run the risks of space travel
and meeting alien species. However, they are very intelligent, more so than
humans, and industrious, and devious. It becomes clear over the course of
the books that Puppeteers have selectively bred the Kzinti into constructive
docility by engineering the many human-kzin wars, and their plans for everyone
else are scarcely less manipulative.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, my personal favorite was always the Pak. As alien as could be, and yet
they are us. On humanity's original home-world, long before introduction to
planet Earth, a symbiotic plant grows which young humans find uninteresting,
but in middle-age they develop a compulsion to binge on it. It activates genes
that provoke startling physiological and psychological changes, transforming
the human from a &lt;em&gt;breeder&lt;/em&gt;, into a &lt;em&gt;protector&lt;/em&gt; - stronger, and with large
joints for better leverage, with a tough wrinkled armour-like skin, much
smarter, with a second heart, and ruthlessly dedicated to just one goal -
protecting their own offspring. It is protectors who, it turns out many novels
later, originally built the Ringworld. The absence of the transforming plant,
which won't grow on Earth, means we grow without its benefits, leaving us with
inadequate hearts, joints that fail with age, and an old-aged descent into
feeble bodies and minds. Then, as the story begins, the first known
interstellar spaceship shows up at Earth, piloted by one protector, come to
rescue the failed colony, with a hold full of strange plant roots...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wonders like these, from the novels and short stories set in his Known Space
universe kept me up at night, and shaped the way I thought. Although Niven's
writing had some mildly conservative tendencies, especially when under the
influence of his militaristic writing partner Jerry Pournelle, it is also
permeated with the necessity of a very liberal philosophy of non-judgemental
tolerance of other lifestyles, both alien and human, a philosophy made explicit
in one of &lt;em&gt;Niven's Laws&lt;/em&gt;: "The only universal message in science fiction: There
exist minds that think as well as you do, but differently."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's clear I wasn't the only one spellbound. Niven's ideas have been
influential throughout science fiction culture. Bank's Culture's Orbitals and
the understandably much rarer full Rings are clear descendants, as is the
eponymous megastructure/superweapon of the juggernaut &lt;em&gt;Halo&lt;/em&gt; franchise, and
countless other imitators. Niven's meticulous hard-SF approach to fantasy in
&lt;em&gt;The Magic Goes Away&lt;/em&gt;, and in particular his concept of the conservation of
&lt;em&gt;mana&lt;/em&gt;, was an influence on &lt;em&gt;Magic: The Gathering&lt;/em&gt;, as acknowledged in the card
Nevinyrral's Disk (Niven's name backwards), which uses magic to simultaneously
accelerate it's own spin, and to hold itself together, thus rapidly using up
all the mana in an area, rendering further magic unusable. Movies such as
Wall-E throw in sly nods - the Axiom is labelled in a passing graphic as using
a "General Dynamics Type Three Hull", which is a similar size and shape to
Niven's "General Products Number Three Hull".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For years I remember toting Niven's various doorstop 500 page novels to one
place or another, such as being forbidden from carrying one into the Houses of
Parliament viewing gallery. All the better that they usually had these crazy
great '70s covers, mostly by artist
&lt;a href="http://www.peterandrewjones.net/iacg.htm"&gt;Peter Andrew Jones&lt;/a&gt;,
from whom you can buy prints of some of them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Collecting these today by Google image search, I see today that these funky
covers are relatively rare - the vast majority of Niven's sales were of
editions with far less interesting and less skillfully put together covers. So
I think it's appropriate to collect and celebrate them here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;span style="padding: 0.3em"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://tartley.com/files/2022/niven/mote-in-gods-eye.webp"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style="padding: 0.3em"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://tartley.com/files/2022/niven/footfall.webp"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style="padding: 0.3em"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://tartley.com/files/2022/niven/oath-of-fealty.webp"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style="padding: 0.3em"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://tartley.com/files/2022/niven/dream-park.webp"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style="padding: 0.3em"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://tartley.com/files/2022/niven/patchwork-girl.webp"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style="padding: 0.3em"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://tartley.com/files/2022/niven/convergent-series.webp"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style="padding: 0.3em"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://tartley.com/files/2022/niven/magic-goes-away.webp"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style="padding: 0.3em"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://tartley.com/files/2022/niven/lucifers-hammer.webp"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style="padding: 0.3em"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://tartley.com/files/2022/niven/world-out-of-time.webp"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style="padding: 0.3em"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://tartley.com/files/2022/niven/tales-of-known-space.webp"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style="padding: 0.3em"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://tartley.com/files/2022/niven/hole-in-space.webp"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style="padding: 0.3em"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://tartley.com/files/2022/niven/flight-of-the-horse.webp"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style="padding: 0.3em"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://tartley.com/files/2022/niven/protector.webp"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style="padding: 0.3em"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://tartley.com/files/2022/niven/inconstant-moon.webp"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style="padding: 0.3em"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://tartley.com/files/2022/niven/ringworld.webp"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style="padding: 0.3em"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://tartley.com/files/2022/niven/ringworld-engineers.webp"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style="padding: 0.3em"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://tartley.com/files/2022/niven/long-arm-of-gil-hamilton.webp"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style="padding: 0.3em"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://tartley.com/files/2022/niven/a-gift-from-earth.webp"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style="padding: 0.3em"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://tartley.com/files/2022/niven/neutron-star.webp"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style="padding: 0.3em"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://tartley.com/files/2022/niven/world-of-ptavvs.webp"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: both"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've not even read half of what Niven wrote. By the '90s the crazy covers had
been replaced by more conservative designs, and at the same time I drifted away
to other things. At the time it felt more like Niven was drifting away from me,
evolving in style over the years, losing something hard-to-characterize that
I'd enjoyed, maybe just the rawness of his earlier works. Maybe his style was
diluted through him writing so many books as partnerships, or, as I
increasingly assumed, in an advisory role, lending his name to the cover for
younger, less well-known authors, who did most of the work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking back on it, with 30-or-so year's hindsight, there are also
components of Niven's writing that are lacking, and I was slowly growing out of
it. Hard SF often celebrates the elevation of ideas over characters, and while
there is a value to that, particularly for those readers who are the most
vulnerable to the sensation of wonder, it also needlessly shuns other aspects,
like the emotional impact of character-driven drama or individual psychological
epiphany. A more skilled writer, I now think, would have a broader range of
tools to imbue the story with more emotional resonance and meaning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, while the affair lasted, it was fabulous. Goodreads page counts
indicates it was eleven thousand pages, beating my Neal Stephenson consumption
by a clear thousand pages. Combining that with a very conservative estimate of
the number of times I re-read each one, nearly twenty five thousand pages. What
can I say, I was a teenager, with seemingly endless oceans of time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following are just his books that I've read. He has many others, especially
many that are more recent than these.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Title&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style="text-align: right;"&gt;Pages&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style="text-align: right;"&gt;Times&lt;br&gt;read&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style="text-align: right;"&gt;Effective&lt;br&gt;pages&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/100379.Rainbow_Mars"&gt;Rainbow Mars&lt;/a&gt; (1999)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;477&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;477&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/64750.Destiny_s_Road"&gt;Destiny's Road&lt;/a&gt; (1997)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;448&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;448&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/64467.The_Ringworld_Throne"&gt;The Ringworld Throne&lt;/a&gt; (1996)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;368&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;368&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/69448.Beowulf_s_Children"&gt;Beowulf's Children&lt;/a&gt; (1995)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;512&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;1,024&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/40932142-flatlander"&gt;Flatlander&lt;/a&gt; (1995)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;369&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;369&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/100347.Crashlander"&gt;Crashlander&lt;/a&gt; (1994)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;281&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;281&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/218453.The_Gripping_Hand"&gt;The Gripping Hand&lt;/a&gt; (1993)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;413&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;826&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/218470.The_Barsoom_Project"&gt;The Barsoom Project&lt;/a&gt; (1989)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;352&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;352&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/899392.The_Legacy_of_Heorot"&gt;The Legacy of Heorot&lt;/a&gt; (1987)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;383&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;766&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/100351.The_Smoke_Ring"&gt;The Smoke Ring&lt;/a&gt; (1987)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;323&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;646&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/116356.Footfall"&gt;Footfall&lt;/a&gt; (1985)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;524&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;1,572&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/939740.The_Integral_Trees"&gt;The Integral Trees&lt;/a&gt; (1983)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;272&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;544&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/583441.Oath_of_Fealty"&gt;Oath of Fealty&lt;/a&gt; (1981)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;324&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;648&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/357922.Dream_Park"&gt;Dream Park&lt;/a&gt; (1981)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;448&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;1,344&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/1124048.The_Patchwork_Girl"&gt;The Patchwork Girl&lt;/a&gt; (1980)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;205&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;410&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/61181.The_Ringworld_Engineers"&gt;The Ringworld Engineers&lt;/a&gt; (1979)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;307&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;614&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/1124090.Convergent_Series"&gt;Convergent Series&lt;/a&gt; (1979)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;227&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;454&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/1002736.The_Magic_Goes_Away"&gt;The Magic Goes Away&lt;/a&gt; (1978)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;212&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;1,060&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/218467.Lucifer_s_Hammer"&gt;Lucifer's Hammer&lt;/a&gt; (1977)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;629&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;1,258&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/64725.A_World_Out_of_Time"&gt;A World Out of Time&lt;/a&gt; (1976)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;246&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;738&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/100359.Tales_of_Known_Space"&gt;Tales of Known Space&lt;/a&gt; (1975)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;240&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;1,200&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/100365.The_Mote_in_God_s_Eye"&gt;The Mote in God's Eye&lt;/a&gt; (1974)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;596&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;1,788&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/218473.A_Hole_in_Space"&gt;A Hole in Space&lt;/a&gt; (1974)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;196&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;392&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/378683.The_Flight_of_the_Horse"&gt;The Flight of the Horse&lt;/a&gt; (1973)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;212&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;1,060&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/100344.Protector"&gt;Protector&lt;/a&gt; (1973)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;218&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;872&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/1255867.Inconstant_Moon"&gt;Inconstant Moon&lt;/a&gt; (1971)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;200&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;800&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/61179.Ringworld"&gt;Ringworld&lt;/a&gt; (1970)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;228&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;456&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/100363.N_Space"&gt;N-Space&lt;/a&gt; (1969)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;693&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;693&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/116355.The_Long_Arm_of_Gil_Hamilton"&gt;The Long Arm of Gil Hamilton&lt;/a&gt; (1969)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;182&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;364&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/218479.All_the_Myriad_Ways"&gt;All the Myriad Ways&lt;/a&gt; (1968)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;181&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;362&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/218461.A_Gift_from_Earth"&gt;A Gift from Earth&lt;/a&gt; (1968)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;256&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;768&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/100366.Neutron_Star"&gt;Neutron Star&lt;/a&gt; (1966)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;285&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;1,140&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/218463.The_World_of_Ptavvs"&gt;The World of Ptavvs&lt;/a&gt; (1966)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;188&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;752&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;totals&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;10,995&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;24,842&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(&lt;a href="https://www.facebook.com/groups/324897304599197/permalink/1329010600854524"&gt;Discussion&lt;/a&gt;
on Damien Walter's &lt;em&gt;Science Fiction&lt;/em&gt; Facebook group)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: both"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>fiction</category><category>media</category><category>niven</category><category>novel</category><category>science-fiction</category><category>short</category><guid>https://tartley.com/posts/the-works-of-larry-niven/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 14 Jan 2022 23:37:37 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Lena</title><link>https://tartley.com/posts/lena/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Lena" src="https://tartley.com/files/2021/lena.webp"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fabulous short story, &lt;a href="https://qntm.org/mmacevedo"&gt;Lena&lt;/a&gt; by qntm, riffs on
&lt;a href="http://www.scpwiki.com/"&gt;SCP&lt;/a&gt;'s idea of a work of fiction as a wiki entry.
But this is entirely standalone, not part of the SCP universe, and more
resembles a Wikipedia entry. Seems both genuinely scary and almost inevitable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The title stems from the image above, head-and-shoulders hurriedly torn from
the centerfold of a colleague's issue of Playboy in 1972, while searching for
an image to use in an image processing conference paper. From this, we can
infer the proper pronunciation is &lt;em&gt;Lenna&lt;/em&gt;, as in the name of the model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This image has been widely re-used in scientific journals for decades. It has
some objectively useful properties - good dynamic range, details and flat
regions, shading and texture. However, its viral popularity most probably stems
overwhelmingly from its racy nature, featuring an attractive woman, used in
male-dominated fields. This was in contrast to other common test images of
the time, derived from dull 1960s television standards work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The common long term use of the image was done without the knowledge or
permission of Playboy magazine - the copyright holder - or Lena herself. Over
the years they each became aware of it, and made their peace with it. By 2019,
though, Lena stated that the image, like her, ought to be retired.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: left"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>fiction</category><category>free-to-read</category><category>media</category><category>qntm</category><category>science-fiction</category><category>short</category><guid>https://tartley.com/posts/lena/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 09 May 2021 21:25:51 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>A Science-Fiction Omnibus</title><link>https://tartley.com/posts/a-science-fiction-omnibus/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="a-science-fiction-omnibus" src="https://tartley.com/files/2008/12/a-science-fiction-omnibus.jpg" title="a-science-fiction-omnibus"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Editor: Brian Aldiss, 2007&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A collection of short stories from 1941 to 2006. Most of my favourites
in here are ones I've already read before: Asimov's &lt;em&gt;Nightfall&lt;/em&gt;, Bear's
&lt;em&gt;Blood Music&lt;/em&gt;, Aldiss' own &lt;em&gt;Poor Little Warrior!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of the ones that are new to me, not many seemed to have much appeal. A
few nicely crafted exceptions are worthy of special mention: Ward
Moore's &lt;em&gt;Lot&lt;/em&gt;, a tale of a family 's departure from home in the station
wagon as civilisation ends around them; James Tiptree's &lt;em&gt;And I Awoke and
Found Me Here on the Cold Hill's Side&lt;/em&gt;, a tragic and visceral vision of
humanity's emotional and charismatic failings amongst the sleek,
sophisticated races of the galaxy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Amongst the others, there are instances where the collection's vintage
lets it down, ideas that were once exciting and cutting edge, which have
been dulled by the passage of time and events, to expose the lackluster
writing beneath. Multiple tales of supreme computers achieving godhood,
for better or for worse. Tales of malfunctioning machinery that barely
held my interest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Great Work of Time&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine, then, my surprise, when the final story of the collection,
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Crowley"&gt;John Crowley&lt;/a&gt;'s &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Great_Work_of_Time"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Great Work
of Time&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, of which I
have never heard until now, turned out to be an absolute triumph. 75
pages of beautifully crafted prose, all by itself it is easily worth the
cost of this collection, and a more than worthy reward for the time and
effort of reading all the other stories in it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This final story is yet-another-novel-take on time-travel - at once bold
and understated, a nostalgic and wistful story of alternate histories
and the motives of the people charged with affecting the critical
junctures of human civilisation. An exquisitely crafted scene lies
embedded within the story's amber perfection, in which &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cecil_rhodes"&gt;Cecil
Rhodes&lt;/a&gt;' 23 year-old would-be
assassin is recruited for the job by none other than his elderly self,
who persuades with a moving and cathartic retelling of how the events in
question went for him. The reader at this point is already steeped in
the bitter-sweet consequences that the outcome will have for each of
their lives, for the mysterious organisation under who's auspices they
act, for the British Empire's fading hopes of uniting the world under a
single banner versus the looming spectre of future World Wars - it is so
poignant and well constructed and performed that I immediately went back
and read the whole story over again. Absolutely bloody marvellous.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rating 9/10, if you only read the last story in the book. Diluted
otherwise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update:&lt;/strong&gt; A Great Work of Time is available as a stand-alone 75 page
book on Amazon Kindle for £2.99, and Calibre with the DeDRM plugin will
convert this into an epub which can be read on any device.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: both"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>bear</category><category>book</category><category>fiction</category><category>media</category><category>science-fiction</category><category>short</category><guid>https://tartley.com/posts/a-science-fiction-omnibus/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 14 Dec 2008 23:32:47 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Flight of the Horse</title><link>https://tartley.com/posts/the-flight-of-the-horse/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="The Flight of the Horse" src="https://tartley.com/files/2007/03/the_flight_of_the_horse_f.jpeg"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Larry Niven (1969-1973)&lt;/em&gt; &lt;img alt="spoilers" src="https://tartley.com/files/spoilers.svg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I just got this back from long-term loan to
&lt;a href="http://frosties2.com/"&gt;Phil&lt;/a&gt;, and I just couldn't resist reading it
clean through once again. It's a quick, light read, and I honestly
couldn't really justify my love of it to a dispassionate third party.
But Niven's stuff, particularly his early short stories like this, are
always a nostalgia trip for me, representative of the ideas that got me
into science fiction as a kid in the first place. He writes throwaway
tales of quirky worlds, but each one is crafted with such a singularly
consistent exploration of the logical implications of a single, simple
premise, that with hindsight, suddenly complicit in the gag, you can
almost see how each story's conclusion grew inescapably out of the very
opening paragraphs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's very much Niven's modus operandi, and it lends itself well to a
book like this, which is essentially a couple of sets of related short
stories, in settings that verge on fantasy, but which abide by a strict
internal logic that makes them indisputably hard SF to me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first sequence follows the fortunes of a 24th century
post-apocalyptic time traveller, who is trying his best to investigate
the past - our time, and pre-industrial ages - and bring back specimens
of long-extinct species. Things never quite go according to plan - the
horse he bags has an unexpected horn, and the whale he sought turns out
to be a biblical leviathan, until eventually, he figures out the hard
way what we the reader should have known all along - his time machine is
screwy, slipping a little &lt;em&gt;sideways&lt;/em&gt; in time every time he travels back
to the past, sometimes a little, to worlds that differ from ours merely
in happenstance, or sometimes further, to worlds that never could have
been, in which mythical beasts roam and humanity is a very different
breed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second series explores a similarly simple premise - that countless
generations ago, deep in prehistory, when magic thrived and was a
practical art in the world, a sorcerer discovers a terrible secret: that
magic uses up energy from its surroundings, and that eventually this
&lt;em&gt;mana&lt;/em&gt; runs out, leaving an area sterile of magical potential, deadly to
aged magicians, uninhabitable by mythical beasts. The knowledge is
exploited to further various agendas, a vicious cycle that accelerates
the process, that we the reader can see will inevitably lead to the fall
of their civilisation, and the immeasurable dark ages before our own
recorded history began.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's the sort of stuff that people who don't 'do' SF clearly won't have
any patience for. But if you can conjour up a little willing suspension,
can overlook the writer's unsubtle early works, then the imagination and
clarity of the tales shines through, weaving entertaining worlds of both
humour and grandeur.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rating: 7/10&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: both"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>fiction</category><category>media</category><category>niven</category><category>science-fiction</category><category>short</category><guid>https://tartley.com/posts/the-flight-of-the-horse/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Mar 2007 06:22:18 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>