<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>tartley.com (Posts about short)</title><link>https://tartley.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://www.tartley.com/categories/short.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2021 &lt;a href="mailto:tartley @ the domain tartley dot com"&gt;Jonathan Hartley&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 23 Nov 2021 17:14:49 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Lena</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/lena/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Lena" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2021/lena.webp"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fabulous short story, &lt;a href="https://qntm.org/mmacevedo"&gt;Lena&lt;/a&gt; by qntm, riffs on
&lt;a href="http://www.scpwiki.com/"&gt;SCP&lt;/a&gt;'s idea of a work of fiction as a wiki entry.
But this is entirely standalone, not part of the SCP universe, and more
resembles a Wikipedia entry. Seems both genuinely scary and almost inevitable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The title stems from the image above, head-and-shoulders hurriedly torn from
the centerfold of a colleague's issue of Playboy in 1972, while searching for
an image to use in an image processing conference paper. From this, we can
infer the proper pronunciation is &lt;em&gt;Lenna&lt;/em&gt;, as in the name of the model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This image has been widely re-used in scientific journals for decades. It has
some objectively useful properties - good dynamic range, details and flat
regions, shading and texture. However, its viral popularity most probably stems
overwhelmingly from its racy nature, featuring an attractive woman, used in
male-dominated fields. This was in contrast to other common test images of
the time, derived from dull 1960s television standards work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The common long term use of the image was done without the knowledge or
permission of Playboy magazine - the copyright holder - or Lena herself. Over
the years they each became aware of it, and made their peace with it. By 2019,
though, Lena stated that the image, like her, ought to be retired.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: left"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>media</category><category>science-fiction</category><category>short</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/lena/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 09 May 2021 21:25:51 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>A Science-Fiction Omnibus</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/a-science-fiction-omnibus/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="a-science-fiction-omnibus" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2008/12/a-science-fiction-omnibus.jpg" title="a-science-fiction-omnibus"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Editor: Brian Aldiss, 2007&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A collection of short stories from 1941 to 2006. Most of my favourites
in here are ones I've already read before: Asimov's &lt;em&gt;Nightfall&lt;/em&gt;, Bear's
&lt;em&gt;Blood Music&lt;/em&gt;, Aldiss' own &lt;em&gt;Poor Little Warrior!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of the ones that are new to me, not many seemed to have much appeal. A
few nicely crafted exceptions are worthy of special mention: Ward
Moore's &lt;em&gt;Lot&lt;/em&gt;, a tale of a family 's departure from home in the station
wagon as civilisation ends around them; James Tiptree's &lt;em&gt;And I Awoke and
Found Me Here on the Cold Hill's Side&lt;/em&gt;, a tragic and visceral vision of
humanity's emotional and charismatic failings amongst the sleek,
sophisticated races of the galaxy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Amongst the others, there are instances where the collection's vintage
lets it down, ideas that were once exciting and cutting edge, which have
been dulled by the passage of time and events, to expose the lackluster
writing beneath. Multiple tales of supreme computers achieving godhood,
for better or for worse. Tales of malfunctioning machinery that barely
held my interest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Great Work of Time&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine, then, my surprise, when the final story of the collection,
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Crowley"&gt;John Crowley&lt;/a&gt;'s &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Great_Work_of_Time"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Great Work
of Time&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, of which I
have never heard until now, turned out to be an absolute triumph. 75
pages of beautifully crafted prose, all by itself it is easily worth the
cost of this collection, and a more than worthy reward for the time and
effort of reading all the other stories in it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This final story is yet-another-novel-take on time-travel - at once bold
and understated, a nostalgic and wistful story of alternate histories
and the motives of the people charged with affecting the critical
junctures of human civilisation. An exquisitely crafted scene lies
embedded within the story's amber perfection, in which &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cecil_rhodes"&gt;Cecil
Rhodes&lt;/a&gt;' 23 year-old would-be
assassin is recruited for the job by none other than his elderly self,
who persuades with a moving and cathartic retelling of how the events in
question went for him. The reader at this point is already steeped in
the bitter-sweet consequences that the outcome will have for each of
their lives, for the mysterious organisation under who's auspices they
act, for the British Empire's fading hopes of uniting the world under a
single banner versus the looming spectre of future World Wars - it is so
poignant and well constructed and performed that I immediately went back
and read the whole story over again. Absolutely bloody marvellous.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rating 9/10, if you only read the last story in the book. Diluted
otherwise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update:&lt;/strong&gt; A Great Work of Time is available as a stand-alone 75 page
book on Amazon Kindle for £2.99, and Calibre with the DeDRM plugin will
convert this into an epub which can be read on any device.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: both"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>fiction</category><category>media</category><category>science-fiction</category><category>short</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/a-science-fiction-omnibus/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 14 Dec 2008 23:32:47 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Flight of the Horse</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/the-flight-of-the-horse/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="The Flight of the Horse" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2007/03/the_flight_of_the_horse_f.jpeg"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Larry Niven (1969-1973)&lt;/em&gt; &lt;img alt="spoilers" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/spoilers.svg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I just got this back from long-term loan to
&lt;a href="http://frosties2.com/"&gt;Phil&lt;/a&gt;, and I just couldn't resist reading it
clean through once again. It's a quick, light read, and I honestly
couldn't really justify my love of it to a dispassionate third party.
But Niven's stuff, particularly his early short stories like this, are
always a nostalgia trip for me, representative of the ideas that got me
into science fiction as a kid in the first place. He writes throwaway
tales of quirky worlds, but each one is crafted with such a singularly
consistent exploration of the logical implications of a single, simple
premise, that with hindsight, suddenly complicit in the gag, you can
almost see how each story's conclusion grew inescapably out of the very
opening paragraphs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's very much Niven's modus operandi, and it lends itself well to a
book like this, which is essentially a couple of sets of related short
stories, in settings that verge on fantasy, but which abide by a strict
internal logic that makes them indisputably hard SF to me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first sequence follows the fortunes of a 24th century
post-apocalyptic time traveller, who is trying his best to investigate
the past - our time, and pre-industrial ages - and bring back specimens
of long-extinct species. Things never quite go according to plan - the
horse he bags has an unexpected horn, and the whale he sought turns out
to be a biblical leviathan, until eventually, he figures out the hard
way what we the reader should have known all along - his time machine is
screwy, slipping a little &lt;em&gt;sideways&lt;/em&gt; in time every time he travels back
to the past, sometimes a little, to worlds that differ from ours merely
in happenstance, or sometimes further, to worlds that never could have
been, in which mythical beasts roam and humanity is a very different
breed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second series explores a similarly simple premise - that countless
generations ago, deep in prehistory, when magic thrived and was a
practical art in the world, a sorcerer discovers a terrible secret: that
magic uses up energy from its surroundings, and that eventually this
&lt;em&gt;mana&lt;/em&gt; runs out, leaving an area sterile of magical potential, deadly to
aged magicians, uninhabitable by mythical beasts. The knowledge is
exploited to further various agendas, a vicious cycle that accelerates
the process, that we the reader can see will inevitably lead to the fall
of their civilisation, and the immeasurable dark ages before our own
recorded history began.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's the sort of stuff that people who don't 'do' SF clearly won't have
any patience for. But if you can conjour up a little willing suspension,
can overlook the writer's unsubtle early works, then the imagination and
clarity of the tales shines through, weaving entertaining worlds of both
humour and grandeur.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rating: 7/10&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: both"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>fiction</category><category>media</category><category>science-fiction</category><category>short</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/the-flight-of-the-horse/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Mar 2007 06:22:18 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>