<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>tartley.com (Posts about todo)</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://www.tartley.com/categories/todo.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2020 &lt;a href="mailto:tartley@domain tartley dot com"&gt;Jonathan Hartley&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Sat, 13 Jun 2020 00:42:03 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Vonnegut on software development teams.</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/2019/6/30/vonnegut-on-software-development-teams.html</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;So here's a thing. Spotted this in some of Kurt Vonnegut's personal
correspondence, talking about an instructor of his named Slotkin:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What Slotkin said was this: no man who achieved greatness in the arts operated
by himself; he was top man in a group of like-minded individuals. This works
out fine for the cubists, and Slotkin had plenty of good evidence for its
applying to Goethe, Thoreau, Hemingway, and just about anybody you care to
name.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If this isn't 100% true, it's true enough to be interesting—and maybe helpful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The school gives a man, Slotkin said, the fantastic amount of guts it takes to
add to culture. It gives him morale, esprit de corps, the resources of many
brains, and—maybe most important—one-sidedness with assurance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reminds me powerfully of my growing impressions of the environment a person
needs to be in in order to do great things in software. There is no doubt some
effectiveness in assembling great individuals to create a great team.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But in my personal experience, there is a whole lot &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; value in creating a
great team by instilling the right values, and then watching the members
visibly level each other up, producing a succession of great individuals,
and only subsequently attracting more of the same.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>todo</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/2019/6/30/vonnegut-on-software-development-teams.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jul 2019 02:28:04 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>