<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Made out of meat (Posts about wallace)</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://www.tartley.com/categories/wallace.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2023 &lt;a href="mailto:tartley @ the domain tartley dot com"&gt;Jonathan Hartley&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 23 Aug 2023 18:34:55 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Brief Interviews with Hideous Men</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/brief-interviews-with-hideous-men/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left; padding: 1em"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Brief Interviews With Hideous Men cover" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2014/01/brief-interviews-with-hideous-men.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by David Foster Wallace (1999)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A collection of creative essays, varying from playful to unflinchingly
uncomfortable, shot through with Wallace's typical humour and
introspection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've tended to love and hate his &lt;a href="https://www.tartley.com/infinite-jest"&gt;other&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.tartley.com/everything-and-more"&gt;writing&lt;/a&gt; in equal measure, but with such
ferocity that I unreservedly place him amongst my very favourite
authors. There wasn't even much for me to hate in this one, relatively
lacking as it is in labyrinthine footnotes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A couple of the essays left me cold (&lt;em&gt;Tri-Stan: I Sold Sissee Nar to
Ecko&lt;/em&gt; springs to mind - presumably I'm missing the point entirely),
but most of them I found thoroughly engaging and
thought provoking. I'm tempted to read up on those that seemed most
challenging to me (&lt;em&gt;Church Not Made With Hands&lt;/em&gt;, say), and give them
another try.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's been a while. Rating:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;0/10 if you don't want to delve deeply into sometimes uncomfortable
subjects, such as depression, unconventional sex acts, and rape.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;10/10 if you like to be stretched, or at least stirred around, in
interesting directions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: both"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>essays</category><category>fiction</category><category>media</category><category>wallace</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/brief-interviews-with-hideous-men/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2014 02:51:51 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Infinite Jest</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/infinite-jest/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Inifinite Jest" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2009/02/infinitejest.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by David Foster Wallace (1996)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've had such a diverse set of reactions to this, and how could I not?
The writing is bold and idiosyncratic throughout. The novel's story is
not presented in chronological order, and the timeline is obfuscated by
the gleeful adoption of 'subsidised time', in which traditional numeric
monikers denoting each calender year are replaced by the sponsored
labels designated by major corporations - 'Year of the Whopper', and so
on - a marvellous concept which nevertheless makes it completely and
artificially impossible to tell what the hell's going on until about 500
pages in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The whole novel unashamedly celebrates the author's literary and formal
grammatical credentials - from the extraordinarily-crafted opening
scene, where a tragically misunderstood literary genius disastrously
fails a university entrance interview, with just a hint of a
semi-autobiographical air about him. Scenes of superlative execution are
interspersed with a narrative that is, on the whole, told in the third
person but in the argot of the currently eminent protagonist, leading to
large swathes of the book which are, like, more than conversational in
their familiarity. The combination gives rise to a relentlessly
inventive stream of neology and malapropism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the book resoundingly makes many insightful points by the conclusion, the
story which serves as a vehicle for their delivery is, a collision of ideas,
introducing entirely new and unexplored premises at the 11th hour, which
peter out, ignored and unresolved, by the final page. The jest continues
on, I suppose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The insidious footnotes for which Wallace's writings are well-known do
not serve to streamline the prose by separating out incidental
annotations, but instead seem specifically employed to elevate the
reader's awareness of the footnotes themselves. Including them in the
main body of the text would allow for the possibility of a busy reader
failing to give each pithy addendum it's full, weighty consideration.
Wallace cunningly obviates this possibility, by discreetly giving pause
to any reader assiduously trying to do their best with a challenging
book, requiring them to invoke the titillating ritual of thumbing
forward a literal thousand pages or so, giving an involuntary moment of
rest in the narrative in which the reader may properly anticipate the
mysterious text to be revealed while they dereference the footnote's
numeric identifier, and then a second pause afterwards to properly
digest and appreciate, while they thumb a literal thousand pages back
again to find where they left off. Three hundred and eighty eight times,
no less. Plus sub-footnotes, obviously. Some of these are pages-long
tomes of critically insightful dialog between major characters. Many
others are completely irrelevant technical specifications. I have to
ask, what the fuck is going on here? Does this really make the novel
somehow better? While I laughed and cried about the content of many of
the footnotes, I remain unconvinced by the mechanism of their delivery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I rant about these aspects of style because these are definitely the
first impressions any reader will have. Getting into the book &lt;a href="http://kottke.org/09/03/growing-sentences-with-david-foster-wallace"&gt;does
require a little
work&lt;/a&gt;.
But fortunately Wallace more than provides the incentive to do so. The
book ranges over many areas, but is mostly about addiction, in its many
forms, and its relationship to freedom of will and to happiness. These
are deep and interesting topics, and are unflinchingly explored with a
very keen eye. For every one of the annoyances mentioned above, the book
provides powerful rewards for those who stick it out. The
heart-wrenching depictions of people going through the utter destruction
of their humanity are as touching and insightful as anything I have
read.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are some problems or tasks in life which are small enough that an
individual can overcome them by force of will, grinding down the problem
until it is flattened and overcome. This approach fails, however, when
the problem is too large or too hard. Some problems cannot be crushed by
any individual. To navigate past them requires that, instead of trying
to demolish the problem, the individual must instead mould themselves to
fit around the problem's existing contours. People emerge on the other
side of these experiences triumphant but sober - having been changed to
their core by the experience. I consider &lt;em&gt;Infinite Jest&lt;/em&gt; to belong to
this latter class of experience. From the base-camp of its 981 pages
(plus 98 of footnotes), it is intimidating and uncompromising. You love
it and hate it in equal measure, and it makes no attempt to pander to
the former. But as I ploughed on, through it, week after week after
week, I grew to enjoy it more and more and more. I began to see
reminders of it everywhere I looked. I spotted echoes of its style in
the speech of friends who are fans of Wallace. It began, very subtly, to
infect my own speech and writing. The topics it covered touched me to
the core, changing my outlook on deep issues such as religion. By the
time I reached the very last page I emerged, bruised and weary, but also
tremendously excited - I actually flipped it right back and re-read the
first few chapters all over again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now for perhaps the greatest test to date of my supposedly
subjectivity-proof rating system. Here goes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rating:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;10/10: If you are ready for a challenge, that entertains and wrenches in
equal measure, stretching you, changing your definitions, taking you on
a tour of regions you never knew existed. It will make you laugh and it
will make you cry. It will leave you a different person than when you
began.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;0/10: If you can't be bothered.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>drugs</category><category>fiction</category><category>media</category><category>mental-health</category><category>novel</category><category>wallace</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/infinite-jest/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 28 Mar 2009 21:26:49 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Everything and More: A compact history of ∞</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/everything-and-more/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;o&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Cover: Everything and More" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2007/02/everything-and-more.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by David Foster Wallace (2003)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Short and Unnecessary Foreword&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before I describe the book I should like to set the scene, as it were,
by describing how it was recommended to me in glowing terms by my new
friend, viz. Xtian&lt;em&gt;[1]&lt;/em&gt;, whom I hold in high regard w.r.t. both
intellectual pursuits and such matters of taste as one's reading
material. Such an introduction lead me to have high expectations of E&amp;amp;M,
and I shall now relate the extent to which these were fulfilled.&lt;em&gt;[2]&lt;/em&gt;
But first, for your convenience, a glossary of abbreviations:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: both"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;E&amp;amp;M&lt;/strong&gt; - Everything and More&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DSP&lt;/strong&gt; - Digital signal processing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;NZ&lt;/strong&gt; - New Zealand&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;YMMV&lt;/strong&gt; - Your mileage may vary&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[1]&lt;/em&gt; Who hails from NZ, which is known, amongst other things, for its
geographical isolation, being some 2,000km from its nearest neighbour,
SE Australia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[2]&lt;/em&gt; See &lt;em&gt;(a)&lt;/em&gt; below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;§1a.&lt;/strong&gt; It is probably appropriate, when writing about a book such as
this, to describe my own mathematical background, which is that I have a
ten-year-old B.Sc in Physics and Electronics, following which I spent a
couple of years using stuff like Fourier and digital domain
transformations fairly heavily, working in R&amp;amp;D on the software analysis
of radar echoes from "non-co-operative targets". Since then, however, my
math usage dropped off pretty much to zero, leading to the present day
in which I find myself so completely rusty that, while I'm happy and
comfortable arm-waving around the concepts &lt;em&gt;[3]&lt;/em&gt;, I'd have
&lt;em&gt;substantial&lt;/em&gt; revision to do in order to be able to coax out any kind of
actually useful derivations &lt;em&gt;[4]&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[3]&lt;/em&gt; For example, I once abandoned an otherwise delightful pub crawl
halfway through, when I received a last-minute invite to attend a math
lecture by Prof. "chaos theory" Mandelbrot across town instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[4]&lt;/em&gt; Beyond the basics, that is. Obviously I could still limp through
some fundamentals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;§2a.&lt;/strong&gt; So, the first thing to relate is that Mr. Wallace's
descriptions of the nature of, and relationships between, all the
&lt;em&gt;transfinites&lt;/em&gt;** brought me genuinely thrilling moments of
heart-racing excitement and revelatory wonder - not once, but several
times. The subject matter is indeed a captivating one, and made all the
more so for me because it covers topics which I have not previously
studied, namely the central one of infinity itself, but also peripheral
ones such as the difficulties the Ancient Greeks had in wresting with
abstraction, as hinted at by their lack of a verb meaning 'to exist'.
This, of course, caused them no end of problems mathematically, which is
arguably nothing but abstractions, and they therefore had problems not
just with infinity, but also with significantly more mundane concepts
such as zero &lt;em&gt;[5]&lt;/em&gt; and irrationals &lt;em&gt;[6]&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[5]&lt;/em&gt; which they didn't have and apparently never missed&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;** due to Cantor, et al,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[6]&lt;/em&gt; which, if I were Bill Bryson, I would describe as "all the
fiddly fractions &lt;em&gt;[7]&lt;/em&gt; that exist in the gaps between the familiar,
round-number fractions*** such as 3/4, 1/8 and 34/978."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[7]&lt;/em&gt; The A.Greeks refused to believe irrationals &lt;em&gt;[6]&lt;/em&gt; existed, and
when they eventually realised that even some of the most basic
measurements from geometry&lt;em&gt;(a)&lt;/em&gt; could not ever be expressed as the ratio
of two whole numbers, it shook their mathematical confidence in ways
from which they arguably never really recovered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(a)&lt;/em&gt; (such as the diagonal of a unit square)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;*** viz. the &lt;em&gt;rationals&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The negatives&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;§2b.&lt;/strong&gt; However, there is one other factor about the book which
&lt;em&gt;(B)&lt;/em&gt; I should probably mention, and that is that I have never, in all
my life, read a document of any description which was as poorly
organised, as haphazardly ordered, and ridiculously and unnecessarily
over-footnoted, as inconsistently titled and annotated and bracketed
by section headings and end-of-section headings, as pointlessly
cross-referenced, and as littered with notes to the effect that his
editor suggested he should make the following changes. It is in the
exact state that I would expect to find it if I had found a first
draft abandoned on a park bench, heavily marked with red biro as the
result of several furious exchanges with an increasingly antagonistic
publisher. And reading an entire paperback of this idiocy almost drove
me BATSHIT SCREAMING INSANE.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;End of the negatives&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(B)&lt;/em&gt; in the interests of fairness&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;§3.&lt;/strong&gt; So there you have it. YMMV. I'm am glad I read it, but god I
found it hard work - not because the math was hard to follow, just
simply because the shambolic prose annoyed the living snot out of me. If
you have a potential interest in the subject matter, and the style of
this review doesn't make your hackles stand on end, then this book is
for you &lt;em&gt;(c)&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(c)&lt;/em&gt; probably&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rating: ∞ x 0. Er... 6?&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>math</category><category>media</category><category>non-fiction</category><category>wallace</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/everything-and-more/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 22 Feb 2007 16:07:17 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>