<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>tartley.com (Posts about completed)</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://www.tartley.com/tags/completed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2026 &lt;a href="mailto:tartley @ tartley dot com"&gt;Jonathan Hartley&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 04:18:28 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Iron Lung</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/iron-lung/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Game by David Szymanski, published 2022&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Movie written, directed, and starring Mark "&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UC7_YxT-KID8kRbqZo7MyscQ"&gt;Markiplier&lt;/a&gt;" Fischbach, released 2026&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Iron Lung" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2026/iron-lung.webp"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style="clear: both"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;New work meeting background just dropped!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Invited to view the movie at Pop's with Phil and Sarah, I crammed the game it
was based on from start to finish the night before, with Zander watching
disdainfully over my shoulder every step of the way. I gave
&lt;a href="https://scp-wiki.wikidot.com/scp-354"&gt;SCP-354&lt;/a&gt;, which inspired the game, a wide
berth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both are tense and engaging, but clearly only for a particular kind of viewer.
The game itself has a very narrow focus, as befits a single-person indie
production. This means you'll only really enjoy it if you're dorky enough to
fixate on the mechanic of cross referencing your submarine's map co-ordinates
sufficiently hard to orient your way around a whole system of underwater
trenches. Every step of the way you negotiate your way past unseen but deadly
canyon walls by dead reckoning alone, a tense enough exercise even without the
proximity alarms. On top of that, strange noises and... other interuptions...
when they drop, are technically relatively tame and limited, but in context,
entwined in the co-ordinate grind, they are experienced as shocking and panic
inducing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Similarly, I enjoyed the movie, but I see reviews are all over the map. Clearly
some don't have patience for its limited scope - 99% of the runtime takes place
with one character in a single room. But I found it taut and thrilling. Some
patches of unclear dialog softened the high-concepts thrown around, but for me
it was always an experience of style and vibes anyway.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>completed</category><category>geek</category><category>media</category><category>movie</category><category>pc</category><category>videogame</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/iron-lung/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 01:55:23 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Tactical Breach Wizards</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/tactical-breach-wizards/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Tactical Breach Wizards screenshot." src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2025/tactical-breach-wizards.lossy.webp"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In this house, we use the metric system. Released in 2024 by Suspicious Developments.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was toying with the idea of advancing the kiddo's videogaming curriculum into
a turn-based tactics phase, maybe starting with the genius of 1994's &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/UFO%3A_Enemy_Unknown"&gt;UFO:Enemy
Unknown&lt;/a&gt;, on which I spent
endlessly fascinated evenings of my youth, or maybe one of the better of its
numerous sequels and offshoots. Somehow I was distracted from that plan by
multiple people enthusing about last year's &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tactical_Breach_Wizards"&gt;Tactical Breach
Wizards&lt;/a&gt;, and I'm so glad
that I was.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is &lt;em&gt;such&lt;/em&gt; a lovely, synergistic blend of gameplay mechanics, setting,
characters, story, plot-twists and whip-smart dialog, making substantial
improvements on the traditional bombastic and yet intensely thoughtful
turn-based formula.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, it defuses the self-righteous seriousness of the genre's customary tone
by replacing the gurning muscle-bound military types with a bunch of special-ops
&lt;em&gt;wizards&lt;/em&gt;. Still formidably competent, but now replete with pointy hats,
hazardous runes, and bejeweled wands protruding from their assault rifle
barrels. Further, while presenting a thrilling facade of enemies dispatched in a
dizzying flurry of rapid-fire magic, the game explicitly disavows wanton
killing. While one of our characters does sneer at the stance, your team is
revealed early-on to use only nonlethal take-downs. This is soon followed up by
a cut-scene which shows your team leaving a building after a mission, revealing
the enemies you earlier dispatched out of eighth floor windows floating gently
earthwards, each safely cocooned in a magical bubble.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, a fundamental mechanic bestows one of your characters with the gift
of magical foresight, allowing you to see the outcome of planned actions before
you actually commit to them. It's a slick narrative integration of a mechanic
that serves multiple purposes. Preventing the anguish of losing a character due
to dumb bad luck means the player is freed up to experiment more, trying
audacious plans rather than playing it safe. Then, when it all goes wrong, you
can rewind just a smidgeon, and try out nearby alternatives, until you have it
all &lt;em&gt;just&lt;/em&gt; right, bouncing generative combos back and forth between characters,
unleashing staggering waves of action, discovering gleefully that a level you
initially thought to be an impossible slog is actually completable in a single
nimble turn. When combined with the inventive diversity of each character's
specific talents, it simultaneously presents real challenges, while allowing the
construction of surprising solutions that leave one feeling feeling incredibly
clever and creative.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's not often worthwhile dwelling on the characters in a videogame, but here
they are the stars of the show. Distinctive, flawed and intensely likeable each
in their own way, with personalities and back-stories that resonate so
pleasingly with their in-game abilities. The writing is just top notch, with
phenomenal dialog, giving the group as a whole a fresh, wholesome and real-talk
vibe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is an all-time classic in my book, and has been fabulous to experience
alongside the 13 year-old kiddo, as we've each run parallel games through to
completion, ogling over each other's shoulders to get sneak previews of
encounters we haven't seen yet.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>completed</category><category>geek</category><category>media</category><category>pc</category><category>videogame</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/tactical-breach-wizards/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 May 2025 21:43:45 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>That Which Gave Chase</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/that-which-gave-chase/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2024/that-which-gave-chase.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Released in 2023, played on Linux in 2024.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="background:#bb2200; color:white; border-radius: 1em; padding-left: 0.5em; padding-right: 0.5em; padding-top: 2px;"&gt;&lt;b&gt;spoilers&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mush your dog sled across cruel Arctic wastelands, driven onwards by a brisk and intense companion, who hired you to take him back to some remote spot, where it becomes apparent he had some sort of revelation, or maybe a breakdown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The low-res, dithered presentation conveys the harsh, blinding conditions, as you struggle to make out details through the relentless wind and ice. The days and nights of the journey blur into one another, leaving you only fragmentary, disjointed memories:
sledding across the ice;
arriving at crude wooden huts for the night;
mounting the sled before dawn;
collapsing into rough bunks; 
righting the sled while your companion curses you for a fool;
silent moments alone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Smash cuts amongst snowy wastes echo &lt;a href="https://readcomic.me/comic/nemo-heart-of-ice/issue-full/31"&gt;the discontinuities in Alan Moore's "&lt;em&gt;Nemo: Heart of Ice&lt;/em&gt;"&lt;/a&gt;, albeit this is a far more understated tale. The sense is of a protracted, exhausting time spent covering the distance, through punishing conditions, and it's surprisingly evocative.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The narrative leans into the disorientation, making nothing clear. Your companion becomes increasingly cryptic. He urges you onward, never pausing more than absolutely necessary. The deer behave increasingly strangely. Your companion regales you with sickening tales of the investigative mistreatment he subjected them to on his previous visit. By the time the strange mushrooms come into play it is very obvious that you are in a place to which you should never have come, very far from anywhere or anyone, with mounting dread, alone with with a madman. What happened the last time he took this route? What did he leave behind here? What awaits at your journey's end?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's hard to know whether the difficulty of interpretation, or the non-literal aspects of your journey, are intended as the result of your character's mushroom-induced fever, or the pretensions of intrusively figurative allusions. Most likely, it seems to be both. The deliberate ambiguity runs deep.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Doesn't outstay its welcome, all done in an hour. But the memories remain.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>completed</category><category>drugs</category><category>geek</category><category>media</category><category>pc</category><category>videogame</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/that-which-gave-chase/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 04 Nov 2024 21:56:38 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Soma</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/soma/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Frictional Games, published 2015&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
![Soma - protagonist](/files/2022/soma-protagonist.webp)
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Soma is a creepy survival horror game, that leans deeply into the moral and
existential quandaries arising from the deterministic principle that it's
possible to scan one's brain and copy the structure into some other substrate,
yielding a second conscious entity, which thinks it is you. So there are deep
science-fiction issues in play here, about whether we think such a scheme could
ever possibly work, and about the practical, personal, and societal
ramifications of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Major &lt;span style="background:#bb2200; color:white; border-radius: 1em; padding-left: 0.5em; padding-right: 0.5em; padding-top: 2px;"&gt;spoilers&lt;/span&gt; ahead. It's seven years old at this point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I loved the setup. A humdrum morning begins in your present-day Toronto
apartment. A note on the fridge reminds you that today is the day of your
medical appointment, a brain scan. Reaching the doctor's office by train, you
find the experimental new type of brain scanner, run by some PhD in a
cable-strewn side-office. Sit in the chair, don the helmet, wait for the scan
to complete and- blink! Suddenly, you are elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the game progresses, it becomes obvious that the version of you that sat
down in the seat did not experience this discontinuity. They completed the
scan, removed the helmet, and continued their normal, everyday life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You are not that copy. You open your eyes to a grim, decrepit cyberpunk future.
Exploring, your only company is a menagerie of half-functional robots and
drones, many of which are insane, and, in conversation, seem to be under the
impression that they are human beings. It gradually becomes apparent that
perceptual filters are in play, preventing them - and you - from noticing they
are no longer human. At one point the ocean crashes in on you, and you drown
for a little while, or at least think you are, but you still don't die. At that
point you have to acknowledge the truth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You have awoken to the year 2104, and the recorded brain scans of real humans
are being used to animate drones. This is a scenario much like that told from a
different perspective in the smashing short story
&lt;a href="https://qntm.org/mmacevedo"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Lena&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; by qntm.
Failing systems engaged fall-backs, resulting in your obsolete brain scan being
yanked from storage to inhabit an advanced humanoid robot, in a facility deep
under the ocean, some time after a comet strike has scoured all life from the
planet's surface.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If that wasn't bad enough, one facilitating technology of this nightmarish
scenario, a black goo that mimics and improves upon electrical and biological
circuitry it comes into contact with, has run rampant, growing probing tendrils
which are wrecking the facility. Among other effects, it has reanimated the
corpses of the last few humans, who skulk around, not in a good way. As our
protagonist asks, incredulously, "You mean they've been brought back to life?".
Our reassuring AI companion replies "Yeah, let's call it that."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The game borrows the highly effective mechanics of Frictional's previous games,
the Amnesia and Penumbra series, where the proximity of horrific, shambling
enemies causes your character to experience debilitating symptoms, including,
in this case, static-y visual distortions as your neural hardware suffers from
some overload or interference. This applies even if you simply look at an
enemy, an act which immediately draws their attention. So your only chance to
survive encounters is to stay well out of sight, and actively avert your eyes
so you can't even watch what's going on. Not being able to see exactly what
your enemies are, or what they are up to, turns out to be fabulously scary and
atmospheric. At one point it lead directly to my wife catching me staring
intently at a blank, black screen for a prolonged period, with a peculiar
expression on my face, as I hid in a dark cupboard waiting for the slithering
sounds behind me to go away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Spurring us through this environment are not just threats to our immediate
survival, but also the adoption of a project, to launch into space a
solar-powered simulation, hosting all the last remaining brain scans of the
now-defunct human race, known as the 'ARK'. This will allow the on-board sims
to live a prolonged period of idyllic virtual existence, preserving at least
some echo of what humanity was. Since the conceit of the game is that our
character is a living and conscious entity that feels real emotion, the sims on
the ARK are all presumably the same, so this seems like a worthwhile endeavor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are guided, motivated, and assisted by "Catherine", a simulated personality
running on our hand-held omni-tool, based on the brain recording of an AI
researcher, whose project during her lifetime was the ARK. Plugging her in to a
wall or console socket lets her interface with our surroundings, activating
power supplies and manipulating machinery. She leads us through a series of
undersea facilities, linked by trains, submersibles, and the occasional
disorienting trudge across the murky ocean floor, stirred up by ferocious
currents and landslides, populated by organic-mechanical hybrid horrors that
glide by in the darkness. I found these some of the absolute best, most
atmospheric "walking simulator" moments I've experienced in a game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
![The ocean floor, stirred up by currents and landslides](/files/2022/soma-murky.webp)
&lt;br&gt;Is that another distant light up ahead? Good luck finding them while the currents pummel you,
and hideous, deadly beasts loom out of the murk.
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Along the way, we encounter a few unforgettable scenarios. We come across the
failing storage system in which the last remaining copy of our own brain scan
resides. I decide to flip some buttons which delete it, prompting my character
to respond with something like "Let this be the last time I wake up in this
godforsaken place."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At another point, we find ourselves trapped within a collapsing facility on the
bottom of the ocean, with the gibbering undead hammering on the door from the
next room. There is an airlock leading out into the ocean, but we would be
crushed at this depth. There is no way out. Luckily, Catherine is able to guide
us into assembling a more robust robot, one capable of withstanding the
pressure - all we have to do is sit in the chair and activate the transfer into
it. We already did this once, back in Toronto. Easy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Except, after the transfer, we glance back across the lab at our original - the
pictured chap with red LED eyes - who, we notice, is still breathing. Asking
Catherine about it, she reminds us that the brain scan is not a destructive
operation. He's still in there, chemically subdued for the moment, but he'll
soon wake up again, wondering why the transfer didn't work. So we are left with
the option of stomping out of the airlock to safety, leaving him behind to his
nightmarish fate. Or flipping a switch to deactivate him before we go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lot of these narrative beats work better as a game than they perhaps might in
a written story. They emphasize the player's complicity, your moral
culpability, which is a mode that games, for all their faults, can do better
than any other media. Plenty of the lesser moments along the way expose the
player to decisions about unplugging some human simulation or other which
declares itself to be "alive", but which is gating your progress in some way.
Some of them are yourself. Some of these acts require manhandling weighty
cables, which require large, insistent tugging with the mouse controls. It's
not just a disembodied button press. One has to provide a determined,
definitive, mechanical input to end a life. In context, the guilt feels real.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Later in the journey, we finally stumble across an honest-to-goodness real,
live human being. She describes how the rest of the humans will be gathered in
particular locations, while she stayed to protect the ARK. But, we tell her, we
just passed through those locations, and there were no humans remaining there.
We both know that the planet's surface is sterile. A beat passes before she
announces "So I'm the last human being left alive." She's deathly sick, and
without hope. By the end of your interactions she asks you to turn off her
life-support before you leave, and stay with her for her last wheezing moments.
So this is how humanity ends.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Carrying on, because what else is there to do? We finally we get the ARK loaded
into the launch system that delivers it to orbit, upload our brain scans onto
it just before it launches, and - we've done it! Success!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was a moment, about five minutes before the end, when I realized what was
going to happen here, even though my character had not. It was a real emotional
blow. I envied and pitied him for his naive hope. For believing there was still
a way out. For, of course, the ARK's launch changed nothing for us. Our
simulations are aboard it, but we are still sitting here, in a broken robot
corpse in a collapsing facility at the bottom of a haunted ocean on a dead
planet. The dispatched copy will enjoy life on the ARK, but we - like the copy
of ourselves we left behind earlier - are stuck here for good. Roll credits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>completed</category><category>geek</category><category>media</category><category>pc</category><category>videogame</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/soma/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 04 Oct 2022 18:51:16 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Infra</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/infra/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2024/infra.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Released in 2016, played by me on Linux in 2022.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So much to love about this game. My enjoyment was perhaps stoked by my initial
expectation that such a humdrum, non-mainstream game idea - of a civil engineer
performing building inspections, documenting elements such as cracks and exposed
rebar - must surely be a modest indie offering. But that expectation was vastly
exceeded by the overwhelming generosity of the included content, providing level
after level after level, all rich in geometry and atmosphere, navigable pathways
surrounded by loads of non-essential scene setting, from broom cupboards to
passing container ships, replete with specially coded set-pieces, and a story
that expands in scope beyond all possible initial expectations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is filled with puzzles that are grounded in the atmospheric setting, having
me clamber under cobweb-strewn desks with a flashlight, looking for tripped
circuit breakers. The setting itself builds beautifully, starting with my
inspection of bridges and decrepit sawmills as I wander along a small overgrown
river path, but increasing in scope and severity as we continue downstream into
town, culminating in varied and ambitious city facilities, from water treatment
plants, abandoned sprawling secret WWI facilities, and various types of railway
and power stations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The puzzle difficulty is perfectly judged, demanding about the limit of effort I
could bring to bear, and only on one or two occasions did I give up and find
solutions online, leading overall to a tremendous sense of accomplishment. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The storyline exposes longstanding secretive corruption in the city, explaining
both the pervasive neglect and sabotage that your inspections reveal, and it
provides a variety of creative reasons why the buildings on your route are
either long-abandoned, or else hastily evacuated moments before your arrival.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This gives you gloriously free reign over the facilities you pass through,
opening up possibilities to perform ad-hoc repairs as you go. In particular, I
particularly loved the way a successful navigation of levels like the water
treatment plant requires the player to cross reference wall charts showing how
the plant operates, with computer schematics showing the state of various
machinery and valves, and overlay on top of that an understanding of a few signs
and hand-written notes left behind by operators, to remind themselves about
proper operating procedures, broken equipment, workarounds, and switches that
were wired up backwards. And once you figure out this abstract understanding of
what needs to be done, you have to map it all onto the actual 3D spatial layout
of the massive hardware all around you, which often spans multiple buildings.
Just delightful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I should probably also mention the penultimate level, which is one of the most
ambitious of many bold experiments that keep the levels diverse and surprising,
by straying away from the core conceit. In this case that means navigating the
locked-down hallways of an alternative, mushroom obsessed commune, squatting in
a depressing tower block surrounded by trash. While this level is laudable for
being the boldest of these experiments, and represents an important pillar of
the narrative, an alternate society dropping out from the dysfunction induced in
the city by the main story line. However, it didn't quite land for me, and I
soon consulted an online walkthrough, without which I think I would have been
trudging its grimy corridors for a long and dispiriting time. As it was, in
contrast to the entire rest of the game, I was pleased to get it done as quickly
as possible and move on without getting into its optional exploration and
side-quests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But other than that one level, I &lt;em&gt;loved&lt;/em&gt; this game, and played it with a passion
and obsession that burned fiercely for weeks.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>completed</category><category>drugs</category><category>geek</category><category>media</category><category>pc</category><category>videogame</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/infra/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 07 Aug 2022 20:43:24 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Journey</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/journey/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2022/journey-screenshot.webp"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Released on PlayStation 3 by thatgamecompany in 2012. Played on Windows 10 in
2022.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The slow-paced opening scenes, alternately trudging up and then surfing down
sunbaked desert dunes, failed to sustain Zander's interest, so I ended up
playing through its short runtime by myself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In some ways it's an indictment of videogame culture that ten years later it
still feels so fresh and radical to pair players up with another internet
rando, while giving them no means to communicate or interact other than helping
each other out, either leading by example, or exchanging wordless shouts. It
seems like a pretty limited repertoire at first. I'm half tempted to just wander
off ahead, alone, into the endless desert.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, you realize that standing close enough together recharges each other's
magical flying scarves. Suddenly, it's enough. You cling to each other for dear
life through the howling storms, double back to rescue each other from prowling
beasts, and then fly exuberantly above the sunlit clouds, forever curving back
to seek each other's life-giving sustenance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don't know who the two internet randos were, with whom I shared the first and
second halves of my journey. But in those minutes together, we lived a
lifetime's worth.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>completed</category><category>geek</category><category>media</category><category>pc</category><category>videogame</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/journey/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 09 May 2022 11:22:20 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Subnautica: Below Zero</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/subnautica-below-zero/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;PC, published 2021&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="background:#bb2200; color:white; border-radius: 1em; padding-left: 0.5em; padding-right: 0.5em; padding-top: 2px;"&gt;&lt;b&gt;spoilers&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/span&gt;, obviously. This is a map of an area in the game, revealing many of its secrets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://subnautica.fandom.com/wiki/Subnautica_Wiki"&gt;Subnautica&lt;/a&gt;,
and its icy sequel,
"&lt;a href="https://subnautica.fandom.com/wiki/Subnautica:_Below_Zero"&gt;Below Zero&lt;/a&gt;",
have perhaps been my favorite
games of the last few years. The majority of their run time takes place under
the colorful waters of an alien ocean. It's been a joy to sit side-by-size
with Zander for tense scuba cave dives, or piloting vehicles through
vertiginous underwater cave systems, headlights straining through the murk to
reveal wonders. It has inspired
&lt;a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/Subnautica_Below_Zero/comments/r82l3i/birthday_cake_no_spoilers/"&gt;cake&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Part of the games take place on land though. I &lt;em&gt;started&lt;/em&gt; drawing a map of Below
Zero's Glacial Basin region just to keep track of where we'd been. To make sure
we visited all the locations, found all the MacGuffins (I'm looking at &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt;,
pesky antidote), and experienced all that there was to experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But as those goals approached completion, I &lt;em&gt;finished&lt;/em&gt; drawing it because it
had become a therapeutic experience. Happily exploring away, mesmerised by the
scenery, avoiding hostile wildlife, uncovering the ruins of ancient alien
artifacts. Reckoning distances by eye, scribbling down what we found, updating
and correcting the map as we went. Being lost in the experience. Simply a joy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/Subnautica_Below_Zero/comments/qutkqz/hand_drawn_map_of_southern_glacial_region_wip/"&gt;Reddit is encouraging me&lt;/a&gt;
to tackle the tricky Actic Spires area, too. &lt;em&gt;&amp;lt;Rubs hands&amp;gt;...&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Subnautica screenshot" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2021/subnatica-below-zero-map-glacial-basin.png"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: left"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>completed</category><category>geek</category><category>map</category><category>media</category><category>pc</category><category>videogame</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/subnautica-below-zero/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 22 Nov 2021 22:24:22 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Manifold Garden</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/manifold-garden/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Manifold Garden screenshot" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2021/manifold-garden.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Windows, 2019&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was always going to turn my head, marrying a marvellous geometric engine
to an austere, flat-shaded renderer. Bewildering portals, seamlessly disguised
as humble doorways, are the simplest of its tricks. More pervasive, levels are
wraparound along all three spatial dimensions, as can be seen by the
disorienting arrays of geometry - the current level, infinitely repeated,
offset or re-oriented - marching to the vanishing points, dwindling to infinity
in all directions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is no mere trippy backdrop. Gravity can be trivially flipped to lie along
any cardinal axis, and one will routinely step off, into a yawning, infinite
abyss, to fall through the entire level, and beyond, through and amongst the
infinite constellations of geometry, airsteering all the way, to land,
unharmed, anywhere that's exposed to the direction you're falling from. It
becomes a form of teleportation, used to get from A to B almost as frequently
as simply walking around.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This non-Euclidean wrapping is baked deeply into the visuals, the engine, and
the gameplay. But for all that technical mastery, the puzzles themselves aren't
as deep and creative and varied as those in the ostensibly similar, but
less technically accomplished, &lt;em&gt;Antichamber&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having said that, there's something entirely appropriate in this. The puzzles
end up being as much rituals as a head-scratchers, holy spatial rites one
performs to unleash the deeply evocative visuals towards the end of each level
- a faceted and angular psychedelic, coupled with unnerving reformulations of
reality straight out of Farbrausch's
&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=wqu_IpkOYBg"&gt;Debris&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. By the final level,
this crescendos in scenes reminiscent of &lt;em&gt;2001: A Space Odyssey&lt;/em&gt;, profound in
both the intimacy of my commune with godhood, and in my continued inability to
understand what I had achieved. Created a universe, probably? Yeah, probably.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>completed</category><category>geek</category><category>media</category><category>pc</category><category>videogame</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/manifold-garden/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 05 Oct 2021 03:16:08 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Legend of Zelda : The Phantom Hourglass</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/legend-of-zelda-the-phantom-hourglass/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Phantom Hourglass" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2008/05/phantom-hourglass.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nintendo, 2008&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nintendo spin off a &lt;em&gt;fourteenth&lt;/em&gt; iteration of the familiar and
oh-so-beloved franchise. I'd only previously played the
preposterously-sub-titled &lt;em&gt;Ocarina of Time&lt;/em&gt; on the N64, of which I
retain fond, sepia-coloured memories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I found &lt;em&gt;Phantom Hourglass&lt;/em&gt; to be engaging, and played it to a
thoroughly jolly completion over the course of a couple of months. The
gameplay and plot are a tad more casual and lightweight than &lt;em&gt;Ocarina&lt;/em&gt;,
as befitting play snatched while on-the-go on the handheld platform.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using the DS stylus to control Link is delightfully transparent and
intuitive. Just as for a mouse, however, expert users will eventually
eschew it for many actions, preferring the speed, precision and
tactility of distinct physical buttons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the down side, some of the puzzles are downright contrived. After
introducing a handy little map, on which you can scrawl notes and
reminders for yourself, the game then promptly takes it away again for
&lt;em&gt;exactly&lt;/em&gt; the levels on which it would be of most use, proclaiming 'you
can't use the map here, some sort of magic prevents it.' Right. Up
yours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Equally intrusive, the dialog is entirely Nintendo-esque cutesy Japanese
schmultz, and it would have improved the game no end for it to have been
entirely absent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Such niggles are few and far between, though. Time for another go of the
newfangled rating system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rating: Place yourself somewhere between...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;10/10 if you're into a deftly executed handheld riff on the Zelda
series, beautifully integrated with the affordances and sensibilities of
the hosting hardware in that way that only Nintendo can do. Lots to love
here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;0/10 if you're done with revisiting timeworn ideas, even ones as
compelling and charming as this, and yearn for a resurgence in
experimental originality to kick the gaming industry out of one or two
ruts (such as having a blind spot for crappy dialog.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: both"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>completed</category><category>ds</category><category>geek</category><category>media</category><category>videogame</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/legend-of-zelda-the-phantom-hourglass/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2009 20:36:05 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Shadow of the Colossus</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/shadow-of-the-colossus/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2009/01/sotc4-300x225.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Team ICO, PS2, 2005.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As is common for a title released in the autumn years of a console's
lifetime, the programmers at Team ICO have mastered the PS2 hardware,
and wring the utmost from it for this virtuoso performance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The gameplay consists of nothing more than a series of sixteen boss
fights between your character and a succession of gigantic mythical
creatures, each rising from the landscape upon your approach. Half
stone, half furry flesh, these colossi shake the earth as they walk, and
facing up to them, armed with nothing but a sword and a bow, elicits a
genuine rush of fear, firstly as their size and magnificence become
apparent, then as they stand up, and then, finally, terrifyingly, as
they &lt;em&gt;see you&lt;/em&gt;. Like moments from a piercing dream, playing this game is
an experience that will not be forgotten.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's in this emotive ability that the game's strength lies, and the
initial adrenaline is only the most coarse example of it. Those disposed
to gallop directly in the hinted direction of the the next objective
would be missing out on large parts of what &lt;em&gt;Colossus&lt;/em&gt; has to offer, and
would be well advised to ease back, enjoy the view, and take some
pleasure from the journey. For fully half your time will be spent
traversing this epic landscape in search of your next quarry, and the
landscape is fantastic, in every sense. Across open plains, rent by
canyons and gorges spanned by ancient, elegant arches, past thundering
waterfalls, though shafts of sunlight across boulder-strewn forest
floors. Cutting through mighty, vine-covered ruins, now occupied only by
lizards and hawks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This tranquil exploration is punctuated by the excitement of the
battles, forming a delightful sense of anticipation. The battles
themselves are gripping and rewarding, and provides a enough of a
challenge to stimulate a corresponding level of victorious elation upon
bringing down each of the colossi. Interestingly, as the game
progresses, the tone of the animations and solemn music begin to subtly
expose these victories for what they are: the slaughter of a magical,
unique and irreplaceable creature, leaving the world a more forlorn and
empty place. This effectively leverages the player's third-person
complicity in the killings, eventually evoking feelings of guilt for
your premeditated attacks on your ultimately vulnerable victims.
Reflective of your character's determination, heedlessly pursuing an
outcome that is hinted at in his own deteriorating appearance, you have
no choice but to carry on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overlaid on this evolving cyclic structure, a delicate narrative is
unobtrusively woven, complete with possibly the most affecting death of
a character in any videogame to date. The story culminates by
exquisitely dovetailing with the opening of the game &lt;em&gt;Ico&lt;/em&gt; (PS2, Team
Ico, 2001), making this &lt;em&gt;Ico'&lt;/em&gt;s prequel (and finally explaining that
game's protagonist's stigmatic horns.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've said it before and I'll say it again. Videogames are a nascent,
immature medium. None amongst us can so much as dream of what they will
one day be capable of. Look upon works such as this as history in the
making, the first time a human has wrought a creative endeavour such as
this, pushing forward the expectations and outlook of the whole
industry, and spellbinding a generation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alright, we're done here. You may leave. Time for me to begin my
experiments with a new subjectivity-proof rating system:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rating: Position yourself appropriately somewhere between:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;10/10 if you wish to enjoy the state of the art in what videogames as a
medium are capable of.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;0/10 if you are incapable of appreciating beauty or have no soul.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: both"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>completed</category><category>geek</category><category>media</category><category>ps2</category><category>videogame</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/shadow-of-the-colossus/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2009 01:33:59 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>