<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>tartley.com (Posts about fantasy)</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://www.tartley.com/tags/fantasy.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2025 &lt;a href="mailto:tartley @ tartley dot com"&gt;Jonathan Hartley&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 26 May 2025 23:19:06 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>The Witch's Heart</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/the-witches-heart/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="The Witch's Heart cover" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2022/the-witchs-heart-cover.webp"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Genevieve Gornichec, 2021.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Old Norse mythology only briefly mentions the witch
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Angrbo%C3%B0a"&gt;Angrboða&lt;/a&gt;,
as the mother of three "monsters", fathered by the trickster god, Loki. This
book explores her life, explicitly acknowledging her erasure as a woman, and
resolves it, providing her a powerful story, in which she survives men, gods,
and all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another fantastic Suze recommendation. Loved it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also this month: &lt;em&gt;The Emperess of Salt and Fortune&lt;/em&gt; by Nghi Vo. I wanted to
like this sooo much, and can see so many things about that are wonderful, but
for some reason I just couldn't get in the mood. The problem is indubitably me,
not you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: left"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>fantasy</category><category>fiction</category><category>media</category><category>myth</category><category>novel</category><category>science-fiction</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/the-witches-heart/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 20 Mar 2022 03:43:53 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Circe</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/circe/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Circe cover" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2022/circe-cover.webp"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Madeline Miller, 2018.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recommended by The Suze, after reading it for one of her book clubs,
and I absolutely loved it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tells the life story of the mythical Circe of the ancient Greek pantheon.
Daughter of Helios, mightiest of the Titans, Circe is driven from her family by
their capricious cruelty. She puts her meagre supernatural talents to work in
service of witchcraft, amongst mortals. Along the way she meets many well-known
mythological characters, such as Odysseus, and the Cretean Minotaur.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was the writing style that captivated me. A timeless, elegant style uses
powerful turns of phrase to spin a tale of drama and high passions, soaked
in the psychological resonances so typical of Greek mythology.
This style, along with the setting, reminded me powerfully of another favourite
couple of novels of recent years, Mary Renault's absolutely fabulous &lt;em&gt;The King
Must Die&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;The Bull From the Sea&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Circe is my favorite book of the year so far, beating out even the marvellous
&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.tartley.com/posts/klara-and-the-sun"&gt;Klara and the Sun&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: left"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>fantasy</category><category>fiction</category><category>media</category><category>myth</category><category>novel</category><category>science-fiction</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/circe/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 20 Mar 2022 03:14:53 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Three Parts Dead</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/three-parts-dead/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Three Parts Dead cover" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2021/three-parts-dead-cover.webp"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Max Gladstone (2012).&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A loveable romp. Technical witchcraft. Lawyerly magic wielders. Murdered gods.
What's not to like?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But will I continue with the series? I think... not. Which is actually a good
thing - there are just
&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/189147.To_Your_Scattered_Bodies_Go"&gt;so&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/968902.Dying_Inside"&gt;many&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/26187256-the-thing-itself"&gt;other&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/36836025-the-electric-state"&gt;things&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/25372801-all-the-birds-in-the-sky"&gt;I'm&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/42036538-gideon-the-ninth"&gt;dying&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/13821.Lord_of_Light"&gt;to&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/13259270-free-will"&gt;read&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/50202953-piranesi"&gt;right&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/31379914-the-collapsing-empire"&gt;now&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: left"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>fantasy</category><category>media</category><category>novel</category><category>science-fiction</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/three-parts-dead/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 16 Dec 2021 05:16:46 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Buried Giant</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/the-buried-giant/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="The Buried Giant cover" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2021/the-buried-giant-cover.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Kazuo Ishiguro, 2015&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A mythical tale, set in post-Arthurian England. Author Kazuo Ishiguro, Nobel
prize winner for literature, is also famous for Klara and the Sun, Never Let
Me Go, and The Remains of the Day (yes, that one about butlers.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ishiguro moved from Japan to England as a young child, and his insightful
observation of English and Western culture and myth benefits from that
transplant's perspective - at once deeply at home in England, and also
an outsider to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="background:#bb2200; color:white; border-radius: 1em; padding-left: 0.5em; padding-right: 0.5em; padding-top: 2px;"&gt;spoilers&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The tale is populated by ragged peoples, affected by a pervasive amnesia.
Elderly couple Axl and Beatrice abruptly decide to leave their village of damp,
hobbit-like underground burrows to visit a son they'd forgotten they had.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Simlarly, other characters are inspired by a variety of classical sources, from
Beowulf to Arthur's knight and nephew Sir Gawain, now old and prone to quixotic
rants - hinting at the subconscious conflict his code of honor has with the
dark means by which he and other knights formerly helped Arthur achieve the
current uneasy peace between native Britons and invading Saxons, now occupying
villages across the land.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The journey is perilous, encountering roaming ogres and deadly pixies, not
to mention soldiers of the local lords, and deadly conflicts within the party
itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But any action is relayed with cool distance. Either through the pervasive
mental fog, or using expert fighters' clinical analysis of the minutia of
stance or grip, or by foretelling the ebb and flow of a battle by analysing the
terrain, then allowing the battle itself to take place off stage, only assumed
to have happened, by characters who weren't there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This muted indirectness is entirely in keeping with the ambiguous, dreamlike
style of the book, which is heightened by the sing-song formalism of the
characters' medieval speech, and the narrator's occasional surreal hint of
relating this tale to contemporaries who live in some other, unidentifiable,
historic time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The journey eventually comes to revolve around the dispatch - or defence - of a
dragon that is said to be the source of everyone's forgetfulness, and as this
goal approaches, vague fears surface of what might be remembered when the
mist lifts. Will Axl and Beatrice's treasured relationship survive the
revelations of their pasts? Will the longstanding truce in the land survive
the remembering of wartime battles and atrocities? Will Saxon resentment at
Arthur's desperate misdeeds be stoked into resumption of the violent war of
invasion? This is left unresolved by the novel's end, but as reader, we know
that the Saxons did ultimately conquer all of England, displacing the Britons
culturally and politically, and probably murdering a good number of them along
the way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Personally, I'm minded to think of ancient England here as being a root of
modern Western culture, and the mist as an allegory for the bland ignorance of
our own culture's atrocities. The deliberate forgetting, like the mist, clouds
all our conciousnesses, making it hard for us to remember who we are. Why we're
here. The silent resentment of crushed minorities and genocide survivors forms
a pressure, struggling against the placating narrative that everything's OK
now. But, contained, the pressure builds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Truly a buried giant, indeed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: left"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>fantasy</category><category>fiction</category><category>ishiguro</category><category>media</category><category>myth</category><category>novel</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/the-buried-giant/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 25 Oct 2021 15:16:53 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Someone Comes to Town, Someone Leaves Town</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/someone-comes-to-town-someone-leaves-town/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Someone Comes to Town, Someone Leaves Town" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2008/02/someone-comes-to-town.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Cory Doctorow&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I just don't know about this one. I really wanted to like it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="background:#bb2200; color:white; border-radius: 1em; padding-left: 0.5em; padding-right: 0.5em; padding-top: 2px;"&gt;&lt;b&gt;spoilers&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It starts out with an interesting, down-to-earth story about a guy establishing
himself in a new neighbourhood, setting up an open wireless mesh net across the
neighbourhood, back in a day when this was still a &lt;em&gt;really cool idea&lt;/em&gt;. This
tale is then peppered with initially disconcerting non-literal sounding
references to his family, such as the cliffs and caves of his Father, the
mountain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps I embarked upon it too casually. It was certainly engaging, but
by the last few pages I began to suspect that threads of the plot had
eluded me. For example, I had entertained the idea that the fantasy
elements of the story were actually the product of the main character's
stated intention to write a book, which is otherwise only mentioned in
passing here and there. However, the fantasy is woven extremely tightly
together with the realistic aspects of the story, such that I can't
discern any clear boundary to distinguish between the two. So I'm left
wondering if parts of the book didn't actually happen, and if so, which
parts? I should have anticipated someone like &lt;a href="http://craphound.com"&gt;Mr
Doctorow&lt;/a&gt; would have to be a terrific smarty-pants
in the narrative department, and I doubtless should have paid more
attention along the way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rating: 6/10 - One to revisit, maybe, if I like his other stuff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update 12th Feb:&lt;/strong&gt; Coincidentally, I just read a short story by Cory,
&lt;em&gt;I Row-boat&lt;/em&gt;, which despite the awful titular pun, I really liked.
However, I've read a bunch of discussion about &lt;em&gt;Someone Comes to
Town...&lt;/em&gt;, and I don't seem to have missed much that anyone else has been
getting out of it. So while I'm looking forward to other stuff by him,
I'm sticking by my personal low enjoyment of this one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: both"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>doctorow</category><category>fantasy</category><category>fiction</category><category>media</category><category>novel</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/someone-comes-to-town-someone-leaves-town/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 08 Feb 2008 07:01:37 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>