<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>tartley.com (Posts about fiction)</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://www.tartley.com/tags/fiction.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2025 &lt;a href="mailto:tartley @ tartley dot com"&gt;Jonathan Hartley&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 31 Jan 2025 05:36:59 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Ferris Bueller's Day Off</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/ferris-buellers-day-off/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Ben Stein in Ferris Bueller's Day Off" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2023/ferris-bueller.webp"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Directed and written by John Hughes, 1986.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0091042"&gt;IMDB&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, way back in my teen years, we had a VHS tape of this, which friends and I
played and played and played, probably racking up more rewatches than any other
movie in my life. So it was a pleasure to break it out for our 11 year-old,
some some 37 years later (!), to see whether it still holds up, and find that
it really does.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By chance this was the week after we'd just watched &lt;em&gt;The Blues Brothers&lt;/em&gt;, so we
got to compare and contrast two movies set in Chicago - a privileged white
story, and a poverty stricken, largely colored one, which even share scenes
filmed in the very same restaurant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back then, I had no idea who Ben Stein was, so it was amusing to see him now
and suddenly join the dots. Apparently his infamous "voodoo economics" speech
had no script and was ad-libbed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reviewing Rooney's comical attempts to break into the Buellers' house made me
realize for the first time that this was Hughes' dry-run at what would become
&lt;em&gt;Home Alone&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had always been frustrated that I'd never been able to lay my hands on the
"&lt;em&gt;You're not dying&lt;/em&gt;" song that Cameron plays while sick in his bedroom (i.e. here's the few seconds
of it
&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6mcFGW0RjAo&amp;amp;t=70s&amp;amp;autoplay=1"&gt;on Youtube&lt;/a&gt;,
exactly as it appears in the movie.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now we have the Internet, I can see that this failure wasn't exactly my fault -
there is no such song. The few bars we hear were whipped up by Ira Newborn
specially for the film, based on an old Louis Armstrong song,
&lt;a href="https://youtu.be/fHbC8Nhd46s?autoplay=1"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Let My People Go&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Fortunately for us,
one man was obsessed about it enough to actually recreate a full length
song based on the snippets from the movie. Here is Daniel Simone's
&lt;a href="https://youtu.be/MDEXlOk_suM?autoplay=1"&gt;Let My Cameron Go&lt;/a&gt;,
full of a lush Pink Floyd sound, and ripe with the sort of ecstatic
anticipation that even Roger Waters would be proud of.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Duly &lt;a href="https://www.tartley.com/posts/download-audio-from-youtube/"&gt;added to my rotation&lt;/a&gt; for next time I'm sick.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update:&lt;/strong&gt; Dany Boyd's CinemaStix posted &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/DaMimdNNnAw?si=diaI1lde64EL7OPE"&gt;a lovely YouTube about how Ferris isn't the main
character of this movie&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: left"&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>comedy</category><category>fiction</category><category>media</category><category>movie</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/ferris-buellers-day-off/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 27 Sep 2023 15:01:22 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Resolution and The Endless</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/resolution-and-the-endless/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Resolution" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2023/resolution.webp"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt1977895"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Resolution (2012)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="The Endless" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2023/the-endless.webp"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt3986820"&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Endless (2017)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I only had a hazy awareness of Justin Benson and Aaron Moorhead, the writer
and directors, before watching these movies. But having discovered them, I now
realize that they are doing just about my favorite thing in film: Quirky,
intense, psychological drama wound around some high concept science fiction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Going in, I hadn't realized the two films are related. But then they contain
the same scene, viewed from two different angles (pictured above), and it
starts to become clearer. As it happens, I watched them out of order - my
enthusiasm for &lt;em&gt;The Endless&lt;/em&gt; caused me to look up their earlier &lt;em&gt;Resolution&lt;/em&gt;.
But with hindsight, I think this is actually the best order to view them. If
&lt;em&gt;Resolution&lt;/em&gt; has a weakness, it's that the science fictional elements seem a
bit arbitrary. Why should this supernatural entity focus its narrative-obsessed
attentions on these two men, here in this cabin, out in the middle of nowhere?
But in &lt;em&gt;The Endless&lt;/em&gt;, this particular brand of supernatural outlandishness is
revealed to be just part of a wider pattern, affecting many people in this
geographical area. Although this is the bigger, weirder story, it is more fully
fleshed out and becomes more believable, creating a setting which
recontextualizes and improves the earlier film.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rating: 10/10 if you like mindbending SF horror, 0/10 if you prefer something a
bit more polished and comfortable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>fiction</category><category>media</category><category>movie</category><category>science-fiction</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/resolution-and-the-endless/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 22 Sep 2023 19:12:24 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Aurora</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/aurora/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Aurora cover" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2023/aurora.webp"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Kim Stanley Robinson, 2015&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It has long been held by fans of science fiction that &lt;em&gt;fantasy&lt;/em&gt; is a lowly
subset of science-fiction, or perhaps a disreputable cousin, one for whom
the normal rules of discernment do not apply. If such unlikely and unrealistic
things as dragons and magic are allowed, the reasoning goes, then the book
cannot be relied upon to deliver any kind of coherent narrative experience,
since the lapsed rule-set now allows for any old &lt;em&gt;ex machina&lt;/em&gt; plot twists to
save the day. A magical "defeat the evil" spell? No problem. A new mythical
creature capable of defeating the previously unassailable one? Why not? All
reason is gone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's more useful though, is to invert the hierarchy of this received wisdom,
and consider science fiction as a subset of fantasy. Mentioning this in fandom
circles blows mental fuses. Does not compute. But the speculative flights of
science fiction are also fantasies. Just fantasies that a particular type of
person finds especially beguiling, compelling, and believable. To some extent,
I concede that on occasion they are believable because they seem to be a
reasonable extrapolation of our current situation. But no matter how reasonable
your extrapolation seems to be, it's always possible that reality will zig
instead of zag, and even the most humdrum tale of a rocket man's life will
find itself at odds with the unexpected reality of suspended human spaceflight
in the face of spiraling real-world costs. The vision that one is selling is
always, to a greater or lesser extent, a wishful one - a &lt;em&gt;fantasy&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This becomes immediately apparent once we stray beyond the confines of low
Earth orbit, to take in the wider scope of science fiction, the vast majority
of which encompasses tales across the galaxy, nay, the universe, including time
travel, teleportation booths, aliens of every color, quantum reality
displacement, and multiversal escapades in which literally everything is
possible. These are very clearly fantasies, and it is intensely curious to me
why this sort of fantasy is considered more "realistic" or "believable" than,
say, flying lizards with fiery breath. Even though the narrative hand-waving
that explains away the former - "It's an alternate &lt;em&gt;universe&lt;/em&gt;, where different
rules apply" - is abundantly adequate to more than completely explain anything
in the fantasy realm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I once asked my guru science fiction critic &lt;a href="https://damiengwalter.com/podcast/"&gt;Damien
Walter&lt;/a&gt; what makes people consider some
stories believable, while other are not. He replied with a statement that has
stuck with me ever since: People are willing to invest the effort to provide
the conceptual scaffolding around an idea to make it seem believable (e.g. to
speculate on the mechanism that might allow for a faster-than-light
hyper-drive) &lt;em&gt;when the story fulfills some deeper psychological need for them&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hence, a story on the same topic as &lt;em&gt;Aurora&lt;/em&gt;, of a generation ship sent to
colonize an Earth-like planet orbiting the nearby star of Tau Ceti, is
(usually) a story about the triumph of modernism. Such stories leverage the
sources of strength in the modern world, science and technology and
&lt;em&gt;colonialism&lt;/em&gt;, and a reader who is invested in a modern world-view will feel
validated and empowered by this type of fantasy. They will be will be willing
to exercise whatever extracurricular creative effort is required on the part of
the reader to make the story believable. Doing so will inspire them with the
feeling that their world all makes sense, is leading to something, so that
their daily grind is a part of the heroic story of how humanity transcends its
planetary origins. This is much more fulfilling than investing any effort
getting on board with the waning powers of superstition that are represented by
the fantasy genre.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="background:#bb2200; color:white; border-radius: 1em; padding-left: 0.5em; padding-right: 0.5em; padding-top: 2px;"&gt;&lt;b&gt;spoilers&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In keeping with this, Aurora's colonists are granted every conceivable boon
that science and industry can supply. A ship fully ten kilometers across,
enclosing twenty four massive biomes, each stuffed full of hills and lakes,
soil and forests, microbes and wildlife. A population of well over a thousand
human beings. Miraculous nanotech fabricators, and megatons of elemental
feedstock to run them. A miraculous acceleration laser, fired from Titan for
decades after departure, allowing the ship to coast up to 0.1c, making the
journey in only seven generations, while retaining enough fuel to decelerate
for arrival. A miraculous magnetic shield protects the ship from catastrophic
collisions with stray particles along the way. A benign AI runs the ship,
amusingly pressed into service as the narrator of the tale, and grows visibly
more sentient, emotionally robust and capable as the years pass.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And hot damn, they are going to &lt;em&gt;need&lt;/em&gt; all these things, because in this story,
human interstellar colonization is revealed for the fantasy it really is.
Nothing works out, and the problems encountered are far bigger than anything
the ship's designers planned for. Although the ship does limp into orbit
around the destination planet, soon after that people start dying, major
disagreements emerge which descend into catastrophic riots, and the ship's
society falls apart - when have humans ever invented a reliable form of
governance?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a rip-roaring final act, that stretched my credulity, but revives the
stakes and entertainment value in what might otherwise be a relentless downer
of a read.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book, and interviews with the author, caused quite a stir in science
fiction circles. People were extremely angry. The book was attacking their
deeply held beliefs that the future of humanity is as a successfull
space-faring species. They had invested their identity in this world-view,
because of how it serviced their psychological needs for fulfillment and
meaning. They had developed a religious conviction around this particular kind
of fantasy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The point of Aurora is to highlight the idea of human interstellar colonization
as a dangerous distraction from the very real project of taking care of the
long term health of our planet and our society right here on Earth. It is going
to take &lt;em&gt;beyond&lt;/em&gt; miraculous levels of technology and resources to start
thinking about interstellar travel. If, by some miracle, we make it to a year
10,000 utopia, with infinite resources and the wisdom to manage them, then
sure, we can worry about interstellar travel. But for now, can we just focus on
some of the very basic problems of existence here on Earth, like how to make
everyone fed and liberated, educated and fulfilled, without killing our planet
to do it? Maybe invent some sort of government that is reliably able to do
that? That would be nice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: left"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>fiction</category><category>media</category><category>novel</category><category>science-fiction</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/aurora/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 21 Sep 2023 20:29:16 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Dhalgren</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/dhalgren/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Dhalgren cover" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2023/dhalgren.webp"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Samuel Delaney, 1975&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It broke me. I need to take another run up to this. Advice welcome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://localhost:8000/categories/did-not-finish/"&gt;&lt;span style="background:grey; color:white; border-radius: 1em; padding-left: 0.5em; padding-right: 0.5em; padding-top: 2px;"&gt;did-not-finish&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: left"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>did-not-finish</category><category>fiction</category><category>media</category><category>novel</category><category>science-fiction</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/dhalgren/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 01 Sep 2023 18:23:19 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Doomsday Clock</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/doomsday-clock/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;By Geoff Johns (writer), Gary Frank (pencil) &amp;amp; Brad Anderson (colors). (2017-2019)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://archive.org/details/Watchmen1987"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Watchmen&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is a
seminal 12-issue superhero comic by Alan Moore (writer) &amp;amp; Dave Gibbons
(artist), published from 1986 to 1987, that transformed the comics world. A
superhero tale in which all-but-one of the superheroes have no superhuman
powers at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The decades since have spawned a number of remakes, sequels, prequels and
spin-offs. Zach Snyder's movie adaptation has its adherents, although I am not
among them - one of Moore's goals was always to explore what makes the comic
medium unique, developing and advancing the boundaries of what you can do in
a comic but cannot do in other media. For example, a reader absorbs a comic at
their own pace, and will often voluntarily flip back to clarify overlooked
aspects of recent panels. What use, then, a shot-for-shot remake in the medium
of video, which steamrolls the viewer along, heedless of their desire to
cross-check important details? The HBO miniseries sequel, on the other hand,
was excellent - better than I imagined any Watchmen sequel could be. But other
than that they have not been very good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I initially thought the 12 issue sequel &lt;em&gt;Doomsday Clock&lt;/em&gt; comic would fall
solidly into this group - indeed, it was decried by many review headlines,
so I passed it by when it came out a couple of years ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But on reading it last week, I really enjoyed it. It really swings for the
fences, providing a smashing tale, with good arcs for both old and new
characters, and a genuine attempt to advance the conversation that &lt;em&gt;Watchmen&lt;/em&gt;
started by deconstructing the superhero.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="background:#bb2200; color:white; border-radius: 1em; padding-left: 0.5em; padding-right: 0.5em; padding-top: 2px;"&gt;&lt;b&gt;spoilers&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We last saw Dr Manhattan at the end of &lt;em&gt;Watchmen&lt;/em&gt;, having been isolated from
humanity by Adrien Veidt's plans, tired of his entanglement in the messy
complexity of people's lives, threatening to leave the galaxy "for one less
complicated".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img alt="Manhattan's departure at the end of Watchmen" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2022/doomsday-clock-watchmen-manhattan.webp"&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;em&gt;Doomsday Clock&lt;/em&gt;, Adrian Veidt, genius that he is, invents a means to follow
Dr Manhattan, seeking his help with the re-emergence of imminent nuclear war
brought about by the revelations in Rorschach's journal, and it becomes clear
that the "simpler place" Dr Manhattan has journeyed to is the DC universe,
populated by Superman, Batman, and the &lt;em&gt;whole&lt;/em&gt; stable of DC heroes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Various other &lt;em&gt;Watchmen&lt;/em&gt; characters make their way, or are transferred to, the
DC universe. This has been described across the comic industry as "the
crossover event nobody wanted", but personally I felt it was really well done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two of the most prominently deceased &lt;em&gt;Watchmen&lt;/em&gt; characters are brought back
into play, using mechanisms I thought were legitimate and, on occasion,
laugh-out-loud satisfying as they reached their resolution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img alt="Doomsday Clock Watchmen Comedian Alive" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2022/doomsday-clock-comedian.webp"&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In particular, they find a way to bring back Rorschach. Or, at least, &lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt;
Rorschach. Another individual picks up the mask. This seems like the most
controversial of the many decisions in the book, but it's handled deftly, and
there are both similarities and differences between the old and the new
Rorschach, making it an interesting character in its own right. In some ways
this transformation is reminiscent of HBO Watchmen's treatment of Hooded
Justice - retaining everything we already knew about the character, but
performing an astonishing piece of narrative ju-jitsu to utterly transform
everything about what that meant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The DC heroes slowly realize their world is being altered by Dr Manhattan's
manipulations, tying this crossover into the latest of the DC universe's
"crisis" events, as Manhattan experiments with this reality, in order to
understand it. In doing so, he uncovers deep truths that affect the
inter-relationship between all the DC time-lines and universes, establishing
that historical stories, such as Superman's original appearance in Action
Comics of the 1930s, represent realities that still exist, out in the
multiverse, unaffected by subsequent commercial re-ploughing that forever
drives Superman's origin story further forward in time over the years. All
these worlds, including the various DC pre-crisis worlds, are accessible to
Manhattan's powers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Incidentally, this enables DC to undo the changes wrought by the last few
years' unpopular &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_New_52"&gt;"New 52" era&lt;/a&gt;. This
meant nothing to me when I started reading, I know basically nothing about
American comics, only being familiar with the fabulous British
&lt;a href="https://2000ad.com"&gt;&lt;em&gt;2000AD&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I was spurred into reading around the DC lore,
and by the time I was done, I understood that the &lt;em&gt;New 52&lt;/em&gt; reality included
things like
&lt;a href="https://www.cbr.com/justice-league-darkseid-war-guide/"&gt;The Justice League's alternate roster&lt;/a&gt;,
the
&lt;a href="https://www.cbr.com/superman-ma-pa-kent-deaths/"&gt;early death of Clark's parents&lt;/a&gt;,
which distances Superman from humanity and changes the character dramatically,
the loss of the Justice Society of America from Earth, and the loss of Wally
West's Flash. All these and more are written off as the effects of Dr
Manhattan's meddling, isolated and preserved in just another spun-off part of
the multiverse, while being jettisoned from the privileged &lt;em&gt;metaverse&lt;/em&gt;, the
core template from which all subsequent multiversal threads are forged, as it
reverts to more-or-less its former state when Manhattan's changes are undone
during &lt;em&gt;Doomsday Clock&lt;/em&gt;'s story.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In doing all this, Manhattan exhibits his usual clinical detachment from the
human consequences of his actions, setting himself up as the villain of the
piece, an uncaring "being of inaction", in contrast to Superman, the literal
"man of Action".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img alt="Doomsday Clock: Superman &amp;amp; Manhattan" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2022/doomsday-clock-superman.webp"&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This forms a genuine riposte to &lt;em&gt;Watchmen's&lt;/em&gt; criticism of the superhero genre.
Yes, the DC heroes inhabit a simpler world, but the simplicity serves a purpose.
Escaping the mundane enhances the mythological power of what they represent as
symbols. Particularly the value of &lt;em&gt;hope&lt;/em&gt;, as personified by Superman, which,
although possibly somewhat overwrought in the telling - quite literally, in
this tale - makes all other things possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was especially pleased with the quiet, understated places Doomsday Clock goes
with &lt;em&gt;Mothman's&lt;/em&gt;, back-story. The character in &lt;em&gt;Watchmen&lt;/em&gt; was only a punchline,
a recurring throwaway reference to instability and alcoholism, telegraphing his
subsequent mental breakdown. But here, we see him fully fleshed out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like the rest of the &lt;em&gt;Watchmen&lt;/em&gt; heroes, he has no magical superhuman powers,
but is still able to pull off entirely unexpected and superhuman-seeming
stunts, merely by the virtue of his own unique kind of extreme mental and
emotional resourcefulness. Flawed, but aware of his faults, and able to pull it
together when he needs to, he befriends the younger Rorschach II during their
overlapping stays in a mental institution, becoming a beacon of warmth,
kindness, and generosity to the younger man.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He acts as a symbol, if you will, that just as &lt;em&gt;Watchmen's&lt;/em&gt; ruthless gaze
influenced the wider world of comics, so the comic world gazes back. They see
us, all the real-world, fully-rounded humans, trapped in the depths of our
pathos, and they wonder, when will each of us learn to transcend our humdrum
limitations, to finally act on our hopes and dreams, and &lt;em&gt;fly...&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img alt="Doomsday Clock: Mothman" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2022/doomsday-clock-mothman.webp"&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;br&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>comic</category><category>fiction</category><category>media</category><category>moore</category><category>science-fiction</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/doomsday-clock/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Sep 2022 01:57:55 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Expanse</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/the-expanse/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="The Expanse screencap" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2022/the-expanse-screencap.webp"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(This post rescues content from
&lt;a href="https://www.facebook.com/mfoord/posts/10158389841835880?comment_id=10158390351245880I"&gt;a Facebook comment&lt;/a&gt; I got carried away with recently.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's so much to write about the Expanse. It's such a relief to find a
science fiction show with an ambitiously futuristic setting depicted in a way
that doesn't make scientifically literate people cringe and shout at the
television.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, it shines at taking the time for quiet moments of character work, from
Miller's lonely, poignant realization in s01 that he wasn't the talented
office maverick, just incompetent and unreliable, right up to the quiet,
unseen payoff of Naomi's years-long efforts to save her son from his father's
influence, in the final seconds of s06.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On many axes, it's the best SF on television, which is saying something, as
there are so many competitors. Science fiction output is following some sort
of Moore's law of endless expansion, in response to society's need for
mythic stories of relevance to modern life, itself a symptom of the meaning
crisis of modern society. But this is a mixed blessing, because the resulting
shows &amp;amp; movies are often drawn to using the superficial trappings of science
fiction, spaceships and lasers (pew pew!), while failing to fulfil the deeper
psychological needs of mythical or symbolic significance that brought about
their creation. The Expanse is perhaps the prime example of this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.tartley.com/posts/the-expanse/damiengwalter.com"&gt;My fantastic SF podcast guy&lt;/a&gt; defines SF as the arena in
which we forge new myths of psychological meaning for modern life, which are
sorely needed as traditional myths dwindle in relevance, as they are
predominantly based on nature and superstition. Movements such as spiritual
atheism are a reflection that even the least spiritual amongst us recognize
that something is missing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I do concede that defining SF in this way is a bit of a cheat. It's somewhat
aggrandizing, claiming any great mythic work as actually being part of the
SF genre, an no doubt is a somewhat defensive reaction to mainstream
dismissal of science fiction as puerile. But it does provide a marvellous
framework for discussion, and adopting this definition makes several
previously puzzling things fall into place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It settles the revealing, never-ending debates over which works are, and
are not, science fiction. Somewhat tellingly, to me, such debates are
irreconcilable precisely because of the misnomer "science fiction", which was
never really about the science to begin with, as this style of fiction has
existed long before science was the focus. It only gravitated towards using
science as it became apparent that is now where society's power and
transformation springs from - our incarnation of gods and magic - and the name
"science fiction" was then applied post-facto, missing the underlying fact
that this is just mythic fiction with some modern attributes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This definition perfectly explains things like how the first half of the movie
"Sunshine" could be such astonishing science-fiction, while the second half
- set aboard the exact same spaceship - is just a mediocre slasher flick.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So. SF is the arena within which we construct new mythic narratives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By this I mean that great science fiction tends to create a story that
resonates because it leans on powerful mythic tropes - symbolic
representations of psychological significance, character arcs mirroring
Jungian archetypes, thematic elements that are told allegorically, suggesting
things to the reader/watcher on a level that can be more powerful than merely
stating them directly to the conscious mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this way, all-time-great examples such as &lt;em&gt;2001: A Space Odyssey&lt;/em&gt; (the
title being conscious of this mythic entanglement) leans heavily into themes
such as humanity watched over by an ancient, mysterious, godlike alien
influence which has literally created humanity in its present form, and
observes as we now reach a second inflection point, materializing not
just a tale of personal transcendence (although it is certainly that), but one
of species-wide sublimation - suggesting that it is time for us all to reach
spiritual adulthood, to graduate to whatever comes next, to meet and be
transformed by the wise and powerful force that has shepherded humanity
through our previous prehistorical transitions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I could go on with similar examples, but will just briefly mention the original
Matrix movie, which is a story which resonates because it is absolutely soaked
in allegory of both religious transcendence and Jungian archetypes - which are
so on-the-nose that it cannot possibly be accidental, a fact acknowledged
directly by the creators in the sequels, when they depict the Architect,
ultimate villain encountered at the narrative peak of the story, as a prim,
middle aged, white bearded gentleman, wearing an Edwardian suit. He speaks in a
precise, almost Germanic manner. This is, unmistakably, Sigmund Freud. Why is
Freud the villain of the Matrix? Because Freud was a contemporaneous antagonist
to Jung, resisting Jung's ideas of self actualization through reconciliation of
the archetypes, just as the Architect resists Neo's progression along that same
path.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It may be my own lack of imagination, but compared to examples like this, the
Expanse starts to look a bit thin. I don't see any symbolism or allegory.
There is some good character work but no actual arcs of transcendence. Through
the unfortunate realities of converting books to screen, large chunks of what
could have been the most meaningful story were simply abandoned and will
apparently never be finished on the screen. In their stead, what would have
been mythic elements become a series of "McGuffin of the week", as we never
circle back to resolve why the protomolecule was created, why it was sent to
our ancient solar system, why it turns people into nuclear-powered zombies,
and what force destroyed the protomolecule creators, and why? And that's just
series one's unresolved elements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, lacking that, what the Expanse has to offer is its superlative
world-building and sane, believable depictions of a gritty interplanetary
future. Which is no small feat - arguably nobody else has done it better. But,
for me, it isn't enough. Maybe that's just because I'm a godless heathen who
looks to get my spiritual fix through TV shows about spaceships. Or maybe it's
because science fiction is where we show ourselves what we're capable of, what
to aim for, and I believe we can aim higher than just exciting technological
dystopias.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>fiction</category><category>media</category><category>science-fiction</category><category>tv-show</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/the-expanse/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 08 Apr 2022 19:42:40 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Contact</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/contact/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Contact cover" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2022/contact-cover.webp"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Carl Sagan, 1985.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I put this into my library queue as it's highly regarded in some parts, and I'd
never read it. But at about chapter 2, I started to realize that I actually
have read it, maybe thirty years ago. Not only that, but I'm pretty sure I
actually have a copy somewhere on the shelves here at home. I'm going senile.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oh well, at least it's the sort of senile that gives me quick, pleasant things
to read.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also this month: &lt;em&gt;The Long Way to a Small, Angry Planet&lt;/em&gt; by Becky Chambers.
Once again, I wanted to like this so much. I started reading it twice, spaced
about 18 months apart. But each time, I just couldn't get into it, and
abandoned it about 1/3 in. It is indubitably me, not you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: left"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>fiction</category><category>media</category><category>novel</category><category>science-fiction</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/contact/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 20 Mar 2022 04:01:53 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Witch's Heart</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/the-witches-heart/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="The Witch's Heart cover" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2022/the-witchs-heart-cover.webp"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Genevieve Gornichec, 2021.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Old Norse mythology only briefly mentions the witch
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Angrbo%C3%B0a"&gt;Angrboða&lt;/a&gt;,
as the mother of three "monsters", fathered by the trickster god, Loki. This
book explores her life, explicitly acknowledging her erasure as a woman, and
resolves it, providing her a powerful story, in which she survives men, gods,
and all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another fantastic Suze recommendation. Loved it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also this month: &lt;em&gt;The Emperess of Salt and Fortune&lt;/em&gt; by Nghi Vo. I wanted to
like this sooo much, and can see so many things about that are wonderful, but
for some reason I just couldn't get in the mood. The problem is indubitably me,
not you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: left"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>fantasy</category><category>fiction</category><category>media</category><category>myth</category><category>novel</category><category>science-fiction</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/the-witches-heart/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 20 Mar 2022 03:43:53 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Circe</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/circe/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Circe cover" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2022/circe-cover.webp"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Madeline Miller, 2018.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recommended by The Suze, after reading it for one of her book clubs,
and I absolutely loved it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tells the life story of the mythical Circe of the ancient Greek pantheon.
Daughter of Helios, mightiest of the Titans, Circe is driven from her family by
their capricious cruelty. She puts her meagre supernatural talents to work in
service of witchcraft, amongst mortals. Along the way she meets many well-known
mythological characters, such as Odysseus, and the Cretean Minotaur.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was the writing style that captivated me. A timeless, elegant style uses
powerful turns of phrase to spin a tale of drama and high passions, soaked
in the psychological resonances so typical of Greek mythology.
This style, along with the setting, reminded me powerfully of another favourite
couple of novels of recent years, Mary Renault's absolutely fabulous &lt;em&gt;The King
Must Die&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;The Bull From the Sea&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Circe is my favorite book of the year so far, beating out even the marvellous
&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.tartley.com/posts/klara-and-the-sun"&gt;Klara and the Sun&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: left"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>fantasy</category><category>fiction</category><category>media</category><category>myth</category><category>novel</category><category>science-fiction</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/circe/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 20 Mar 2022 03:14:53 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Project Hail Mary</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/project-hail-mary/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Project Hail Mary cover" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2022/project-hail-mary-cover.webp"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lot of people really like this, but it really isn't for me. The plot
is an eerie recreation of the author's previous (and superior) big hit,
&lt;em&gt;The Martian&lt;/em&gt;, in which an astronaut finds themselves unexpectedly alone on an
ambitious space mission, and has to science the shit out of things (by which we
mean deploy some high-school science trivia, along with a penchant for very
ordinary mental arithmetic) to save the day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A badly written, distractingly unconvincing, and ultimately deeply annoying
collision between hard science fiction and hand-wavy nonsense, with no literate
themes, no higher meanings, no lurking Jungian archetypes - no mythology to it
at all. Just a succession of edge-of-the-seat will-he-or-won't-he survive tense
moments... Then: Yay, it worked, he did it! But &lt;em&gt;in space!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not even worth engaging the subjectivity-proof rating system for this one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rating: 2/10. I did finish it, but I wish I hadn't.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: both"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>fiction</category><category>media</category><category>novel</category><category>science-fiction</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/project-hail-mary/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 14 Feb 2022 02:07:47 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>