<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>tartley.com (Posts about media)</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://www.tartley.com/tags/media.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2024 &lt;a href="mailto:tartley @ tartley dot com"&gt;Jonathan Hartley&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 08 Nov 2024 19:34:41 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>That Which Gave Chase</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/that-which-gave-chase/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2024/that-which-gave-chase.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Released in 2023, played on Linux in 2024.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="background:#bb2200; color:white; border-radius: 1em; padding-left: 0.5em; padding-right: 0.5em; padding-top: 2px;"&gt;&lt;b&gt;spoilers&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mush your dog sled across cruel Arctic wastelands, driven onwards by a brisk and intense companion, who hired you to take him back to some remote spot, where it becomes apparent he had some sort of revelation, or maybe a breakdown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The low-res, dithered presentation conveys the harsh, blinding conditions, as you struggle to make out details through the relentless wind and ice. Smash cuts disorient you, making the days and nights of the journey blur into one another, leaving only fragmentary, disjointed memories: sledding across the ice; nights in crude wooden huts, collapsing into rough bunks; righting the sled while your companion curses you for a fool; silent moments alone, outside in the dark; mounting the sled before dawn. The sense is of endless, exhausting time spent covering the distance, through punishing conditions, and it's surprisingly evocative.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The narrative leans into the disorientation, making nothing clear. Your companion becomes increasingly cryptic. He urges you onward, never pausing more than absolutely necessary. The deer behave increasingly strangely. Your companion regales you with sickening tales of the investigative mistreatment he subjected them to on his previous visit. By the time the strange mushrooms come into play it is very obvious that you are in a place to which you should never have come, very far from anywhere or anyone, with mounting dread, alone with with a madman. What happened the last time he took this route? What did he leave behind here? What awaits at your journey's end?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's hard to know whether the difficulty of interpretation, or the non-literal aspects of your journey, are intended as the result of your character's mushroom-induced fever, or the pretensions of intrusively figurative allusions. Most likely, it seems to be both. The deliberate ambiguity runs deep.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Doesn't outstay its welcome, all done in an hour. But the memories remain.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>completed</category><category>geek</category><category>linux</category><category>media</category><category>videogame</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/that-which-gave-chase/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 04 Nov 2024 21:56:38 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Ferris Bueller's Day Off</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/ferris-buellers-day-off/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Ben Stein in Ferris Bueller's Day Off" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2023/ferris-bueller.webp"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Directed and written by John Hughes, 1986.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0091042"&gt;IMDB&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, way back in my teen years, we had a VHS tape of this, which friends and I
played and played and played, probably racking up more rewatches than any other
movie in my life. So it was a pleasure to break it out for our 11 year-old,
some some 37 years later (!), to see whether it still holds up, and find that
it really does.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By chance this was the week after we'd just watched &lt;em&gt;The Blues Brothers&lt;/em&gt;, so we
got to compare and contrast two movies set in Chicago - a privileged white
story, and a poverty stricken, largely colored one, which even share scenes
filmed in the very same restaurant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back then, I had no idea who Ben Stein was, so it was amusing to see him now
and suddenly join the dots. Apparently his infamous "voodoo economics" speech
had no script and was ad-libbed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reviewing Rooney's comical attempts to break into the Buellers' house made me
realize for the first time that this was Hughes' dry-run at what would become
&lt;em&gt;Home Alone&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had always been frustrated that I'd never been able to lay my hands on the
"&lt;em&gt;You're not dying&lt;/em&gt;" song that Cameron plays while sick in his bedroom (i.e. here's the few seconds
of it
&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6mcFGW0RjAo&amp;amp;t=70s&amp;amp;autoplay=1"&gt;on Youtube&lt;/a&gt;,
exactly as it appears in the movie.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now we have the Internet, I can see that this failure wasn't exactly my fault -
there is no such song. The few bars we hear were whipped up by Ira Newborn
specially for the film, based on an old Louis Armstrong song,
&lt;a href="https://youtu.be/fHbC8Nhd46s?autoplay=1"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Let My People Go&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Fortunately for us,
one man was obsessed about it enough to actually recreate a full length
song based on the snippets from the movie. Here is Daniel Simone's
&lt;a href="https://youtu.be/MDEXlOk_suM?autoplay=1"&gt;Let My Cameron Go&lt;/a&gt;,
full of a lush Pink Floyd sound, and ripe with the sort of ecstatic
anticipation that even Roger Waters would be proud of.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Duly &lt;a href="https://www.tartley.com/posts/download-audio-from-youtube/"&gt;added to my rotation&lt;/a&gt; for next time I'm sick.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: left"&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>comedy</category><category>fiction</category><category>media</category><category>movie</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/ferris-buellers-day-off/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 27 Sep 2023 15:01:22 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Resolution and The Endless</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/resolution-and-the-endless/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Resolution" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2023/resolution.webp"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt1977895"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Resolution (2012)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="The Endless" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2023/the-endless.webp"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt3986820"&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Endless (2017)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I only had a hazy awareness of Justin Benson and Aaron Moorhead, the writer
and directors, before watching these movies. But having discovered them, I now
realize that they are doing just about my favorite thing in film: Quirky,
intense, psychological drama wound around some high concept science fiction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Going in, I hadn't realized the two films are related. But then they contain
the same scene, viewed from two different angles (pictured above), and it
starts to become clearer. As it happens, I watched them out of order - my
enthusiasm for &lt;em&gt;The Endless&lt;/em&gt; caused me to look up their earlier &lt;em&gt;Resolution&lt;/em&gt;.
But with hindsight, I think this is actually the best order to view them. If
&lt;em&gt;Resolution&lt;/em&gt; has a weakness, it's that the science fictional elements seem a
bit arbitrary. Why should this supernatural entity focus its narrative-obsessed
attentions on these two men, here in this cabin, out in the middle of nowhere?
But in &lt;em&gt;The Endless&lt;/em&gt;, this particular brand of supernatural outlandishness is
revealed to be just part of a wider pattern, affecting many people in this
geographical area. Although this is the bigger, weirder story, it is more fully
fleshed out and becomes more believable, creating a setting which
recontextualizes and improves the earlier film.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rating: 10/10 if you like mindbending SF horror, 0/10 if you prefer something a
bit more polished and comfortable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>fiction</category><category>media</category><category>movie</category><category>science-fiction</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/resolution-and-the-endless/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 22 Sep 2023 19:12:24 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Aurora</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/aurora/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Aurora cover" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2023/aurora.webp"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Kim Stanley Robinson, 2015&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It has long been held by fans of science fiction that &lt;em&gt;fantasy&lt;/em&gt; is a lowly
subset of science-fiction, or perhaps a disreputable cousin, one for whom
the normal rules of discernment do not apply. If such unlikely and unrealistic
things as dragons and magic are allowed, the reasoning goes, then the book
cannot be relied upon to deliver any kind of coherent narrative experience,
since the lapsed rule-set now allows for any old &lt;em&gt;ex machina&lt;/em&gt; plot twists to
save the day. A magical "defeat the evil" spell? No problem. A new mythical
creature capable of defeating the previously unassailable one? Why not? All
reason is gone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's more useful though, is to invert the hierarchy of this received wisdom,
and consider science fiction as a subset of fantasy. Mentioning this in fandom
circles blows mental fuses. Does not compute. But the speculative flights of
science fiction are also fantasies. Just fantasies that a particular type of
person finds especially beguiling, compelling, and believable. To some extent,
I concede that on occasion they are believable because they seem to be a
reasonable extrapolation of our current situation. But no matter how reasonable
your extrapolation seems to be, it's always possible that reality will zig
instead of zag, and even the most humdrum tale of a rocket man's life will
find itself at odds with the unexpected reality of suspended human spaceflight
in the face of spiraling real-world costs. The vision that one is selling is
always, to a greater or lesser extent, a wishful one - a &lt;em&gt;fantasy&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This becomes immediately apparent once we stray beyond the confines of low
Earth orbit, to take in the wider scope of science fiction, the vast majority
of which encompasses tales across the galaxy, nay, the universe, including time
travel, teleportation booths, aliens of every color, quantum reality
displacement, and multiversal escapades in which literally everything is
possible. These are very clearly fantasies, and it is intensely curious to me
why this sort of fantasy is considered more "realistic" or "believable" than,
say, flying lizards with fiery breath. Even though the narrative hand-waving
that explains away the former - "It's an alternate &lt;em&gt;universe&lt;/em&gt;, where different
rules apply" - is abundantly adequate to more than completely explain anything
in the fantasy realm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I once asked my guru science fiction critic &lt;a href="https://damiengwalter.com/podcast/"&gt;Damien
Walter&lt;/a&gt; what makes people consider some
stories believable, while other are not. He replied with a statement that has
stuck with me ever since: People are willing to invest the effort to provide
the conceptual scaffolding around an idea to make it seem believable (e.g. to
speculate on the mechanism that might allow for a faster-than-light
hyper-drive) &lt;em&gt;when the story fulfills some deeper psychological need for them&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hence, a story on the same topic as &lt;em&gt;Aurora&lt;/em&gt;, of a generation ship sent to
colonize an Earth-like planet orbiting the nearby star of Tau Ceti, is
(usually) a story about the triumph of modernism. Such stories leverage the
sources of strength in the modern world, science and technology and
&lt;em&gt;colonialism&lt;/em&gt;, and a reader who is invested in a modern world-view will feel
validated and empowered by this type of fantasy. They will be will be willing
to exercise whatever extracurricular creative effort is required on the part of
the reader to make the story believable. Doing so will inspire them with the
feeling that their world all makes sense, is leading to something, so that
their daily grind is a part of the heroic story of how humanity transcends its
planetary origins. This is much more fulfilling than investing any effort
getting on board with the waning powers of superstition that are represented by
the fantasy genre.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="background:#bb2200; color:white; border-radius: 1em; padding-left: 0.5em; padding-right: 0.5em; padding-top: 2px;"&gt;&lt;b&gt;spoilers&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In keeping with this, Aurora's colonists are granted every conceivable boon
that science and industry can supply. A ship fully ten kilometers across,
enclosing twenty four massive biomes, each stuffed full of hills and lakes,
soil and forests, microbes and wildlife. A population of well over a thousand
human beings. Miraculous nanotech fabricators, and megatons of elemental
feedstock to run them. A miraculous acceleration laser, fired from Titan for
decades after departure, allowing the ship to coast up to 0.1c, making the
journey in only seven generations, while retaining enough fuel to decelerate
for arrival. A miraculous magnetic shield protects the ship from catastrophic
collisions with stray particles along the way. A benign AI runs the ship,
amusingly pressed into service as the narrator of the tale, and grows visibly
more sentient, emotionally robust and capable as the years pass.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And hot damn, they are going to &lt;em&gt;need&lt;/em&gt; all these things, because in this story,
human interstellar colonization is revealed for the fantasy it really is.
Nothing works out, and the problems encountered are far bigger than anything
the ship's designers planned for. Although the ship does limp into orbit
around the destination planet, soon after that people start dying, major
disagreements emerge which descend into catastrophic riots, and the ship's
society falls apart - when have humans ever invented a reliable form of
governance?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a rip-roaring final act, that stretched my credulity, but revives the
stakes and entertainment value in what might otherwise be a relentless downer
of a read.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book, and interviews with the author, caused quite a stir in science
fiction circles. People were extremely angry. The book was attacking their
deeply held beliefs that the future of humanity is as a successfull
space-faring species. They had invested their identity in this world-view,
because of how it serviced their psychological needs for fulfillment and
meaning. They had developed a religious conviction around this particular kind
of fantasy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The point of Aurora is to highlight the idea of human interstellar colonization
as a dangerous distraction from the very real project of taking care of the
long term health of our planet and our society right here on Earth. It is going
to take &lt;em&gt;beyond&lt;/em&gt; miraculous levels of technology and resources to start
thinking about interstellar travel. If, by some miracle, we make it to a year
10,000 utopia, with infinite resources and the wisdom to manage them, then
sure, we can worry about interstellar travel. But for now, can we just focus on
some of the very basic problems of existence here on Earth, like how to make
everyone fed and liberated, educated and fulfilled, without killing our planet
to do it? Maybe invent some sort of government that is reliably able to do
that? That would be nice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: left"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>fiction</category><category>media</category><category>novel</category><category>science-fiction</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/aurora/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 21 Sep 2023 20:29:16 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Dhalgren</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/dhalgren/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Dhalgren cover" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2023/dhalgren.webp"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Samuel Delaney, 1975&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It broke me. I need to take another run up to this. Advice welcome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://localhost:8000/categories/did-not-finish/"&gt;&lt;span style="background:grey; color:white; border-radius: 1em; padding-left: 0.5em; padding-right: 0.5em; padding-top: 2px;"&gt;did-not-finish&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: left"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>did-not-finish</category><category>fiction</category><category>media</category><category>novel</category><category>science-fiction</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/dhalgren/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 01 Sep 2023 18:23:19 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Ur-Fascism</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/ur-fascism/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Ur-Fascism cover" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2023/ur-fascism-cover.webp"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Umberto Eco, 1995.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eco's prose has left me in the dust on occasion in the past. I missed so many references, or failed to keep up with the relentlessly nested layers of meaning, that I was simply holding on for the ride. This essay matches Eco's characteristically dense, intellectual prose, studded with foreign phrases, and references to contemporary thinkers, historical movements and causes and revolutions and dictatorships, and their antecedents. But it is short, and perhaps in contrast to the flourishes of brilliance that comprise his fiction, this is a factual piece, and is written to be understood rather than to dazzle. It begins by establishing Eco's credentials to speak on this topic, with the first of several entrancing first-hand indications of what it was like to grow up as an intellectual young child in Italy under Mussolini, and the revelations that followed at the opening up of his world at the end of WWII.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He differentiates between the truly totalitarian fascism of, say, Nazism, which subordinated all of life to the state, with the looser, less coherent Italian fascism, noting that this did not derive from any increment of tolerance, merely the absence of a sufficiently encompassing underlying philosophy. Despite this, it is the Italian mode, which was the first right wing dictatorship in modern history, from which subsequent dictators seem to have drawn most stylistic inspiration, and from which our generic term of "fascism" derives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last half of the essay describes how fascism means different things in different contexts, but the various incarnations through history have exhibited sufficiently overlapping sets of symptoms as to glean a family resemblance. Eco enumerates 13 identifying traits, noting that the presence of even one of them can be sufficient to allow fascism to coagulate around it. Mostly for my own benefit, (with my own parenthesised observations) they are, briefly:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fascism incorporates a cult of tradition. This can be deployed as an automatic refutation of any undesirable new ideas, enshrining in their place the immutable wisdom of a mythical past. In addition, traditionalism undermines the perceived value of learning in itself - pre-emptively thwarting troublesome intellectuals. This anti-intellectual received wisdom, in order to provide whichever justifications are required of it, requires the syncretistic combination of various ancient beliefs. As a result it must tolerate contradictions. Indeed, the more stark they are, the better they serve the purpose of selecting followers who will obediently think whatever they are told.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rejection of modernism. This is a powerful recruiting tool, enabling the fascist to leverage any dissatisfaction of the populous, laying claim to the emotionally appealing universal solution of a regression to simpler, happier times, while simultaneously rewinding societal progress in equality or liberty. While Nazis and fascists love their technology, this is a superficial tool, used in support of a deeply regressive project, namely the restoration of power to those with the strength and the will to take it. This irrationality goes hand in hand with anti-intellectualism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Value vigor and action above reflection. Thinking is emasculation. Culture is suspect insofar as it aligns with any sort of critical theory or values. Regard centers of analysis or learning such as libraries or universities with suspicion for harboring - or even indoctrinating - people of opposing political viewpoints. Again, this is deeply intertwined with (1) &amp;amp; (2), and its prevalence pre-emptively defuses any kind of mainstream understanding or critique.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of the above make it inevitable that any given fascist regime will be rife with internal contradictions.  While modernity achieves its intellectual prowess through the nurturing of diverse thought, fascism cannot possibly withstand any critical analysis. Hence, disagreement is treason.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fascist appeal to popularity exploits and exacerbates the natural fear of &lt;em&gt;the other&lt;/em&gt;, and hence is always inherently racist. Expect demonization of immigrants, foreigners, other nation states, as well as other marginalized groups, taking advantage of whatever local contemporary biases and fears might be present.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The above exploitation takes the form of an appeal to the frustrations of the middle class - or whichever class can be most useful and readily mobilized by persuasion that their problems are caused by some identifiable other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Modernity genuinely does disintegrate traditional social bonds, along with sources of identity and meaning. Fascism's solution to this is to unify the disaffected under the only remaining banner common to them all, that of patriotism and nationalism. This unity is strengthened by emphasis on the country's enemies, and especially by conspiracy theories of secret international plots against the nation. Followers must feel besieged (as Trump advised the January 6th crowd that "America is under siege"). Eco makes special mention, in the U.S, of Pat Robertson's &lt;em&gt;The New World Order&lt;/em&gt;, but potential sources of conspiracy are innumerable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Followers can be riled into frenzy of humiliation at their enemies' wealth or power. Jews control the
world and its money. Instead of coastal liberals, refer to coastal elites. But at the same time, the instinct to action requires that enemies can easily be defeated. Hence enemies are simultaneously too weak and too strong. Herein lies one of fascism's greatest weaknesses, responsible for several lost wars, in that it is constitutionally incapable of objectively assessing an enemy's strength.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Goad followers into violent action with rhetoric not just of a struggle for survival, but by declaration that life is struggle, and hence pacifism is conspiring with the enemy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While fascism appeals for the participation of the population by promising empowerment for the majority, its naked power lust is a fundamentally aristocratic endeavor. The leader takes power from those too weak to oppose  him, disdaining both conquered rivals and the subjugated population. Power struggles within the Party are vicious, and the party rides roughshod over the citizens, who likewise are leagues above the disenfranchised. The hierarchy is strict, steep, and ruthless. Elitism abounds, as does fear of losing one's status.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The redress of modernity's threadbare social fabric, by emphasizing nationalism and strength, further erodes interpersonal solidarity. Each individual must becomes their own hero. Strong, independent, and utterly without recourse in times of need. The cult of the hero is intimately entwined with a cult of death. Having only the narrow causes of the nation and the Party to live for, the hero yearns for a heroic death - or, better, to demonstrate their power and status by sending others to their death.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The preeminent will to power, so often frustrated in an aristocratic, dog-eat-dog social order, manifests alternately in things like machismo, disdain for women, and phallic fetishization of weapons. Repressed insecurity breeds an outward contempt for unconventional sexuality, including chastity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Under fascism, the people have no innate rights, and hence no material preferences or expression. Instead, the leader pretends to interpret the Will of the People. This charade requires the party apparatus to select and amplify some emotional response of the people, and present it as representative, so that the party can be empowered to act on behalf of that supposedly majority. Consider the amplifications of manufactured outrage about culture war issues, so that elected representatives are empowered to act decisively on their own preferences, against the majority of the population's wishes. This leads directly to confrontation with institutions such as a parliament. Fascism will therefore cast aspersions on any properly functioning parliament's legitimacy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All fascisms make use of their own varieties of NewSpeak, using an impoverished vocabulary and syntax, in order to limit the instruments for critical reasoning. This may appear in apparently innocent forms, from schoolbooks to popular talk shows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>essays</category><category>media</category><category>non-fiction</category><category>politics</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/ur-fascism/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 12 Jul 2023 00:41:42 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Astroneer Resource Graph</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/astroneer-resource-graph/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Used the trusty &lt;a href="https://graphviz.org/"&gt;Graphviz&lt;/a&gt; to whip up a diagram showing how to
get each of the resources in &lt;a href="https://astroneer.space/"&gt;Astroneer&lt;/a&gt;. Click the WEBP
thumbnail below to get the full glorious SVG, then you can '&lt;em&gt;find in page&lt;/em&gt;' on it.
(&lt;a href="https://www.tartley.com/files/2023/astroneer/astroneer-resources-graph.dot"&gt;Diagram source&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.tartley.com/files/2023/astroneer/astroneer-resources-graph.svg"&gt;&lt;img alt="Astroneer Resource Graph" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2023/astroneer/astroneer-resources-graph-thumb.webp"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>did-not-finish</category><category>geek</category><category>media</category><category>videogame</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/astroneer-resource-graph/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 11 Apr 2023 15:01:51 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Gallery of Drawings</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/gallery-of-drawings/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;This blog now has
&lt;a href="https://www.tartley.com/galleries/Drawings/"&gt;a gallery of my drawings&lt;/a&gt;.
A middle-aged outburst from the dying embers of my creativity has produced some
devastatingly inept scrawls. I weep for having caused them to impinge upon your
consciousness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: left"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>creative</category><category>drawing</category><category>media</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/gallery-of-drawings/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 01 Mar 2023 18:23:19 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Soma</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/soma/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Frictional Games, published 2015&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img alt="Soma - protagonist" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2022/soma-protagonist.webp"&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Soma is a creepy survival horror game, that leans deeply into the moral and
existential quandaries arising from the deterministic principle that it's
possible to scan one's brain and copy the structure into some other substrate,
yielding a second conscious entity, which thinks it is you. So there are deep
science-fiction issues in play here, about whether we think such a scheme could
ever possibly work, and about the practical, personal, and societal
ramifications of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Major &lt;span style="background:#bb2200; color:white; border-radius: 1em; padding-left: 0.5em; padding-right: 0.5em; padding-top: 2px;"&gt;spoilers&lt;/span&gt; ahead. It's seven years old at this point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I loved the setup. A humdrum morning begins in your present-day Toronto
apartment. A note on the fridge reminds you that today is the day of your
medical appointment, a brain scan. Reaching the doctor's office by train, you
find the experimental new type of brain scanner, run by some PhD in a
cable-strewn side-office. Sit in the chair, don the helmet, wait for the scan
to complete and- blink! Suddenly, you are elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the game progresses, it becomes obvious that the version of you that sat
down in the seat did not experience this discontinuity. They completed the
scan, removed the helmet, and continued their normal, everyday life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You are not that copy. You open your eyes to a grim, decrepit cyberpunk future.
Exploring, your only company is a menagerie of half-functional robots and
drones, many of which are insane, and, in conversation, seem to be under the
impression that they are human beings. It gradually becomes apparent that
perceptual filters are in play, preventing them - and you - from noticing they
are no longer human. At one point the ocean crashes in on you, and you drown
for a little while, or at least think you are, but you still don't die. At that
point you have to acknowledge the truth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You have awoken to the year 2104, and the recorded brain scans of real humans
are being used to animate drones. This is a scenario much like that told from a
different perspective in the smashing short story
&lt;a href="https://qntm.org/mmacevedo"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Lena&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; by qntm.
Failing systems engaged fall-backs, resulting in your obsolete brain scan being
yanked from storage to inhabit an advanced humanoid robot, in a facility deep
under the ocean, some time after a comet strike has scoured all life from the
planet's surface.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If that wasn't bad enough, one facilitating technology of this nightmarish
scenario, a black goo that mimics and improves upon electrical and biological
circuitry it comes into contact with, has run rampant, growing probing tendrils
which are wrecking the facility. Among other effects, it has reanimated the
corpses of the last few humans, who skulk around, not in a good way. As our
protagonist asks, incredulously, "You mean they've been brought back to life?".
Our reassuring AI companion replies "Yeah, let's call it that."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The game borrows the highly effective mechanics of Frictional's previous games,
the Amnesia and Penumbra series, where the proximity of horrific, shambling
enemies causes your character to experience debilitating symptoms, including,
in this case, static-y visual distortions as your neural hardware suffers from
some overload or interference. This applies even if you simply look at an
enemy, an act which immediately draws their attention. So your only chance to
survive encounters is to stay well out of sight, and actively avert your eyes
so you can't even watch what's going on. Not being able to see exactly what
your enemies are, or what they are up to, turns out to be fabulously scary and
atmospheric. At one point it lead directly to my wife catching me staring
intently at a blank, black screen for a prolonged period, with a peculiar
expression on my face, as I hid in a dark cupboard waiting for the slithering
sounds behind me to go away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Spurring us through this environment are not just threats to our immediate
survival, but also the adoption of a project, to launch into space a
solar-powered simulation, hosting all the last remaining brain scans of the
now-defunct human race, known as the 'ARK'. This will allow the on-board sims
to live a prolonged period of idyllic virtual existence, preserving at least
some echo of what humanity was. Since the conceit of the game is that our
character is a living and conscious entity that feels real emotion, the sims on
the ARK are all presumably the same, so this seems like a worthwhile endeavor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are guided, motivated, and assisted by "Catherine", a simulated personality
running on our hand-held omni-tool, based on the brain recording of an AI
researcher, whose project during her lifetime was the ARK. Plugging her in to a
wall or console socket lets her interface with our surroundings, activating
power supplies and manipulating machinery. She leads us through a series of
undersea facilities, linked by trains, submersibles, and the occasional
disorienting trudge across the murky ocean floor, stirred up by ferocious
currents and landslides, populated by organic-mechanical hybrid horrors that
glide by in the darkness. I found these some of the absolute best, most
atmospheric "walking simulator" moments I've experienced in a game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img alt="The ocean floor, stirred up by currents and landslides" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2022/soma-murky.webp"&gt;
&lt;br&gt;Is that another distant light up ahead? Good luck finding them while the currents pummel you,
and hideous, deadly beasts loom out of the murk.
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Along the way, we encounter a few unforgettable scenarios. We come across the
failing storage system in which the last remaining copy of our own brain scan
resides. I decide to flip some buttons which delete it, prompting my character
to respond with something like "Let this be the last time I wake up in this
godforsaken place."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At another point, we find ourselves trapped within a collapsing facility on the
bottom of the ocean, with the gibbering undead hammering on the door from the
next room. There is an airlock leading out into the ocean, but we would be
crushed at this depth. There is no way out. Luckily, Catherine is able to guide
us into assembling a more robust robot, one capable of withstanding the
pressure - all we have to do is sit in the chair and activate the transfer into
it. We already did this once, back in Toronto. Easy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Except, after the transfer, we glance back across the lab at our original - the
pictured chap with red LED eyes - who, we notice, is still breathing. Asking
Catherine about it, she reminds us that the brain scan is not a destructive
operation. He's still in there, chemically subdued for the moment, but he'll
soon wake up again, wondering why the transfer didn't work. So we are left with
the option of stomping out of the airlock to safety, leaving him behind to his
nightmarish fate. Or flipping a switch to deactivate him before we go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lot of these narrative beats work better as a game than they perhaps might in
a written story. They emphasize the player's complicity, your moral
culpability, which is a mode that games, for all their faults, can do better
than any other media. Plenty of the lesser moments along the way expose the
player to decisions about unplugging some human simulation or other which
declares itself to be "alive", but which is gating your progress in some way.
Some of them are yourself. Some of these acts require manhandling weighty
cables, which require large, insistent tugging with the mouse controls. It's
not just a disembodied button press. One has to provide a determined,
definitive, mechanical input to end a life. In context, the guilt feels real.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Later in the journey, we finally stumble across an honest-to-goodness real,
live human being. She describes how the rest of the humans will be gathered in
particular locations, while she stayed to protect the ARK. But, we tell her, we
just passed through those locations, and there were no humans remaining there.
We both know that the planet's surface is sterile. A beat passes before she
announces "So I'm the last human being left alive." She's deathly sick, and
without hope. By the end of your interactions she asks you to turn off her
life-support before you leave, and stay with her for her last wheezing moments.
So this is how humanity ends.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Carrying on, because what else is there to do? We finally we get the ARK loaded
into the launch system that delivers it to orbit, upload our brain scans onto
it just before it launches, and - we've done it! Success!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was a moment, about five minutes before the end, when I realized what was
going to happen here, even though my character had not. It was a real emotional
blow. I envied and pitied him for his naive hope. For believing there was still
a way out. For, of course, the ARK's launch changed nothing for us. Our
simulations are aboard it, but we are still sitting here, in a broken robot
corpse in a collapsing facility at the bottom of a haunted ocean on a dead
planet. The dispatched copy will enjoy life on the ARK, but we - like the copy
of ourselves we left behind earlier - are stuck here for good. Roll credits.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>completed</category><category>geek</category><category>linux</category><category>media</category><category>videogame</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/soma/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 04 Oct 2022 18:51:16 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Doomsday Clock</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/doomsday-clock/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;By Geoff Johns (writer), Gary Frank (pencil) &amp;amp; Brad Anderson (colors). (2017-2019)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://archive.org/details/Watchmen1987"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Watchmen&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is a
seminal 12-issue superhero comic by Alan Moore (writer) &amp;amp; Dave Gibbons
(artist), published from 1986 to 1987, that transformed the comics world. A
superhero tale in which all-but-one of the superheroes have no superhuman
powers at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The decades since have spawned a number of remakes, sequels, prequels and
spin-offs. Zach Snyder's movie adaptation has its adherents, although I am not
among them - one of Moore's goals was always to explore what makes the comic
medium unique, developing and advancing the boundaries of what you can do in
a comic but cannot do in other media. For example, a reader absorbs a comic at
their own pace, and will often voluntarily flip back to clarify overlooked
aspects of recent panels. What use, then, a shot-for-shot remake in the medium
of video, which steamrolls the viewer along, heedless of their desire to
cross-check important details? The HBO miniseries sequel, on the other hand,
was excellent - better than I imagined any Watchmen sequel could be. But other
than that they have not been very good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I initially thought the 12 issue sequel &lt;em&gt;Doomsday Clock&lt;/em&gt; comic would fall
solidly into this group - indeed, it was decried by many review headlines,
so I passed it by when it came out a couple of years ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But on reading it last week, I really enjoyed it. It really swings for the
fences, providing a smashing tale, with good arcs for both old and new
characters, and a genuine attempt to advance the conversation that &lt;em&gt;Watchmen&lt;/em&gt;
started by deconstructing the superhero.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="background:#bb2200; color:white; border-radius: 1em; padding-left: 0.5em; padding-right: 0.5em; padding-top: 2px;"&gt;&lt;b&gt;spoilers&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We last saw Dr Manhattan at the end of &lt;em&gt;Watchmen&lt;/em&gt;, having been isolated from
humanity by Adrien Veidt's plans, tired of his entanglement in the messy
complexity of people's lives, threatening to leave the galaxy "for one less
complicated".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img alt="Manhattan's departure at the end of Watchmen" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2022/doomsday-clock-watchmen-manhattan.webp"&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;em&gt;Doomsday Clock&lt;/em&gt;, Adrian Veidt, genius that he is, invents a means to follow
Dr Manhattan, seeking his help with the re-emergence of imminent nuclear war
brought about by the revelations in Rorschach's journal, and it becomes clear
that the "simpler place" Dr Manhattan has journeyed to is the DC universe,
populated by Superman, Batman, and the &lt;em&gt;whole&lt;/em&gt; stable of DC heroes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Various other &lt;em&gt;Watchmen&lt;/em&gt; characters make their way, or are transferred to, the
DC universe. This has been described across the comic industry as "the
crossover event nobody wanted", but personally I felt it was really well done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two of the most prominently deceased &lt;em&gt;Watchmen&lt;/em&gt; characters are brought back
into play, using mechanisms I thought were legitimate and, on occasion,
laugh-out-loud satisfying as they reached their resolution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img alt="Doomsday Clock Watchmen Comedian Alive" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2022/doomsday-clock-comedian.webp"&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In particular, they find a way to bring back Rorschach. Or, at least, &lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt;
Rorschach. Another individual picks up the mask. This seems like the most
controversial of the many decisions in the book, but it's handled deftly, and
there are both similarities and differences between the old and the new
Rorschach, making it an interesting character in its own right. In some ways
this transformation is reminiscent of HBO Watchmen's treatment of Hooded
Justice - retaining everything we already knew about the character, but
performing an astonishing piece of narrative ju-jitsu to utterly transform
everything about what that meant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The DC heroes slowly realize their world is being altered by Dr Manhattan's
manipulations, tying this crossover into the latest of the DC universe's
"crisis" events, as Manhattan experiments with this reality, in order to
understand it. In doing so, he uncovers deep truths that affect the
inter-relationship between all the DC time-lines and universes, establishing
that historical stories, such as Superman's original appearance in Action
Comics of the 1930s, represent realities that still exist, out in the
multiverse, unaffected by subsequent commercial re-ploughing that forever
drives Superman's origin story further forward in time over the years. All
these worlds, including the various DC pre-crisis worlds, are accessible to
Manhattan's powers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Incidentally, this enables DC to undo the changes wrought by the last few
years' unpopular &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_New_52"&gt;"New 52" era&lt;/a&gt;. This
meant nothing to me when I started reading, I know basically nothing about
American comics, only being familiar with the fabulous British
&lt;a href="https://2000ad.com"&gt;&lt;em&gt;2000AD&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I was spurred into reading around the DC lore,
and by the time I was done, I understood that the &lt;em&gt;New 52&lt;/em&gt; reality included
things like
&lt;a href="https://www.cbr.com/justice-league-darkseid-war-guide/"&gt;The Justice League's alternate roster&lt;/a&gt;,
the
&lt;a href="https://www.cbr.com/superman-ma-pa-kent-deaths/"&gt;early death of Clark's parents&lt;/a&gt;,
which distances Superman from humanity and changes the character dramatically,
the loss of the Justice Society of America from Earth, and the loss of Wally
West's Flash. All these and more are written off as the effects of Dr
Manhattan's meddling, isolated and preserved in just another spun-off part of
the multiverse, while being jettisoned from the privileged &lt;em&gt;metaverse&lt;/em&gt;, the
core template from which all subsequent multiversal threads are forged, as it
reverts to more-or-less its former state when Manhattan's changes are undone
during &lt;em&gt;Doomsday Clock&lt;/em&gt;'s story.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In doing all this, Manhattan exhibits his usual clinical detachment from the
human consequences of his actions, setting himself up as the villain of the
piece, an uncaring "being of inaction", in contrast to Superman, the literal
"man of Action".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img alt="Doomsday Clock: Superman &amp;amp; Manhattan" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2022/doomsday-clock-superman.webp"&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This forms a genuine riposte to &lt;em&gt;Watchmen's&lt;/em&gt; criticism of the superhero genre.
Yes, the DC heroes inhabit a simpler world, but the simplicity serves a purpose.
Escaping the mundane enhances the mythological power of what they represent as
symbols. Particularly the value of &lt;em&gt;hope&lt;/em&gt;, as personified by Superman, which,
although possibly somewhat overwrought in the telling - quite literally, in
this tale - makes all other things possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was especially pleased with the quiet, understated places Doomsday Clock goes
with &lt;em&gt;Mothman's&lt;/em&gt;, back-story. The character in &lt;em&gt;Watchmen&lt;/em&gt; was only a punchline,
a recurring throwaway reference to instability and alcoholism, telegraphing his
subsequent mental breakdown. But here, we see him fully fleshed out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like the rest of the &lt;em&gt;Watchmen&lt;/em&gt; heroes, he has no magical superhuman powers,
but is still able to pull off entirely unexpected and superhuman-seeming
stunts, merely by the virtue of his own unique kind of extreme mental and
emotional resourcefulness. Flawed, but aware of his faults, and able to pull it
together when he needs to, he befriends the younger Rorschach II during their
overlapping stays in a mental institution, becoming a beacon of warmth,
kindness, and generosity to the younger man.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He acts as a symbol, if you will, that just as &lt;em&gt;Watchmen's&lt;/em&gt; ruthless gaze
influenced the wider world of comics, so the comic world gazes back. They see
us, all the real-world, fully-rounded humans, trapped in the depths of our
pathos, and they wonder, when will each of us learn to transcend our humdrum
limitations, to finally act on our hopes and dreams, and &lt;em&gt;fly...&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img alt="Doomsday Clock: Mothman" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2022/doomsday-clock-mothman.webp"&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;br&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>comic</category><category>fiction</category><category>media</category><category>moore</category><category>science-fiction</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/doomsday-clock/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Sep 2022 01:57:55 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>