<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>tartley.com (Posts about meetup)</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://www.tartley.com/tags/meetup.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2025 &lt;a href="mailto:tartley @ tartley dot com"&gt;Jonathan Hartley&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 12 Feb 2025 17:59:27 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>PyRochesterMN</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/pyrochestermn/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Announcing the world's newest Python User Group, PyRochesterMN, based in
Rochester, Minnesota, USA.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update:&lt;/strong&gt; We've had a couple of name &amp;amp; hosting changes since:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;del&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.meetup.com/PyRochesterMN"&gt;http://www.meetup.com/PyRochesterMN&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;del&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.meetup.com/RochesTech"&gt;http://www.meetup.com/RochesTech&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/rochestertech/"&gt;https://www.reddit.com/r/rochestertech/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>geek</category><category>meetup</category><category>python</category><category>software</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/pyrochestermn/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 21 Jan 2016 03:01:27 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>London Geek Night : Game Dev</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/london-geek-night-game-dev/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Last night was Game Dev night at the London Geek meet in the
ThoughtWorks offices. It was really enjoyable, I really enjoyed the
talks, and meeting and chatting to everyone there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, there were a bunch of comments throughout the evening
that confirmed some long-standing suspicions I've had about professional
game development. I'm not pointedly directing this at any individuals -
it really was a pleasure and an education talking to every person
present. However, I couldn't help but notice that there seems to be a
pervasive macho streak in the game industry, sustained by the belief
that game development is considerably harder and more creative than any
other form of software. Or, as I have overheard game developers saying,
first hand, &lt;em&gt;than any other human endeavor&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Not rocket science&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, there's no doubt that different niches of the software industry
vary in complexity, just as the commitment and experience of
individuals, teams and organisations varies over an enormous range. I
have no doubt that game development lies on the upper part of that
spectrum rather than in the middle. But I also have no doubt that there
are lots of other software industries which are just as complex,
demanding and creative as game development.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Game dev is not special or unique in having many hard problems to solve.
When game devs claim that it is, it simply looks like a defensive
reaction to the pervasive belief outside the industry that games are
trivial time-wasting distractions, and that creating them must therefore
be one of the easiest and most lightweight aspects of IT.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This would be merely silly self-delusion if that was as far as it went,
but this state of affairs actually has huge damaging knock-on effects.
The belief that they are tackling projects which are harder than other
software projects leads to an attitude verging on arrogance - an
assumption of superiority, and that they have nothing to learn from the
rest of the software industry. As a result, game dev shops don't even
attempt to talk to other software engineers about their common craft,
and as a result the engineering prowess of the game industry actually
&lt;em&gt;lags behind&lt;/em&gt; the rest of the software industry by five or ten years.
Practices and techniques which are &lt;em&gt;de rigour&lt;/em&gt; in the rest of the
industry these days, such as test-driven development and continuous
integration, are virtually unknown in the game industry. Examples during
last night's discussion, which were held up as indicators of how
difficult and complex game dev is, appeared to many people in the room
to simply be symptoms of clearly bad design.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The legendary long hours and project burnout in the game industry is
actually a symptom of this - far from being the most capable engineers
amongst us, the reason they are working such ungodly hours is to
compensate for poor software engineering. The rest of the software
industry used to suffer from a similar overwork problem, but you know
what? We figured it out, decades ago now. It's notable to me that other
industries which suffer from overwork and burnout (eg. the finance
industry) are also buzzing with arrogance and secrecy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Humility and communication are pre-requisites for any learning. Jeez,
get over yourselves and go learn how to run a software project.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>gamedev</category><category>geek</category><category>meetup</category><category>software</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/london-geek-night-game-dev/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 22 Nov 2008 20:19:48 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>PyCon UK 2007</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/pycon-uk-2007/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="PyCon UK 2007 view from the front" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2007/09/pycon.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Had a marvellous time at &lt;a href="http://pyconuk.org/index.html"&gt;PyCon UK
2007&lt;/a&gt;, a conference about the
&lt;a href="http://python.org"&gt;Python&lt;/a&gt; programming language. In the event everyone
from &lt;a href="http://resolversystems.com"&gt;Resolver&lt;/a&gt; bar one of our directors
went along. We met loads of great and interesting folks, heard many
excellent talks, and gave a few of our own:
&lt;a href="http://www.voidspace.org.uk/python/weblog/index.shtml"&gt;Michael&lt;/a&gt; talked
about &lt;a href="http://www.voidspace.org.uk/ironpython/webide/webide.html"&gt;driving Microsoft's natty new Silverlight technology using
IronPython&lt;/a&gt;.
Giles talked about his concept of the &lt;em&gt;New Age of the Amateur:
End-user Computing without Tears&lt;/em&gt;, and I gave a little talk about
test-driven development for beginners, which can be downloaded here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.tartley.com/files/2007/11/tddbrookssilverbullet.zip" title="TddBrooksSilverBullet.zip (871kb)"&gt;TddBrooksSilverBullet.zip
    (871kb)&lt;/a&gt;
    (zip of the presentation and accompanying source code)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My few &lt;a href="https://photos.google.com/album/AF1QipMCq2rBgyBpQLK596zqHJVTAdQu0yUe9ngrXWEb"&gt;photos&lt;/a&gt; are also online.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>geek</category><category>meetup</category><category>presentations</category><category>python</category><category>software</category><category>testing</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/pycon-uk-2007/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 13 Sep 2007 18:57:26 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>