<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>tartley.com (Posts about philosophy)</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://www.tartley.com/tags/philosophy.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2025 &lt;a href="mailto:tartley @ tartley dot com"&gt;Jonathan Hartley&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 31 Jan 2025 05:36:56 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>A Layman's Philosophical Musings</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/a-laymans-philosophical-musings/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;A quick response to to polymath Chris DeLeon's thoughtful post
&lt;a href="http://cdgdl.com/lessons/philosophy.html"&gt;exhorting the virtues of
Philosophy&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A position of ignorance&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Right off the bat I should qualify all this by saying that I don't know
anything about Philosophy. I've never studied it. It seems at times to
be an alien mismatch to the sensibilities of my left-brained mind, and
worse, one that claims to be about logic and reasoning, topics that
ostensibly should be right up my alley. I read Bertrand Russell's
&lt;em&gt;History of Western Philosophy&lt;/em&gt; last year, and although that was a
fabulous, educational romp through the field, &lt;a href="https://www.tartley.com/posts/history-of-western-philisophy"&gt;my complaints about
it&lt;/a&gt; still stand. Now I'm reading a second
book, &lt;em&gt;Think : A Compelling Introduction to Philosophy&lt;/em&gt; by Simon Blackburn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Process&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The process of &lt;em&gt;thinking about things&lt;/em&gt; is a valuable and worthwhile
endeavour. Some people enjoy it, some people don't. Amongst those who
enjoy it, it becomes an end unto itself, and thought and discussions
typically stray towards the more abstract, the more meta, the more
foundational. Anyone who has gleefully participated in a pub discussion
about religion, death, reality, consciousness, government, or any of a
million other topics has participated in this process. It is joyful,
sometimes enlightening, entertaining, and refines the individual's
ability to meaningfully reason on all kinds of topics, from the abstract
to the prosaic. In this sense, and especially from the perspective of
the individual's active participation in the activity, I'm all in favour
of philosophy. Presumably this is why I have been drawn back to read
this second book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Content&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If anything, I have had more objections to &lt;em&gt;Think&lt;/em&gt; than I had to
Russell's book. At first, I thought that my issue was simply that the
discussed historical philosophers produced curiously shoddy work. Their
premises seem shaky. Their arguments full of holes at best. Their
conclusions entirely suspect. While there are some genuinely insightful
ideas and arguments, they are often mutually contradictory, and the
signal to noise is terrible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chris points out the importance of reading a decent translation of the
original sources to gain enough insight to benefit from the arguments,
and in this I defer to his experience. There certainly are some
historical philosophers who seem to make a lot more sense to me than the
others. I had not expected to have to pick and choose based so much upon
my own personal preferences, so in some way my frustration here is
perhaps indicative of an expectation mismatch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As for &lt;em&gt;Think&lt;/em&gt;, as I continue to read, it has slowly dawned on me that
perhaps this impression is actually because the author himself is an
appalling philosopher (sorry Simon!) Every few pages he makes what seems
to me like a terrible logical blunder. If this were correct, that would
presumably make his interpretation of historical philosophers equally
suspect, and perhaps this is why they so often seem simply ludicrous to
me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I realise it is arrogant and bonkers for me to assume I can outclass the
author, a man apparently of considerable knowledge and experience, at
his own game. But this is how it seems to me, so what am I to make of
that?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It seems to me that there are only three possibilities:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Professor Blackburn's thinking is entirely defective. I am sure this
    cannot be the case. He is a professor of his subject, his book,
    while quite understandably not comparable to Russell, has garnered
    great reviews on Amazon and in the press, for whatever that's worth.
    As a layman I shall accord him the deference that is entirely his
    due.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;My own thinking is entirely defective. This is, of course, entirely
    possible, however distasteful it may be to me. How would I know? In
    defence of my sanity, I note that I seem to get by, more or less, in
    everyday life. Or at least, I don't seem to be any more confounded
    by the state of the world than the people around me.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Perhaps, then, the problem lies not solely with myself, but is
    shared by us all. Perhaps human reasoning as expressed in the
    English language is generally not sufficiently precise, well-defined
    or powerful to support consistent philosophical arguments of the
    type that are being put forward. More generally, we aren't remotely
    as good at thinking as we think we are. Pretty much I'm saying
    that (1) and (2) are both true, but that both the professor and I
    can derive some comfort from the idea that the same applies to
    pretty much everybody else.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Method&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is, of course, a method for dealing with the unreliability of our
thoughts and perceptions - the scientific method, in its many forms and
manifestations. I have friends who claim that the scientific method came
out of philosophy, and while I have some reservations about the truth of
this in the day-to-day reality of individual practitioners, of course in
an abstract sense I can see that this lineage is real.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Application of the scientific method would be the normal way out of the
morass of imprecise thoughts that, to date, characterise the majority of
philosophy for me. Some aspects of ancient philosophy have proven
tractable in this regard. These are the subjects that have subsequently
calved off from philosophy to form whole new fields and sciences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, this has the curious effect of diluting the perceived value
of philosophy. As soon as the application of the scientific method lets
thinkers actually gain any traction and start to make real progress on
their topic, we immediately snip that subject off from the realm of
philosophy and give it a different name. Astronomy and cosmology,
biology and psychology, chemistry, physics, and many more. Philosophy
proper, then, consists of the left over bits - the topics upon which the
scientific method has not proven applicable, and hence upon which no
meaningful progress can be made.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chris, and discussion with friends, has helped me see that in this
dismissal, I was overlooking the value of philosophy as an incubator for
other fields. This is of course critical to the development of human
civilisation, and of interest to historians of the respective fields.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What it isn't&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I'm left with is the impression that my minor experiences of
philosophy would have been much improved if my expectations had been
very different at the outset.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My layman's impression of philosophy from the outside was that it
claimed to be the study of tremendously insightful reasoning done by
some of the most powerful minds in history. This expectation was
naturally bound to lead me to be disappointed when my initial foray led
me to discover that many philosophers, particularly ancient ones,
distorted as they are by translation and interpretation, cultural
mismatch, and lack of my modern knowledge of the world, appear to my
sensibilities to be pretty poor. I hope to improve on this situation by
taking on board Chris' advice about choosing particular philosophers who
resonate for me personally, together with the idea of studying
particular translations of original works, rather than quick summaries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition, I had an expectation that all this intense thought might
lead to some more definitive and objective conclusions. However ancient
philosophers acted without the benefit of the scientific method, and
modern philosophy is pruned of topics to which the scientific method is
applicable. As a result, there is much bad mixed in with the good. Even
the good parts cannot be trusted as a guide to any sorts of truth, since
choosing 'the good parts' seems to be a subjective process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This seems inevitable, since without the benefit of the scientific
method, there is no utility function to be used as feedback, by which
ideas could be judged and one school of thought meaningfully compared
against another. There can be no definitive winners or losers, and
without competition, ideas cannot improve by evolution. Instead, each
contributor adds their own voice to the mutually contradictory babble,
and it is left to the reader to sift through for the parts of value.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The lack of an objective means to prune the discussion of its less
worthy branches mean that many philosophers are deified, their writings
sacrosanct and studied for generations, even in cases where they were
clearly absolutely wrong. (Plato's thoughts about the shapes of atoms,
for example.) I accept that study of historical and ancient philosophers
is valid for the perspective it gives on the &lt;em&gt;process&lt;/em&gt; of philosophy,
and as a study of the &lt;em&gt;history&lt;/em&gt; of philosophy itself. However, I am
appalled that so much of their actual, specific writings are studied and
discussed in so much detail, in the same way I would be mortified by the
prospect of scholars spending centuries reviewing the specifics of what
me and my friends said in our philosophical discussions in the pub.
There may be some value in there, but I came to this expecting a précis
of the best minds in the world, not a mishmash of sometimes incoherent
ideas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Upshot&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've done a lot of bitching, but don't take it as a wholesale rejection.
In addition to the things I complain about, there are also a bunch of
really great, stimulating ideas. I just didn't expect to have to do so
much searching and interpretation to find them. Rather, interpret the
above as the painful transitions in my understanding of what philosophy
&lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt;, which parts of it are likely to be of value to me, and what I
should expect from it. Thanks to Chris for his significant contributions
towards my continuing education on this.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>imho</category><category>philosophy</category><category>russell</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/a-laymans-philosophical-musings/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 10 Oct 2009 20:09:20 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>History of Western Philosophy</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/history-of-western-philosophy/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="historyofwesternphilosophy.jpg" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2007/07/historyofwesternphilosophy.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Bertrand Russell (1946)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've clearly been putting off this post for &lt;em&gt;months&lt;/em&gt;, no doubt
intimidated by my assumption that my review would have to be as weighty
and well-considered as the tome itself. Screw that, a crap post is
better than no post at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, I enjoyed it greatly. It is a triumph in illustrating the
breadth of the domain to a philosophical layman. It was as fascinating
for me for the context in which different movements have arisen, for
example the operation and mores of of ancient societies which differed
greatly from our own, such as the Spartans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In truth, my original acquisition of the book was partly motivated by a
desire to justify my longstanding dismissal of philosophy as a
meaningful discipline, and this narrow minded and self-fulfilling
expectation was indeed confirmed to some extent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The opening portion of the book, about ancient philosophy, made it all
too easy to infer that the gems of ancient philosophy are very much rare
pinnacles of achievement, set amidst a babble of incoherent theories and
proclamations. The valuable ideas must be carefully searched out,
extracted and refined, much as one might pan for gold on expansive
shores of mud. However, this gratifying exercise in belittlement also
brought with it an increment of my understanding as to why I feel this
way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.ashersarlin.com/archives/2005/01/oh_come_on_plat.php"&gt;&lt;img alt="Plato's greatest finest hour" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2008/02/platos-greatest-hour.gif"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It may be all very well for me to sit here nitpicking from atop the
cumulative results of thousands of years of hindsight, but my shrill,
gauche layman objections seem to be rarely well presented, and even less
often indulged with a sensible rebuttal, so I'm glad that I read the
book and gained some context in which to articulate them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The raising of the intellect above the concerns of mere empiricism, as
typified by the schools of Descartes and Plato, seems to be completely
undermined by the apparently overlooked fact that there is no objective
way of apprising the workings of 'pure reason.' The human mind, of
course, is not capable of 'pure reason', if there even is such a thing,
and is equally incapable of recognising its presence or absence in any
given supposition. As a result, all exercises in deduction are extremely
fallible, and this should come as no surprise to anyone who has ever
forgotten or misjudged something. Just because the mind is not well
understood, that does not make its machinations any less empirical than
the evidence of the senses - what seems to us like logic is entirely
subject to the vagueries of our implementation, regardless of whether or
not our mind's implementation is embodied in our apparent physical
brains or not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To elevate the conclusions reached by this process above the concerns of
mere empiricism is to put them beyond the reach of any form of feedback
or discernment, a state of affairs which leads to entirely nonsensical
stances standing uncontested for hundreds of years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because of this, I would argue that the teachings of thinkers such as
Plato have in fact &lt;em&gt;hindered&lt;/em&gt; the development of modern thought, not
just by by blazing trails down several blind alleys, but more
critically, by then systematically putting their own conclusions beyond
the reach of criticism and refinement, effectively removing the
intellectual tools that might have enabled pupils to retrace their
steps, and map out the geography of thought more thoroughly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second portion of the book is the weakest, dealing with the only
form of educated rumination occurring during the middle ages, which was
religious in nature. It is perhaps unsurprising that a period such as
this is notable for it's lack of original thought, barring individuals
every few centuries such as Aquinas. As a result, large parts of this
section degenerate into a litany of power struggles, assassinations and
coronations, notable only for their tedium.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The final portion deals with modern philosophers, which regains the
interest of the early sections, by virtue of describing the works of
less religiously restricted protagonists, nurtured by the widening
availability of education and communication, resulting in a glorious,
chaotic competition of ideas. It was only during this section that I
feel I gained an appreciation for the process itself, as opposed to the
teachings of individual practitioners.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We, as humans, are rubbish at the act of thinking - we leap to
conclusions, exhibit enormous biases, forget things, overlook things,
make faulty correlations, are inconsistent, are influenced by personal
gain and traumatic past experience, and worst of all: we are incapable
of seeing these weaknesses - completely blind to our own incompetence.
The means by which we evaluate our own conclusions are tied inextricably
to the mechanism which derived them in the first place - we always think
we are right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given this, it is no surprise that we can never agree on anything. We
can never see each other's point of view. Whether tackling the problems
of day-to-day life, or pondering the riddles of existence, a million
different people will jump in a million different directions, no two
quite the same. Most of those ideas turn out to be worthless. Idiocy
that is detrimental or ineffectual. Only a few of them stick - and there
is no way of knowing the merit or otherwise of any idea unless you have
some criteria to judge them by. In day-to-day living, some ideas will
allow the individual or group to prosper and be happy. In fields where
objective measurement is possible - the sciences - then cumulative
progress can be made, as successful ideas are shared and built upon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, outside of these domains, we may be captivated and entranced by
the enthralling pictures philosophy presents to us, and our lives may be
enriched as a result. But without any means of discerning the good ideas
from the bad, we are are forever doomed to explore a multitude of
alternative, competing, overlapping intellectual explorations, without
any knowledge of which ones are meaningful, and which ones are purely
fanciful. It may be great fun, but it's masturbation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rating: 8/10: The box with which to call me &lt;em&gt;philistine&lt;/em&gt; is below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: both"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>media</category><category>non-fiction</category><category>philosophy</category><category>russell</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/history-of-western-philosophy/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 17 Feb 2008 01:56:26 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>