<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>tartley.com (Posts about politics)</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://www.tartley.com/tags/politics.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2025 &lt;a href="mailto:tartley @ tartley dot com"&gt;Jonathan Hartley&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 12 Feb 2025 17:59:25 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Ur-Fascism</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/ur-fascism/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Ur-Fascism cover" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2023/ur-fascism-cover.webp"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Umberto Eco, 1995.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eco's prose has left me in the dust on occasion in the past. I missed so many references, or failed to keep up with the relentlessly nested layers of meaning, that I was simply holding on for the ride. This essay matches Eco's characteristically dense, intellectual prose, studded with foreign phrases, and references to contemporary thinkers, historical movements and causes and revolutions and dictatorships, and their antecedents. But it is short, and perhaps in contrast to the flourishes of brilliance that comprise his fiction, this is a factual piece, and is written to be understood rather than to dazzle. It begins by establishing Eco's credentials to speak on this topic, with the first of several entrancing first-hand indications of what it was like to grow up as an intellectual young child in Italy under Mussolini, and the revelations that followed at the opening up of his world at the end of WWII.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He differentiates between the truly totalitarian fascism of, say, Nazism, which subordinated all of life to the state, with the looser, less coherent Italian fascism, noting that this did not derive from any increment of tolerance, merely the absence of a sufficiently encompassing underlying philosophy. Despite this, it is the Italian mode, which was the first right wing dictatorship in modern history, from which subsequent dictators seem to have drawn most stylistic inspiration, and from which our generic term of "fascism" derives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last half of the essay describes how fascism means different things in different contexts, but the various incarnations through history have exhibited sufficiently overlapping sets of symptoms as to glean a family resemblance. Eco enumerates 13 identifying traits, noting that the presence of even one of them can be sufficient to allow fascism to coagulate around it. Mostly for my own benefit, (with my own parenthesised observations) they are, briefly:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fascism incorporates a cult of tradition. This can be deployed as an automatic refutation of any undesirable new ideas, enshrining in their place the immutable wisdom of a mythical past. In addition, traditionalism undermines the perceived value of learning in itself - pre-emptively thwarting troublesome intellectuals. This anti-intellectual received wisdom, in order to provide whichever justifications are required of it, requires the syncretistic combination of various ancient beliefs. As a result it must tolerate contradictions. Indeed, the more stark they are, the better they serve the purpose of selecting followers who will obediently think whatever they are told.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rejection of modernism. This is a powerful recruiting tool, enabling the fascist to leverage any dissatisfaction of the populous, laying claim to the emotionally appealing universal solution of a regression to simpler, happier times, while simultaneously rewinding societal progress in equality or liberty. While Nazis and fascists love their technology, this is a superficial tool, used in support of a deeply regressive project, namely the restoration of power to those with the strength and the will to take it. This irrationality goes hand in hand with anti-intellectualism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Value vigor and action above reflection. Thinking is emasculation. Culture is suspect insofar as it aligns with any sort of critical theory or values. Regard centers of analysis or learning such as libraries or universities with suspicion for harboring - or even indoctrinating - people of opposing political viewpoints. Again, this is deeply intertwined with (1) &amp;amp; (2), and its prevalence pre-emptively defuses any kind of mainstream understanding or critique.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of the above make it inevitable that any given fascist regime will be rife with internal contradictions.  While modernity achieves its intellectual prowess through the nurturing of diverse thought, fascism cannot possibly withstand any critical analysis. Hence, disagreement is treason.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fascist appeal to popularity exploits and exacerbates the natural fear of &lt;em&gt;the other&lt;/em&gt;, and hence is always inherently racist. Expect demonization of immigrants, foreigners, other nation states, as well as other marginalized groups, taking advantage of whatever local contemporary biases and fears might be present.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The above exploitation takes the form of an appeal to the frustrations of the middle class - or whichever class can be most useful and readily mobilized by persuasion that their problems are caused by some identifiable other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Modernity genuinely does disintegrate traditional social bonds, along with sources of identity and meaning. Fascism's solution to this is to unify the disaffected under the only remaining banner common to them all, that of patriotism and nationalism. This unity is strengthened by emphasis on the country's enemies, and especially by conspiracy theories of secret international plots against the nation. Followers must feel besieged (as Trump advised the January 6th crowd that "America is under siege"). Eco makes special mention, in the U.S, of Pat Robertson's &lt;em&gt;The New World Order&lt;/em&gt;, but potential sources of conspiracy are innumerable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Followers can be riled into frenzy of humiliation at their enemies' wealth or power. Jews control the
world and its money. Instead of coastal liberals, refer to coastal elites. But at the same time, the instinct to action requires that enemies can easily be defeated. Hence enemies are simultaneously too weak and too strong. Herein lies one of fascism's greatest weaknesses, responsible for several lost wars, in that it is constitutionally incapable of objectively assessing an enemy's strength.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Goad followers into violent action with rhetoric not just of a struggle for survival, but by declaration that life is struggle, and hence pacifism is conspiring with the enemy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While fascism appeals for the participation of the population by promising empowerment for the majority, its naked power lust is a fundamentally aristocratic endeavor. The leader takes power from those too weak to oppose  him, disdaining both conquered rivals and the subjugated population. Power struggles within the Party are vicious, and the party rides roughshod over the citizens, who likewise are leagues above the disenfranchised. The hierarchy is strict, steep, and ruthless. Elitism abounds, as does fear of losing one's status.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The redress of modernity's threadbare social fabric, by emphasizing nationalism and strength, further erodes interpersonal solidarity. Each individual must becomes their own hero. Strong, independent, and utterly without recourse in times of need. The cult of the hero is intimately entwined with a cult of death. Having only the narrow causes of the nation and the Party to live for, the hero yearns for a heroic death - or, better, to demonstrate their power and status by sending others to their death.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The preeminent will to power, so often frustrated in an aristocratic, dog-eat-dog social order, manifests alternately in things like machismo, disdain for women, and phallic fetishization of weapons. Repressed insecurity breeds an outward contempt for unconventional sexuality, including chastity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Under fascism, the people have no innate rights, and hence no material preferences or expression. Instead, the leader pretends to interpret the Will of the People. This charade requires the party apparatus to select and amplify some emotional response of the people, and present it as representative, so that the party can be empowered to act on behalf of that supposedly majority. Consider the amplifications of manufactured outrage about culture war issues, so that elected representatives are empowered to act decisively on their own preferences, against the majority of the population's wishes. This leads directly to confrontation with institutions such as a parliament. Fascism will therefore cast aspersions on any properly functioning parliament's legitimacy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All fascisms make use of their own varieties of NewSpeak, using an impoverished vocabulary and syntax, in order to limit the instruments for critical reasoning. This may appear in apparently innocent forms, from schoolbooks to popular talk shows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>essays</category><category>media</category><category>non-fiction</category><category>politics</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/ur-fascism/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 12 Jul 2023 00:41:42 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>US Civics for Naturalization Quiz</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/basic-us-civics/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;I had to learn 100 questions and answers for my US Naturalization civics
quiz this week, and my default way of learning something is to organize the information
into an essay. Not the best work I've ever done, but it got me through the
test, so good enough. Some of these assertions seem somewhat debatable, but my
job here is to learn what the test tells me are the right answers. In some
places I've elaborated around the edges with extra info that isn't on the test,
but helps me to contextualize and remember.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;History&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The region now occupied by the US was originally settled by Native Americans,
probably travelling from the Far East, around 15,000 years ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Modern Native tribes include Apache, Arawak, Blackfeet, Cherokee, Cheyenne,
Chippewa, Choctaw, Creek, Crow, Hopi, Huron, Inuit, Iroquois, Lakota, Mohegan,
Navajo, Oneida, Pueblo, Seminole, Shawnee, Sioux, and Teton.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;European colonists came to America to escape persecution, in pursuit of religious
and political freedom, and economic opportunity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Atlantic slave trade took Africans to the American colonies as slaves. This
practice was widespread by the time of the American Revolution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The colonists decided to fight for freedom from British rule because:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They didn't want to pay high taxes to the British government without representation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They did not like the British army being quartered in their houses.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They wanted self-government.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By the time of the declaration of independence, there were thirteen colonies that
became the initial thirteen United States:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Connecticut&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Delaware&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Georgia&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Maryland&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Massachusetts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;New Hampshire&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;New Jersey&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;New York&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;North Carolina&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pennsylvania&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rhode Island&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;South Carolina&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Virginia&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These States fought the American Revolutionary War against Great Britain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 1803 (27 years after the declaration of independence), the United States
bought the Louisiana territory from France.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Founding&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Declaration of Independence&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;Declaration of Independence&lt;/em&gt; declared the United States to be independent
of, and free from, the rule of Great Britain. It was written by Thomas
Jefferson, and adopted on July 4th, 1776.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It notes the right of all men to enjoy life, liberty and the pursuit of
happiness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The American Constitution&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The supreme law of the land is the &lt;em&gt;constitution&lt;/em&gt;. It sets up and defines the
government, and also enumerates the basic rights of American citizens and
residents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The idea of self-government is represented in the constitution's first three
words: "&lt;em&gt;We the people...&lt;/em&gt;".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The constitution was written at the &lt;em&gt;constitutional convention&lt;/em&gt; of 1787, by
the &lt;em&gt;Founding Fathers&lt;/em&gt;. Its passage was supported by the Federalist Papers,
written by James Madison, Alexander Hamilton, and John Jay, under the pseudonym
"&lt;em&gt;Publius&lt;/em&gt;", after &lt;em&gt;Publius Valerius Poplicola&lt;/em&gt;, a Roman aristocrat who led the
overthrow of the monarchy to found the Roman Republic in 509 BC.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Benjamin Franklin is known as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Oldest member of the constitutional convention,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The first Postmaster General of the United States,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Writer of "Poor Richard's Almanac",&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Starter of the first free libraries,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A US diplomat.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;George Washington is known as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The first President&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The "Father of our Country"&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The original text of the constitution has since been modified by twenty-seven
&lt;em&gt;amendments&lt;/em&gt;, each of which is numbered, and takes the form of an addition to
the existing text.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Rights and Responsibilities&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first ten amendments are known as &lt;em&gt;"the Bill of Rights"&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first amendment prohibits the government from infringing on the right of
residents in the US to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Establish or practice any religion, or no religion at all.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Free speech.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Freedom of the press.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Peaceably assemble.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Petition the government for a redress of grievances.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The final four items above are together known as "freedom of expression".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition, the constitution establishes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The right to bear arms.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;US citizens are granted additional rights that do not apply to all residents,
including:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Running for federal office&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Voting in federal elections&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And US citizens are additionally assigned responsibilities:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jury service&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Voting in federal elections&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Voting in federal elections is thus established as both a right and a
responsibility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The pledge of allegiance declares loyalty to the US flag and the United States.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ways for citizens to participate in their democracy include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Voting&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Join a political party&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Help with a political campaign&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Join a civic or community group&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Give opinions to elected officials, such as calling Senators or Representatives.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Publicly support or oppose an issue or policy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Run for office&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Write to a newspaper&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When becoming a naturalized US citizen, the oath of allegiance declares one will:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Give up loyalty to other countries&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Be loyal to the United States&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Obey the laws of the United States&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Defend the constitution and laws of the United States&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Serve in the US military (if the law demands it)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Serve civil projects for the nation (if the law demands it)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All men resident in the USA must register for &lt;em&gt;selective service&lt;/em&gt; (a list from which
draftees are chosen should the need arise) between the ages of 18 and 26.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last day to submit federal income tax forms is April 15th.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Voting rights&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The enfranchisement and disenfranchisement of different groups has been a
moral and political issue throughout United States history.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The original constitution did not explicitly specify who was able to vote,
and states demonstrated considerable diversity in whom they did or did not grant
suffrage to. In particular, most states only granted the vote to white, male,
property owners - about 6% of the population.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the 1820s, attitudes and state laws shifted, to allow all white males to
vote in most states, although some laws removing the poor's right to vote
continued until the 20th century, and practices that disproportionately
affect the poor's ability to vote continue today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several constitutional amendments successively modified who can vote,
notably:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The 15th Amendment of 1870, in the wake of the Civil War and Emancipation
  Proclamation, prevented the denial of voting rights based on a person's race.
  This was effectively interpreted to mean that &lt;em&gt;men&lt;/em&gt; (not women) of any race
  could vote. However, states continued to prevent the majority of African
  Americans in the United States from voting, via Jim Crow laws, poll taxes,
  literacy tests, grandfather clauses and the like. Only later in the 20th
  century were these laws ruled unconstitutional.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The 19th Amendment of 1920 allowed women to vote. However, in practice, women
  — who were rarely in control of independent sources of income —
  were usually still prevented from voting by the same discriminatory practices
  that prevented voting by poor or non-white men. For example, federal laws
  preventing banks from denying women to hold bank accounts were not passed
  until 1960. (France was a trailblazer in this, passing equivalent laws in
  1881, while the UK trailed, at 1975.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The 24th amendment of 1964 prohibited using a poll tax to control who could
  vote in federal elections.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The 26th amendment of 1971 lowered the voting age from 21 to 18. This was
  passed in response to Vietnam War protest, which noted that if draftees were
  considered old enough to be sent to fight, they should also be old enough to
  vote.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following section was not part of the USCIS civics test. But I'm including it
because it's clear that although the Declaration asserted "all men are created
equal", subsequent laws and behavior has severely curtailed that assertion when it
comes to issues such as being allowed to vote. So, who currently is, and is
not, allowed to vote? Sometimes the best way to understand something is to
trace its contours, by enumerating the exceptions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those who are currently legally denied the right to vote, for reasons that seem
potentially reasonable:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Those aged under 18.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Those deemed mentally "incapacitated" or "incompetent" by a conservatorship
  process.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Illegal or undocumented immigrants (16 million people).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following people are also legally denied the vote, for reasons that I personally
find unreasonable:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;US Citizens and nationals who reside in the United States territories that are
  not States, such as Puerto Rico.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Washington DC residents (718,000 people) have had the right to vote in
  presidential elections since 1961, but no congressional elections have been
  held there since 1801.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Non-citizen residents of the United States such as myself (13 million
  people). This includes legal aliens in good standing, such as foreign
  spouses, asylum claimants and refugees, who might reside within the US,
  paying taxes, for years or decades. Contrast this with the United Kingdom,
  for example, where people in the similar category "with leave to remain" &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt;
  able to vote.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The homeless (580,000 people) are often excluded from voting by residency
  requirements, or by the inability to register without a mailing address or proof
  of identity.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Current prisoners, in almost all states (5.5 million people). Some states
  impose a lifelong denial of voting rights to anyone with a previous felony
  record, which affects another 5.9 million people.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;US Citizens who have never established residence in the United States may be
  denied the vote by various states.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The above categories represent 28.8 million people, around 11 percent of
the adult population, who currently have no legal right to vote for US government
positions due to reasons I personally find controversial or wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Activists&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Susan B Anthony was a prominent activist for womens rights and civil rights.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Martin Luther King Jr. fought for civil rights, to try and provide equality for
Americans of all races.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Wars&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The United States has waged many wars, including:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;18th Century Wars&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;American Revolutionary War to free America from British rule.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cherokee-American wars&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Northwest Indian War&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Quasi-War (a naval war, allied with Britain, against France &amp;amp; Guadeloupe)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;19th Century Wars&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;56 official wars, mostly resulting in the genocide or internment of various
indigenous Native American nations. Sometimes the United States was allied with
or fighting against Great Britain, and sometimes on the soil of other foes such
as the Ottoman Empire and Morocco, China, Mexico, Spanish Florida, the
Philippines, Cuba, Puerto Rico, or Guam. Notable among these wars were:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The War of 1812 against Great Britain&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Mexican-American war, in the disputed former Mexican territories of
  Texas, New Mexico, California and regions of Mexico.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The American Civil War.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Spanish-American war.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;The Civil War&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The American Civil War of 1861 to 1865 was fought between the United States and
the Confederacy of Southern States, over the issues of whether slavery was to
remain legal in the Southern States, upon which many southern white livelihoods
and businesses depended. This is sometimes framed as an academic disagreement about
"States Rights" to self-government, but I personally find it hard to interpret
that as anything other than a disingenuous fig leaf.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abraham Lincoln lead the Northern states to victory in the Civil War, and is praised
for saving or preserving the Union. He presided over the Emancipation
Proclamation which ostensibly freed the slaves, although many still suffer from
ongoing repercussions and outright racism even up to the present day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;20th Century Wars&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;31 official wars, some against outstanding Native American nations, others in
diverse locations such as Cuba, Nicaragua, Haiti, Dominican Republic, Russia,
Mongolia, Korea, Vietnam, Laos, Lebanon, Cambodia, Grenada, Libya, Iran &amp;amp;
Persian Gulf, Panama, Iraq, Kuwait, Saudi Arabia, Israel, Somalia, Bosnia,
Herzegovina, Croatia, Haiti, and Serbia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Notable amongst these were:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;World War I, during which the president was Woodrow Wilson.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;World War II, against Germany, Japan and Italy, during which the president
  was Franklin D. Roosevelt. Eisenhower was a general in this war, and
  subsequently went on to become President.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Korean War&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Vietnam War&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Persian Gulf War&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the Cold war, the main concern of the United States was, it says here,
communism. I'd wonder whether 'mutually assured destruction' might be a
contender, but that is not listed as a correct answer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;21st Century Wars&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On 11th September 2001, terrorists attacked the United States by crashing
commercial passenger airliners into the Pentagon in Virginia near Washington
DC, and the twin towers of the World Trade Center, destroying them and killing
nearly 3,000 people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This atrocity was used as a pretext for the USA's subsequent wars in Afghanistan
and Iraq, both of which ended disasterously. The USA has also engaged in 9 other
wars thus far this century, including Libya, Somalia &amp;amp; Syria.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Government&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The constitution grants the federal government power to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Print money.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Declare war.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Raise an army.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make treaties.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The states are granted power to provide:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Protection in the form of police.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fire departments.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Schooling and education.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Driver's licenses.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Zoning and land use.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The government defined by the constitution is divided into three branches:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The executive branch is formed by the President and their administration.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The legislative branch is formed by Congress.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The judicial branch is formed by the courts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The separation of powers between these three branches forms a system of checks
and balances that prevents any one part of government from becoming too
powerful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The Executive&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The President leads the executive branch. They sign bills into law, and have
veto power over new laws. They are the Commander in Chief of the military.
Presidents are elected for four year terms, in a vote that takes place in
November.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The President appoints a Cabinet of advisors. If the President cannot serve,
succession falls to the Vice President, and then to the Speaker of the House.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other cabinet-level positions include Attorney General, and Secretaries of
Agriculture, Commerce, Defence, Education, Energy, Health and Human Services,
Homeland Security, Housing and Urban Development, the Interior, Labor,
State, Transportation, the Treasury, and Veterans Affairs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The President is currently Joseph Robinette Biden Jr (Democratic).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Vice President is currently Kamala Harris (Democratic).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Speaker of the House is currently Nancy Pelosi (Democratic).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The Legislature&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Congress makes federal laws. It comprises two parts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Senate.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The House of Representatives.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;The Senate&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Senate comprises two senators from each state, yielding 100 total senators.
Each senator represents the entirety of their state. Senators are elected
for six year terms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;The House of Representatives&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each state is divided into a number of &lt;em&gt;congressional districts&lt;/em&gt;, the number
of which depends on the population of the state. Each district sends a single
representative to the House, whose job is to represent the people of their
specific district. Currently, this yields a total of 435 representatives.
Representatives are elected for two year terms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The Judicial branch&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The courts review and explain laws, resolves disputes, and decides whether
laws contravene the constitution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The "rule of law" states that every individual, no matter how highly-placed,
must obey the law, as must the government itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The highest court in the land is the Supreme Court, which comprises nine
justices, lead by Chief Justice John Glover Roberts Jr.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;States, Territories, and Geography&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The United States of America contains 335 million people, of whom around 261
million are adults. The regions of the country comprise:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;50 States (the 48 &lt;em&gt;contiguous&lt;/em&gt; States, plus Hawaii and Alaska)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Washington DC, the capital city and federal district (690,000 people).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Plus other territories:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;American Samoa (43,000 people).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Guam (169,000 people).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Northern Mariana Islands (56,000 people).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Puerto Rico (3,286,000 people).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;United States Virgin Islands (87,000 people).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For comparison, the least populated state, Wyoming, contains 581,000 people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Pacific Ocean is on the West Coast of the United States, while the Atlantic
ocean is on the East Coast.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The two longest rivers within the United States are the Missouri and the Mississippi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Statue of Liberty is on Liberty Island, in New York Harbour, on the Hudson River
near the south end of Manhattan in New York City.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;States that border Canada are: Maine, New Hampshire, Vermont, New York, Pennsylvania,
Ohio, Michigan, Minnesota, North Dakota, Montana, Idaho, Washington, and Alaska.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;States that border Mexico are: California, Arizona, New Mexico, and Texas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The flag has 50 stars to represent the 50 states, and 13 stripes to represent the
initial 13 colonies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The national anthem is &lt;em&gt;The Star-Spangled Banner&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Independence Day is celebrated every July 4th. Other national holidays are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;New Year's Day&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Martin Luther King Jr. Day&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Presidents' Day&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Memorial Day&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Independence Day&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Labor Day&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Columbus Day&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Veterans Day&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Thanksgiving&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Christmas&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;My State, Minnesota&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The capital of Minnesota is St Paul.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The current Governor of Minnesota is Tim Waltz.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The current senators for Minnesota are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Amy Klobuchar (Democratic)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tina Smith (Democratic)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The current representative for my district, the first congressional district of
Minnesota, is Jim Hagadorn (Republican).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Miscellanea&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The economic system of the United States is a capitalist, free market economy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The two major political parties in the US are the Democratic and Republican
parties.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>journal</category><category>politics</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/basic-us-civics/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 08 Jul 2022 16:19:32 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Structure of Scientific Revolutions</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/the-structure-of-scientific-revolutions/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;This post rescues content from a series of tweets I wrote in 2018.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="The Structure of Scientific Revolutions cover" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2020/the-structure-of-scientific-revolutions-cover.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Thomas S. Kuhn, 1962.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I loved &lt;em&gt;The Structure of Scientfic Revolutions&lt;/em&gt;.
It was recommended to me as having similar impact to undergraduate
classics like &lt;em&gt;Godel, Escher, Bach&lt;/em&gt;, or &lt;em&gt;The Blind Watchmaker.&lt;/em&gt; I'm going
to just summarize the content here, so: Spoilers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It begins by observing that discredited scientific theories, even those
which seem laughable today, such as phrenology, or the Ptolemaic model of the
heavens, were not crackpot theories with shaky evidence. Earnest, hardworking
practitioners refined them using sensible processes, which by the 17th century
were converging on the modern scientific method.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This process of "normal" science excels at the incremental refinement of
established scientific theories. But in practice, is unable to perform the
revolutionary transitions required to overcome outmoded theories and replace
them with others, no matter how bizarre and wrongheaded the initial theory
looks to us now with hindsight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what is the unarticulated process that is responsible for these
transitions, i.e. how do scientific revolutions happen? We have intuitive
visions of this occurring overnight. An individual experiment yields unexpected
results, contradicting conventional theory, while irrefutably supporting an
alternate theory to take its place. But in practice, this &lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; happens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At first, and often for years or centuries, no discrepancy between theory and
experiment is noticed, because the prevailing theories of the time have a
massive shaping effect on what questions it is valid to ask, what experiments
are deemed useful to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For practitioners to turn their backs on an established theory in such a time
is never productive. They are shunned for turning their backs on science
itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We see this vividly today with homeopaths (my own example, not the book's).
Often, and incorrectly, homeopathy is mocked because the theories sound
ridiculous to one steeped in a conventional understanding of chemistry.
People will jeer at how total dilution can 'obviously' have no effect,
or at the idea of water exhibiting some sort of 'memory'. But such jeering is
as scientifically illiterate as the quacks it contends with. The argument from
personal incredulity has no place in determining scientific truth. No newer
theory makes sense in the light of the more limited, and often contradictory,
paradigm that it eventually replaces. The only useful criteria is to try it
out. &lt;em&gt;Does it actually work?&lt;/em&gt; This is the axis upon which homeopathy should be
judged. (and upon which it has decisively been found wanting.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All contradictions to conventional science suffer a similar ignominious
treatment, regardless of how right they might later turn out to be. Before any
revolution of theory can overturn conventional understanding, the stage
must be set, the community prepared.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The process begins as the incremental advances of "normal" science gradually
increase the scope and precision of accepted theories. Until this point,
measurements in which experiment does not conform to theory are either ignored
as erroneous artifacts, or are dismissed as indicative of some separate,
unknown phenomena. They are never interpreted to mean prevailing theory is
wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However the growing scope &amp;amp; precision of theory and measurement gradually
uncovers more of these discrepancies, or reveals them in finer detail.
Eventually they become too prominent to ignore, and a kind of phase transition
occurs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eventually, the discrepancies become so prominent and concerning that they
are judged to be a valid area of study in themselves, rather than just annoying
aberrations. Leading practitioners devote themselves to the task. Foundations
of the specialisation that were once accepted without question now come under
scrutiny.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To partially explain the discrepancies, people introduce many incompatible
variations on current theories. The once unified field divides into cliques,
supporting different theoretical variations. The field, formerly a united mass,
calves into fragments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If one of these variations on existing theory manages to explain all
observations, then this gradually gains mindshare, until the whole community
has migrated to this new, incrementally improved theory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, in cases where a truly revolutionary change is required, such
incrementalism is insufficient, and none of the theoretical variations are
fully successful in explaining all observations. The factions' differing
underlying assumptions give them no common ground upon which to arbitrate their
differences, so their debates are irreconcilable. The fragments are melting,
into a churning liquid of disagreement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This state is notably similar to the state of a nascent field before any
established scientific theories have taken hold.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All is chaos, with different groups supporting different ideas, agreeing on
nothing. The field is in turmoil, its practitioners in genuine emotional
distress. Their personal identities are undermined. What does it mean to be a
practitioner when nobody can agree on what the field even is? Is what we do
even &lt;em&gt;science&lt;/em&gt; at all? A crisis has arrived. We are at boiling point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kuhn compares this to individuals in psychological experiments, given cunningly
contradictory sensual stimuli. At first they don't notice anything wrong about
a brief glimpse of a playing card showing a red king of clubs. As the length of
their glimpse expands, and the stimulation becomes more intrusive, the subject
starts to hesitate, and stumble on words. Suddenly it impinges on their
consciousness, and they cry out, distressed, uncertain of even basic facts. "My
God! What did I see? Are clubs always red? What's happening here?"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kuhn also compares scientific revolutions to their social and political
counterparts, in a chillingly familiar passage:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Political revolutions aim to change political institutions in ways that
those institutions themselves prohibit. Their success therefore necessitates
the partial relinquishment of one set of institutions in favor of another, and
in the interim society is not fully governed by institutions at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Initially it is crisis alone that attenuates the role of political
institutions [...] In increasing numbers, individuals become increasingly
estranged from political life, and behave more &amp;amp; more eccentrically within
it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, as the crisis deepens, many individuals commit themselves to [...] some
new institutional framework. At that point, society is divided into competing
camps or parties, one seeking to defend the old institutional constellation,
others seeking to institute some new one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once that polarization has occurred, &lt;em&gt;political recourse fails&lt;/em&gt;. Because
they differ about the political matrix within which political change is to be
achieved and evaluated, and acknowledge no common supra-institutional framework
for adjudication of differences, the parties to a revolutionary conflict must
finally resort to the techniques of mass persuasion, often including force."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At any point, the &lt;em&gt;boldest&lt;/em&gt; practitioners, often those with least invested in
the previous status quo, such as the relatively young, or those entering from
adjacent fields, will introduce strikingly different sets of theories. But only
now that the stage is set, amongst such distressing chaos, is the community
ready to entertain truly revolutionary ideas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Occasionally, one of these new ideas will succeed in explaining all the
observations, but in order to do so, it requires incommensurable changes in the
underlying philosophy of the field, from the axiomatic definitions, to the set
of questions that are valid to ask. One can no longer ask, of a spherical
Earth, "What happens if you fall off?"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Notably, many revolutionary changes are not an unalloyed good. Gains in
explicative power in one area are often balanced by losses elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As in evolution, the new theory is not necessarily more &lt;em&gt;correct&lt;/em&gt;, so much as
it is a better fit for the current circumstances, i.e. providing greater
predictive power in an area that is currently pertinent. Maybe scientific
progress is more obviously useful to society in that area, or instruments are
more capable of making measurements in that area. The two often coincide,
since influences are are unable to detect or manipulate are also unlikely to
be of much direct use to society. So as the social and technological context
evolves, so does the relative fitness of potential competing paradigms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nobody understands this trade-off more deeply than the field's most
invested practitioners, who feel the losses of losing the old model most
keenly, and therefore may resist the new paradigm for the remainder of their
careers. The new paradigm will not achieve total dominance until the field is
populated by a whole new generation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am reminded of the dark priesthood of command-line programmers, although
I note with no little joy that our merry band includes some of the best and
brightest of the next generation (as judged by my own paradigm's criteria.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: left"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>media</category><category>non-fiction</category><category>politics</category><category>science</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/the-structure-of-scientific-revolutions/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 14 Jun 2020 14:02:22 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Quote from Tim Bray</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/quote-from-tim-bray/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The iPhone vision of the mobile Internet's future omits controversy,
sex, and freedom, but includes strict limits on who can know what and
who can say what. It's a sterile Disney-fied walled garden surrounded
by sharp-toothed lawyers. The people who create the apps serve at the
landlord's pleasure and fear his anger.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hate it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hate it even though the iPhone hardware and software are great,
because freedom's not just another word for anything, nor is it an
optional ingredient.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tim Bray, &lt;a href="http://www.tbray.org/ongoing/When/201x/2010/03/15/Joining-Google"&gt;Now a No-Evil
Zone&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm increasingly aware that many of my lifestyle choices, from my
Android phone and my long-standing affection for Linux, through to my
choices of where I live and who I work for, are driven by my instinctive
dislike for being told what I can and can't do. I value my freedom.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>geek</category><category>politics</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/quote-from-tim-bray/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 15 Mar 2010 14:12:29 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Result of MP visit - I suck</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/result-of-mp-visit-i-suck/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;So earlier tonight I turned up at the monthly 'surgery' of my MP, Frank
Dobson (Labour), to present my objections to the Digital Economy Bill.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the benefit of others also going to tackle Mr Dobson on this issue,
(and anyone going to see some other MP) here's a quick write up of my
experiences:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I arrived up half an hour before it started, and there were about eight
parties ahead of me in line. My turn came half an hour after they kicked
off. I had hoped to present my argument pretty much as I laid it out in
my previous blog post. However, sadly I pretty much comprehensively
failed to get my point across.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The 'I am not a spittle-flecked loon' introduction&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As planned, I started out by saying that I fully support copyright law,
and of the importance of finding ways to ensure that artists get
renumerated for their work. The portions of the bill which describe the
pursuit of illegal downloaders therefore have laudable and important
goals, however I think that the costs and problems associated with
preventing illegal downloads like this are substantial, and actually
make this section of the bill counter-productive. Mr Dobson was an
affable gent, and listened attentively to what I had to say.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Disconnection needlessly punishes more innocent people than guilty
ones&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first objection I wanted to raise, because it seems to me to be the
most clear-cut, is that the bill suggests disconnection from the
internet for persistent downloaders. I pointed out that since most
internet connections are shared between several people (families and
housemates) disconnecting a single illegal downloader would also
unfairly affect all the people who share their connection. Mr Dobson's
opinion was that it would rarely come to actual disconnection - the
intention of the Bill is very much that disconnection would be a
rarely-used last resort. The earlier provisions in the bill (warning
offenders for their first 'two strikes') are intended to stop almost
everyone from illegally downloading, without any need for actual
disconnections to take place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obviously I regard that as a grave misjudgement. But I had a lot of
ground to cover, so I left this issue at that. I still feel that even if
disconnection were only applied to a small number of people (which seems
unlikely, from my perspective), it is still true that this would affect
more innocents than guilty parties. There is no reason not to prefer
more conventional punitive measures over disconnection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Impossibility of distinguishing guilt from innocence&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I moved onto my second point: When monitoring downloads, it is
impossible to distinguish between guilt and innocence. If I download a
song I own, from my home to my office, this behaviour may currently be
legally murky, but it is clearly morally justifiable. To any external
observer, this looks indistinguishable from illegal download. An
observer cannot tell whether a particular download is illegal or not
just by looking at the bits going down the wire - it requires more
context than that. It requires the observer to know which CDs I have
bought, and to what use I intend to put the proceeds (is it subject to
fair use exemptions, etc?) Therefore, along with many illegal
downloaders, the system proposed in the bill will also catch many
innocent people in its net.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These innocents can appeal - there is a procedure in the bill for this -
however they will find it impossible to demonstrate their innocence. If
I have bought a CD and ripped it to my computer (which I have done with
all my CDs, many years ago) then when I am accused of illegally
downloading it, how am I supposed to demonstrate that I once bought that
CD?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr Dobson listened with patience and good humour to this. However, it
was clear from his responses that while he is a capable man who is
working hard and with the best of intentions, the scenario I outlined
was fairly foreign to his experience. He suggested that the bill is not
aimed at catching people like me who are doing nothing wrong. It is
aimed at people who are making a dishonest living by massive downloads
which they are somehow making money from. I don't believe that any such
people actually exist, never mind that the bill is aimed at them: The
wording of the bill clearly encompasses individuals downloading music
for their own listening pleasure, and deliberately so, but I did not go
into this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr Dobson felt that the appeals process would be sufficient for anyone
such as my self to protest their innocence. I totally failed to
communicate that demonstrating my innocence during such an appeals
process would be very difficult. When I reiterated that I could not, for
example, produce the receipts to all the music and movies I have ever
bought in my entire lifetime, Mr Dobson reiterated that the bill was not
aimed at innocent people like me, it would only be applied to illegal
downloaders. I again said I don't see how the ISPs can distinguish
between the two - for example I cannot produce the receipts nor the CDs
that my music came from - I ripped them in 1998, and have since
discarded them all. Mr Dobson said that perhaps &lt;em&gt;when&lt;/em&gt; the bill become
law (my emphasis), people will be obliged to keep their CDs "in a
plastic bag in the garage", in preparation for just such a scenario. I
pointed out that all of my music for the last few years has been
purchased online - so never came on any CDs to begin with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr Dobson didn't seem receptive to this argument. He was still in good
spirits at this point, however, I totally failed to persuade him that
difficulty in distinguishing between guilty and innocent downloaders was
even a realistic possibility, never mind that it would actually be a
serious problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had hoped to move on from this point to demonstrate that this
presumption of guilt that the bill contains will have a severe chilling
effect on people's legitimate and morally justifiable uses of the
internet, and this will hamper the development of business models, which
will be presumptively quashed before ever getting a chance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, Mr Dobson suggested that I should send him the remainder of my
points to him in a letter. I asked him if I could just spend 30 seconds
skipping through the executive summary of the remainder of my argument,
since I felt there was a logical chain of inferences to follow, which
demonstrated some real problems with the bill. He suggested that I write
it to him in a letter instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Probable ten or fifteen minutes had elapsed. We exchanged cordial
pleasantries and headed out for a lovely curry down the street with my
awesome wife.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>geek</category><category>imho</category><category>journal</category><category>politics</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/result-of-mp-visit-i-suck/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 05 Dec 2009 05:23:09 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>[SOLVED]UK Digital Economy Bill</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/solveduk-digital-economy-bill/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;So my splendid talented intelligent handsome friend Robert (who is also
my boss, of sorts) today shared this smashing post:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://gizmodo.com/5417318/my-6247-royalty-statement-how-major-labels-cook-the-books-with-digital-downloads"&gt;My \$62.47 Royalty Statement: How Major Labels Cook the Books with
Digital
Downloads&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;About one aspect of how artists get ripped off by the labels. It's not
required reading, but you can if you like. I'll wait.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hey. So it made me realise that a very possible fix to the dreadful
abuse of artists by the labels is possible. Even better, the solution to
this appalling situation is also the solution to the dire problems with
the UK's Digital Economy Bill.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So the UK govt. are debating a new bill, part of which introduces
measures to ruthlessly pursue illegal downloaders. There are some
problems with this, namely that:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;someone (probably the ISPs) will have to monitor what everyone
    downloads, and report people downloading anything that trips their
    filters for 'copyrighted work'. Understandably, they don't want to
    do this.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It will cost lots to implement - currently estimated at 100
    million, but of course the ensuing arms race with encrypted
    downloads will inflate that. Has anyone compared this with the
    &lt;em&gt;actual&lt;/em&gt; economic losses that it is aiming to fix? (not just the
    inflated ones self-reported by those with most to gain.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is literally impossible to automatically detect breach of
    copyright accurately - it can't be done just by looking at the bits.
    There will be lots of false positives and false negatives.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It will be easy to get around, using encryption or similar
    technologies to evade detection. It will not fix the problem it aims
    to fix.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It requires representatives of the state to intrusively monitor
    every single thing we do online.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The false positives will target and punish many innocent people,
    who have no way to demonstrate their innocence.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Perhaps worst of all, its presumption of guilt will have a chilling
    effect on many legal and morally justifiable uses of the internet,
    including business models of the present and the future.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They are talking about disconnection from the internet as a
    potential punitive measure for persistent downloaders. Most internet
    connections are shared by several people, and many of us use each
    other's connections all the time. Disconnecting one person for
    something that someone else downloaded is flagrantly wrong, and
    without wishing to be melodramatic, collective punishment like this
    is, strictly speaking, in breach of article 33 of the Geneva
    Convention. Plus it makes free wi-fi impossible to provide. Are we
    meant to be &lt;em&gt;destroying&lt;/em&gt; the digital economy?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If your country doesn't have a Bill like this, rest assured, it soon
will have.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyhow, it's clear to me that there's no use in railing against the Bill
unless one has an alternative to offer. The debate in the House of Lords
yesterday made it clear that the mood there is that millions are
flouting the law with illegal downloads to rip off artists and Something
Must Be Done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what's the alternative? The solution is the final chapter from
Stanford Law Prof. Lawrence Lessig's book '&lt;a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/Free-Culture-Nature-Future-Creativity/dp/0143034650"&gt;Free
Culture&lt;/a&gt;',
that describes how to fix the whole copyright mess in such a way that
will make everybody happy. Artists will get paid in abundance, very
fairly, in a market-driven way, and the payment will be direct to them.
The labels will be eliminated from the loop. No state monitoring of what
people download will be required. Everybody will be able to continue to
download whatever they like from wherever they like, for free (at point
of use), legally and with clear conscience. Best of all, the creation of
new business models and grass-roots creativity such as songs and other
content will be stimulated through the roof. Whichever country first
introduced this would lead the world in a creative tidal wave that
embraces the powers of the internet, rather than fighting against them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm not going to write what the copyright fix is here. I have to go to
work and I'm still in my pajamas. Oh alright, here's the quick quick
version. We add a tax to every high bandwidth internet connection. The
money goes in a pot. Then a central agency samples how many of each
creative work is being downloaded. This is just a sample - it needn't be
tied to any individual downloader, so it is cheap to do and unintrusive.
Then we distribute the money in the pot to artists, in proportion to the
number of downloads they had.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This quick version has some holes in it. Prof. Lessig ties it all up in
his book. Yes it has some problems - taxes are never popular, and more
expensive internet connections are not what we want. But these problems
are small and soluble, compared to what is currently being discussed
instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know this is so starry-eyed idealistic that it has no chance of being
seriously discussed. But I decided last night that I have to at least
give it a try.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Readers from the UK - Do YOU have even the slightest inkling of
interest in suggesting this to your own MP? Or at least pointing out the
downsides of the current Bill? It would just be one evening out of your
life. I'm visiting mine this weekend. Email me if you have any interest
at all. I can lead you through the process, it's simple.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>geek</category><category>imho</category><category>lessig</category><category>politics</category><category>python</category><category>software</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/solveduk-digital-economy-bill/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 03 Dec 2009 16:04:59 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Letter to my Member of European Parliament : Proposed Copyright Extension</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/letter-to-my-member-of-european-parliament-proposed-copyright-extension/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Thursday 19 March 2009&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dear Baroness Ludford, (&lt;strong&gt;Update&lt;/strong&gt;: This was sent to all eleven of my
MEPs)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am writing with reference to the European Parliament's vote on
copyright extension for sound recordings, due to take place on March
23rd.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you know, this is a complex issue, but I shall try my best to keep
this short, I know you must be busy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Amongst the justification for this particular extension to the term of
copyrights, is the idea that artists need more protection, particularly
towards the end of their lives when their income from royalties might
dry up as their copyrights expire.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is misleading in the extreme. Under the current 50 year term, an
artist recording at age 25 will be protected until age 75, and any
artist who records throughout their lifetime will be protected until
many decades beyond their death.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is no need whatsoever to extend the term in order to benefit or
incentivise artists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, as everyone knows, artists in practice almost never end up
owning the copyrights to their own works - the labels do. While artists
and labels are aligned in the desire to sell as many records as
possible, they are in direct opposition when it comes to dividing up the
proceeds. The majority of the income from sales goes to the labels,
because they have such an overwhelmingly dominant position of power in
the relationship. No label is reliant upon any individual artist, while
every artist is very much dependant on their label, to whom they are
tied by contract for many years. Strengthening copyright only
strengthens the position of the copyright owner, ie. the labels, at the
expense of what little leverage the artist may have. Extending the term
of copyright only enhances the labels' income, not the artists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is not the role of copyright to be a protectionist measure to support
labels who are having to adjust their business models in these times of
great change. The last thing we need to do is to construct laws which
chain Europe's creative industries to last-century modes of operation,
at precisely a time when the current tumult will reveal as yet undreamed
of exciting new ways of doing business.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you know, copyright is intended to stimulate the creation of new
creative works, by enabling the artist to earn an income from their own
creations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There exists significant evidence to suggest that stronger copyright may
actually inhibit the production of creative work, by allowing
monopoly-level profits to be reaped from ever smaller amounts of
creative output. The composer Verdi is notable for suddenly decreasing
his creative output when copyright laws over music were introduced in
18th century Italy - his personal correspondence indicates that he
simply had to work less because he was earning more from his earlier
compositions. (note that he retained copyright over his own work.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Similarly, there is the very vital and oft-overlooked influence of the
creative environment which our society fosters. It could well be that
freedom to borrow and build upon inspiration from other artists is a
vital input to the engines of creativity, and to encourage fledgling
artists. By way of anecdotal evidence I say it would not be very
controversial to suggest that the last great English composer of the
Baroque period was Handel, who coincidentally died around the same year
copyright over music was introduced in England. After that, there is a
dearth of truly top-class composers from England, right up until the
20th century. Meanwhile Germany, too preocupied with invasions and
reforging of the nation to introduce copyright laws over music, went on
to produced greats like Bach, Mozart and Beethoven, in a succession of
creative gear-shifts which formed the romance and classical eras, all
done with no copyright over music. *1&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I apologise if I have been unable to express my points very succinctly,
but I hope I have made given you some reasons to consider rejecting this
extension of the copyright term, or at least to consider assessing it in
the light of evidence over its theorised effects, rather than the
deliberately misleading suppositions put forward by those representing
the special interests who stand to directly benefit from the proposal at
the expense of artists and of the rest of society.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With all my gratitude and respect for the work you and your fellow MEPs
have done and will continue to do to resolve these issues,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yours sincerely,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jonathan Hartley&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;*1 See this February 2009 Harvard paper which notes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"An attempt to determine the impact of legal changes on entry into
composing is inconclusive. The paper shows, however, that a golden age
of musical composition nevertheless occurred in nations that
lackedcopyright protection for musical works."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=1336802"&gt;http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=1336802&lt;/a&gt;
The paper is summarised persuasively in an online news article here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.techdirt.com/articles/20090308/1022324034.shtml"&gt;http://www.techdirt.com/articles/20090308/1022324034.shtml&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>imho</category><category>politics</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/letter-to-my-member-of-european-parliament-proposed-copyright-extension/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 19 Mar 2009 19:32:20 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>