<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>tartley.com (Posts about time-travel)</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://www.tartley.com/tags/time-travel.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2025 &lt;a href="mailto:tartley @ tartley dot com"&gt;Jonathan Hartley&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 26 May 2025 23:19:06 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>The Incal</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/the-incal/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="The Incal 4 cover" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2022/the-incal-4-cover.webp"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="clear: right; float: right"&gt;
&lt;img alt="The Incal The Fall " src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2022/the-incal-the-fall.webp"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="clear: right; float: right"&gt;
&lt;img alt="The Incal The Fall " src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2022/the-incal-divinity.webp"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="clear: right; float: right"&gt;
&lt;img alt="The Incal 4 cover excerpt" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2022/the-incal-4-cover-part.webp"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Written by Alejandro Jodorowsky, art by Jean Giraud (aka Mœbius), 1980-88&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I grabbed this in the English translation from the original French, having been
intrigued by the &lt;em&gt;Pocket Essential Alan Moore&lt;/em&gt;'s description of it as a
contender for "the best comic in the medium's history".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This creative pairing also worked together on
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jodorowsky%27s_Dune"&gt;the unproduced 1970s movie of Dune&lt;/a&gt;,
the one whose cast was to have included Salvador Dalí, Orson Welles,
Gloria Swanson, and Mick Jagger, and presumably would have been pretty trippy -
I mean, &lt;em&gt;even more&lt;/em&gt; trippy than the David Lynch one turned out to be. The
artist, Mœbius, has had a long and glorious career, knighted for his art in his
native France, and he worked on other movies such as Alien, Tron, The Fifth
Element, and The Abyss.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Echoes of all of these are visible throughout the consistently stunning
artwork of The Incal, and it has been explicitly noted as an influence on the
expansive decayed futurescapes of Akira and Blade Runner, and the flamboyant
visuals of the Star Wars prequels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The writing really swings for the fences, a sprawling tale of a reluctant
hero's journey, taking in societal commentary, intergalactic travel, spiritual
transformation, iconic incarnations of good and evil, and a deep thread of
mysticism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For me, it does have a very evident "foreign" feeling - small social nuances
with which I'm unfamiliar. Equally clearly, this is part of its exotic charm.
And while the story touches on, perhaps even consists of, deep themes, it
doesn't so much articulately explore them, but instead simply incorporates
them. This is not a comic for people who are not already comic fans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In lesser hands, it might have been undisciplined. But wherever the story
roams, the artwork is endlessly enthralling. I especially liked the touch of
protagonist, John DiFool, starting out distinctly ugly, but being rendered more
handsomely on the rare occasions he manages to get in touch with his more noble
aspects. Jodorowsky manages to keep it all together, bringing it around to a
splendidly satisfying theatrical close. &lt;em&gt;Bravo!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: both"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>comic</category><category>fiction</category><category>media</category><category>science-fiction</category><category>time-travel</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/the-incal/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 05 Jan 2022 19:56:03 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>This Is How You Lose the Time War</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/this-is-how-you-lose-the-time-war/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="This Is How You Lose the Time War cover" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2021/this-is-how-you-lose-the-time-war-cover.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Amal El-Mohtar &amp;amp; Max Gladstone, 2019&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's a marvellous literary romp, deploying the tropes and language of science
fiction to deliver a scintillating, poetic payload of — dare I say it —
credible romance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="background:#bb2200; color:white; border-radius: 1em; padding-left: 0.5em; padding-right: 0.5em; padding-top: 2px;"&gt;spoilers&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The combatants in the Time War seek to bring about historical outcomes which
predispose those futures which will result in the generation of their own
particular civilisation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In one future, humans have embraced machine-oriented augmentation, uploads,
and all that that implies. In the other, transformation is wrought by
biological means, accepting humankind's role as a part of a natural ecosystem,
bootstrapping the whole to greatness by a ruthless application of evolutionary
principles. Each finds the other repulsive, and their existence is mutually
exclusive. From our perspective, they appear equally awe-inspiring and terrible
to behold.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, as intriguing as all that is, it's not why we're here. Instead we get
the much more personal accounts of two omni-capable antagonists on the front
lines. Theirs is a subtle art, weaving probabilities of lasting change through
very human interventions - as well as wading knee deep in the dead when
occasion demands it, to tip the scales of pivotal battles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regarding each other with wariness and respect, from across the gulf of
realities, they battle up the threads and down the braids of innumerable
possible pasts and futures. Until they begin sending what can only be
characterized as &lt;em&gt;letters&lt;/em&gt; to each other, albeit often encoded in startlingly
— poetically — obscure ways, so as to remain secret from their enemies and
their masters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Around these letters are formed the novel's tight, alternating structure,
reminding me of Bank's &lt;em&gt;Use of Weapons&lt;/em&gt;. Before you know it, their respect for
each other's skills has grown to full-blown giddy all-out love. But where to,
from there? Their communications to date are already traitorous - grounds for
terminal repercussions. Nowhen in the multiverse are they safe from their
respective commanders. Losing the time war would mean they no longer — had
never — existed. Winning the time war would mean the same for their now
beloved opposite number.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At which point, the novel cleverly folds back on itself - these are consummate
masters of time, and subtle but decisive influence, after all - to perform an
act of escapology, hinting to us that all their previous acts and letters could
be re-construed as having left a trail, ready to be exploited once the moment
was right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's a long way from my usual preference of hard-as-nails SF, but I loved it
nonetheless.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: left"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>fiction</category><category>media</category><category>novella</category><category>science-fiction</category><category>time-travel</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/this-is-how-you-lose-the-time-war/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 17 Nov 2021 20:49:26 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>11/22/63</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/112263/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="11/22/63 cover" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2021/112263-cover.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Steven King, 2011&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prompted by a conversation at work about favorite time travel stories,
I snagged this from the library.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;English school teacher Jake is roped into a dying man's plot to exploit a
mechanism of travelling back to 1958, from which, with many complications, he
waits out the intervening few years in order to prevent JFK's assassination.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I found it a page turner, certainly. But nonetheless I was slightly
disappointed, perhaps because of my reverence for such a successful author, who
I haven't actually read since my teens. Expectations of mastery clashed with
what, for me, felt like lowest-common-denominator style.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;King knows exactly what he intends - to use time travel as a hook on which to
hang a human tale of drama, aspiration and loss. He has no interest in my
personal predilections, such as messing with the logical conundrums of his
chosen time-travel mechanic, and he declares this straightforwardly. When the
main character asks "But what if I end up killing my own Grandfather?", his
mentor shoots him a look of incomprehension, replying "Why in hell would you
want to do a thing like that?" Subject closed, and fair enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: left"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>fiction</category><category>media</category><category>novel</category><category>science-fiction</category><category>time-travel</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/112263/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 11 May 2021 18:23:19 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Great Work of Time in A Science-Fiction Omnibus</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/a-science-fiction-omnibus/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="a-science-fiction-omnibus" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2008/12/a-science-fiction-omnibus.jpg" title="a-science-fiction-omnibus"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Editor: Brian Aldiss, 2007&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A collection of short stories from 1941 to 2006. Most of my favourites
in here are ones I've already read before: Asimov's &lt;em&gt;Nightfall&lt;/em&gt;, Bear's
&lt;em&gt;Blood Music&lt;/em&gt;, Aldiss' own &lt;em&gt;Poor Little Warrior!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of the ones that are new to me, not many seemed to have much appeal. A
few nicely crafted exceptions are worthy of special mention: Ward
Moore's &lt;em&gt;Lot&lt;/em&gt;, a tale of a family 's departure from home in the station
wagon as civilisation ends around them; James Tiptree's &lt;em&gt;And I Awoke and
Found Me Here on the Cold Hill's Side&lt;/em&gt;, a tragic and visceral vision of
humanity's emotional and charismatic failings amongst the sleek,
sophisticated races of the galaxy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Amongst the others, there are instances where the collection's vintage
lets it down, ideas that were once exciting and cutting edge, which have
been dulled by the passage of time and events, to expose the lackluster
writing beneath. Multiple tales of supreme computers achieving godhood,
for better or for worse. Tales of malfunctioning machinery that barely
held my interest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Great Work of Time&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine, then, my surprise, when the final story of the collection,
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Crowley"&gt;John Crowley&lt;/a&gt;'s &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Great_Work_of_Time"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Great Work
of Time&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, of which I
have never heard until now, turned out to be an absolute triumph. 75
pages of beautifully crafted prose, all by itself it is easily worth the
cost of this collection, and a more than worthy reward for the time and
effort of reading all the other stories in it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This final story is yet-another-novel-take on time-travel - at once bold
and understated, a nostalgic and wistful story of alternate histories
and the motives of the people charged with affecting the critical
junctures of human civilisation. An exquisitely crafted scene lies
embedded within the story's amber perfection, in which &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cecil_rhodes"&gt;Cecil
Rhodes&lt;/a&gt;' 23 year-old would-be
assassin is recruited for the job by none other than his elderly self,
who persuades with a moving and cathartic retelling of how the events in
question went for him. The reader at this point is already steeped in
the bitter-sweet consequences that the outcome will have for each of
their lives, for the mysterious organisation under who's auspices they
act, for the British Empire's fading hopes of uniting the world under a
single banner versus the looming spectre of future World Wars - it is so
poignant and well constructed and performed that I immediately went back
and read the whole story over again. Absolutely bloody marvellous.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rating 9/10, if you only read the last story in the book. Diluted
otherwise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update:&lt;/strong&gt; A Great Work of Time is available as a stand-alone 75 page
book on Amazon Kindle for £2.99, and Calibre with the DeDRM plugin will
convert this into an epub which can be read on any device.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: both"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>bear</category><category>book</category><category>fiction</category><category>media</category><category>science-fiction</category><category>short</category><category>time-travel</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/a-science-fiction-omnibus/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 14 Dec 2008 23:32:47 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Flight of the Horse</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/the-flight-of-the-horse/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="float: left"&gt;
&lt;img alt="The Flight of the Horse" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2007/03/the_flight_of_the_horse_f.jpeg"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Larry Niven (1969-1973)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I just got this back from long-term loan to
&lt;a href="http://frosties2.com/"&gt;Phil&lt;/a&gt;, and I just couldn't resist reading it
clean through once again. It's a quick, light read, and I honestly
couldn't really justify my love of it to a dispassionate third party.
But Niven's stuff, particularly his early short stories like this, are
always a nostalgia trip for me, representative of the ideas that got me
into science fiction as a kid in the first place. He writes throwaway
tales of quirky worlds, but each one is crafted with such a singularly
consistent exploration of the logical implications of a single, simple
premise, that with hindsight, suddenly complicit in the gag, you can
almost see how each story's conclusion grew inescapably out of the very
opening paragraphs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's very much Niven's modus operandi, and it lends itself well to a
book like this, which is essentially a couple of sets of related short
stories, in settings that verge on fantasy, but which abide by a strict
internal logic that makes them indisputably hard SF to me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="background:#bb2200; color:white; border-radius: 1em; padding-left: 0.5em; padding-right: 0.5em; padding-top: 2px;"&gt;&lt;b&gt;spoilers&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first sequence follows the fortunes of a 24th century
post-apocalyptic time traveller, who is trying his best to investigate
the past - our time, and pre-industrial ages - and bring back specimens
of long-extinct species. Things never quite go according to plan - the
horse he bags has an unexpected horn, and the whale he sought turns out
to be a biblical leviathan, until eventually, he figures out the hard
way what we the reader should have known all along - his time machine is
screwy, slipping a little &lt;em&gt;sideways&lt;/em&gt; in time every time he travels back
to the past, sometimes a little, to worlds that differ from ours merely
in happenstance, or sometimes further, to worlds that never could have
been, in which mythical beasts roam and humanity is a very different
breed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second series explores a similarly simple premise - that countless
generations ago, deep in prehistory, when magic thrived and was a
practical art in the world, a sorcerer discovers a terrible secret: that
magic uses up energy from its surroundings, and that eventually this
&lt;em&gt;mana&lt;/em&gt; runs out, leaving an area sterile of magical potential, deadly to
aged magicians, uninhabitable by mythical beasts. The knowledge is
exploited to further various agendas, a vicious cycle that accelerates
the process, that we the reader can see will inevitably lead to the fall
of their civilisation, and the immeasurable dark ages before our own
recorded history began.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's the sort of stuff that people who don't 'do' SF clearly won't have
any patience for. But if you can conjour up a little willing suspension,
can overlook the writer's unsubtle early works, then the imagination and
clarity of the tales shines through, weaving entertaining worlds of both
humour and grandeur.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rating: 7/10&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br style="clear: both"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>book</category><category>fiction</category><category>media</category><category>niven</category><category>science-fiction</category><category>short</category><category>time-travel</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/the-flight-of-the-horse/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Mar 2007 06:22:18 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>