<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>tartley.com (Posts about tv-show)</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://www.tartley.com/tags/tv-show.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2025 &lt;a href="mailto:tartley @ tartley dot com"&gt;Jonathan Hartley&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 31 Jan 2025 05:36:53 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>The Expanse</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/the-expanse/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="The Expanse screencap" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2022/the-expanse-screencap.webp"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(This post rescues content from
&lt;a href="https://www.facebook.com/mfoord/posts/10158389841835880?comment_id=10158390351245880I"&gt;a Facebook comment&lt;/a&gt; I got carried away with recently.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's so much to write about the Expanse. It's such a relief to find a
science fiction show with an ambitiously futuristic setting depicted in a way
that doesn't make scientifically literate people cringe and shout at the
television.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, it shines at taking the time for quiet moments of character work, from
Miller's lonely, poignant realization in s01 that he wasn't the talented
office maverick, just incompetent and unreliable, right up to the quiet,
unseen payoff of Naomi's years-long efforts to save her son from his father's
influence, in the final seconds of s06.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On many axes, it's the best SF on television, which is saying something, as
there are so many competitors. Science fiction output is following some sort
of Moore's law of endless expansion, in response to society's need for
mythic stories of relevance to modern life, itself a symptom of the meaning
crisis of modern society. But this is a mixed blessing, because the resulting
shows &amp;amp; movies are often drawn to using the superficial trappings of science
fiction, spaceships and lasers (pew pew!), while failing to fulfil the deeper
psychological needs of mythical or symbolic significance that brought about
their creation. The Expanse is perhaps the prime example of this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.tartley.com/posts/the-expanse/damiengwalter.com"&gt;My fantastic SF podcast guy&lt;/a&gt; defines SF as the arena in
which we forge new myths of psychological meaning for modern life, which are
sorely needed as traditional myths dwindle in relevance, as they are
predominantly based on nature and superstition. Movements such as spiritual
atheism are a reflection that even the least spiritual amongst us recognize
that something is missing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I do concede that defining SF in this way is a bit of a cheat. It's somewhat
aggrandizing, claiming any great mythic work as actually being part of the
SF genre, an no doubt is a somewhat defensive reaction to mainstream
dismissal of science fiction as puerile. But it does provide a marvellous
framework for discussion, and adopting this definition makes several
previously puzzling things fall into place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It settles the revealing, never-ending debates over which works are, and
are not, science fiction. Somewhat tellingly, to me, such debates are
irreconcilable precisely because of the misnomer "science fiction", which was
never really about the science to begin with, as this style of fiction has
existed long before science was the focus. It only gravitated towards using
science as it became apparent that is now where society's power and
transformation springs from - our incarnation of gods and magic - and the name
"science fiction" was then applied post-facto, missing the underlying fact
that this is just mythic fiction with some modern attributes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This definition perfectly explains things like how the first half of the movie
"Sunshine" could be such astonishing science-fiction, while the second half
- set aboard the exact same spaceship - is just a mediocre slasher flick.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So. SF is the arena within which we construct new mythic narratives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By this I mean that great science fiction tends to create a story that
resonates because it leans on powerful mythic tropes - symbolic
representations of psychological significance, character arcs mirroring
Jungian archetypes, thematic elements that are told allegorically, suggesting
things to the reader/watcher on a level that can be more powerful than merely
stating them directly to the conscious mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this way, all-time-great examples such as &lt;em&gt;2001: A Space Odyssey&lt;/em&gt; (the
title being conscious of this mythic entanglement) leans heavily into themes
such as humanity watched over by an ancient, mysterious, godlike alien
influence which has literally created humanity in its present form, and
observes as we now reach a second inflection point, materializing not
just a tale of personal transcendence (although it is certainly that), but one
of species-wide sublimation - suggesting that it is time for us all to reach
spiritual adulthood, to graduate to whatever comes next, to meet and be
transformed by the wise and powerful force that has shepherded humanity
through our previous prehistorical transitions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I could go on with similar examples, but will just briefly mention the original
Matrix movie, which is a story which resonates because it is absolutely soaked
in allegory of both religious transcendence and Jungian archetypes - which are
so on-the-nose that it cannot possibly be accidental, a fact acknowledged
directly by the creators in the sequels, when they depict the Architect,
ultimate villain encountered at the narrative peak of the story, as a prim,
middle aged, white bearded gentleman, wearing an Edwardian suit. He speaks in a
precise, almost Germanic manner. This is, unmistakably, Sigmund Freud. Why is
Freud the villain of the Matrix? Because Freud was a contemporaneous antagonist
to Jung, resisting Jung's ideas of self actualization through reconciliation of
the archetypes, just as the Architect resists Neo's progression along that same
path.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It may be my own lack of imagination, but compared to examples like this, the
Expanse starts to look a bit thin. I don't see any symbolism or allegory.
There is some good character work but no actual arcs of transcendence. Through
the unfortunate realities of converting books to screen, large chunks of what
could have been the most meaningful story were simply abandoned and will
apparently never be finished on the screen. In their stead, what would have
been mythic elements become a series of "McGuffin of the week", as we never
circle back to resolve why the protomolecule was created, why it was sent to
our ancient solar system, why it turns people into nuclear-powered zombies,
and what force destroyed the protomolecule creators, and why? And that's just
series one's unresolved elements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, lacking that, what the Expanse has to offer is its superlative
world-building and sane, believable depictions of a gritty interplanetary
future. Which is no small feat - arguably nobody else has done it better. But,
for me, it isn't enough. Maybe that's just because I'm a godless heathen who
looks to get my spiritual fix through TV shows about spaceships. Or maybe it's
because science fiction is where we show ourselves what we're capable of, what
to aim for, and I believe we can aim higher than just exciting technological
dystopias.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>fiction</category><category>media</category><category>science-fiction</category><category>tv-show</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/the-expanse/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 08 Apr 2022 19:42:40 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Battlestar Galactica: Series 3</title><link>https://www.tartley.com/posts/battlestar-galactica-series-3/</link><dc:creator>Jonathan Hartley</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="https://www.tartley.com/files/2007/07/starbuck.jpg"&gt;
&lt;em&gt;"It's gonna be OK."&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's the new "reimagined" version, Dad. I don't really do much
television, and for 2006, downloads of Battlestar was pretty much the
only exception. It's edgy and well-written, and it leaves me
breathlessly excited, and yes it had that lull on New Caprica about five
episodes in, but then it blossomed again, experimenting with one-off
shows, cool ideas, and great characters that remain emotive and
involving while staying well clear of Dawson's Creek. And what a series
finale! Blowing the whole stack of Cylon sleeper agents all at once, the
awful yawning realisation as they each heard the activation signal in
the back of their minds, all drawn to converge on the same room, what a
headfuck, with the psychedelic nebula backdrops all around, to the
rising strains of &lt;em&gt;All Along the Watchtower&lt;/em&gt;, as Apollo discovers
Starbuck is still alive. Hooray! Loved it loved it loved it. 8/10.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>fiction</category><category>media</category><category>science-fiction</category><category>tv-show</category><guid>https://www.tartley.com/posts/battlestar-galactica-series-3/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 22 Jul 2007 06:27:36 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>